All right.
In this lecture
we're going to talk about what problems
microservices actually solve.
And we're going to do the corollary
to that as well.
And find out what problems they introduce.
So let's first start
by what problems do they solve.
We need to understand which problems
are geared more towards microservices.
We need to recognize what they are
and if they're a good fit.
And we need to be aware of key
risks and trade offs.
Moving to a microservice architecture.
So first off microservices in contact.
We we hear this all the time.
Hey we need to scale use microservices
or we have legacy code
rewrite them as microservices.
Hey we want to be modern.
Let's go to microservices.
But they add a lot of complexity.
So just because it's the flash
in the pan thing that's going on right now
doesn't necessarily mean
that you really want to do it.
You got to look at what the trade offs are
in any architectural design that you do.
You need to understand
what specific problems that they solve
and whether you have those problems
and whether you want to move
to that or a simpler
alternative like modular coding.
So a quick definition.
So a microservice architecture is a system
composed of multiple small services
that each focus on a single responsibility
or capability.
They're independently deployable, often
have their own database or schema
services, communicate over network
protocols, either
Http rest, gRPC.
0IO sockets.
Yeah, there's a whole whole bunch of
different protocols that it can talk over.
There's some standard ones
that we're going to use.
In, in these lectures
that you're going to see, but
you can use any of the protocols there.
And it's typically owned by one team
if its services can't be changed
and deployed independently,
you don't have a microservice,
you have a distributed monolith
and not microservices.
I have created distributed monoliths.
I see them all the time.
So you need to make sure that you are
actually doing true microservices here.
All right.
One of the big problems that it, help
solve
is the slow delivery of a huge codebase.
Remember, monoliths
means I've got a huge code base.
Every feature touches one application,
right after I split, right?
I have individual services
that are being built and deployed
independently of each other.
So some of the things that it can do
is it can decrease your build time
dramatically and your test time
dramatically.
Merge conflicts become easier
because it's not one
big, huge
codebase of 5 million lines of code.
It's a small microservice, right?
That has a small amount of code
that I'm doing merges with.
Also, you can isolate the changes
from the different modules, more easily.
Right.
So this gives clear
responsibility on who's in charge of what
and what the services responsible for.
And enables massively parallel development
without constant conflicts.
I used to be a, build meisters,
what we call ourselves
back in the day, in the 90s of a massive,
monolithic, code base,
10 million lines of code,
and our build time took 21 days.
You heard that right? 21 days to build.
So merge were huge, big deals,
doing merges and all that stuff.
We by the time I left there
in a two years, we got that down
to 24 hours and we were happy as clams
with 24 hour turnaround time.
So big monolithic
can have a lot of issues with it.
And that's another option to move
to, microservice architecture.
All right.
Let's look at another one
coupled release cycles.
Now this this is really
when I'm shipping a feature.
And it could be in a modular system.
But I end up having release
chains and change freezes and coordination
between the different modules,
which says that I've got a microservice,
I've got modular
that has coupling, between them, either
because there's tight integration,
through the API, or they're circumventing
the APIs directly,
which I have seen and done myself.
Microservices can allow for independent
deployments per service,
letting teams ship on their own schedules.
Right.
And it can enable small, infrequent,
safe releases.
And we've seen this before.
You have to make sure
that you have backward
compatibility on your APIs
if you're changing the APIs.
Otherwise
the independence is completely fake
and you end up with unseen
dependance, between, the microservices.
So you have to watch out
for that sort of thing.
You need to architect your microservices
so they can handle changes to the API
and that they're additive,
or that they, can fall
back to an earlier,
version if, if required.
Okay.
Another problem.
Uneven, releasing
uneven scaling and poor isolation.
So scaling problem
if I've got a big monolithic code,
some parts of the code are used a lot
and other parts are sitting there idle.
Even if I'm using multithreaded,
I run into this issue.
Monolith forces you
to scale everything at once.
So I had to scale the whole application
all at once.
That could be a problem.
I also have isolation.
I can't isolate symptoms of problems
because everything's kind of hashed
together with microservices.
I can easily find out where thing
where the problems are
and isolate the microservice
that's causing the problem, right?
I can even downgrade gracefully if I need
to, in order to keep things running,
but maybe even at a segregated,
service level agreement.
Right.
Other
things that microservices can help with
is I can scale the services independently.
I can provide process level isolation
if required.
And I can, do for poor,
port forwarding gracefully to handle
degradation and timeouts and callbacks.
And I can scale independently without
without good
resilient
patterns, though failures can now cascade.
And we've seen this
with microservice architectures
in the cloud service providers
where we've had cascading failures
with one microservice
and everyone highly dependent on it.
So you have to have good resilient
patterns.
You have to look at the whole system
architecture.
All right.
Another one is check and schema lock in.
So, one of the biggest problems
that we have with mainframes
and moving off of mainframes
is a tech lock in COBOL.
Right?
And it's not normally a big
monolithic application sitting on its own.
It's a whole bunch of other small apps
that were developed around it
that are all sharing the same schema,
which basically created
a big monolithic
or distributed monolithic masses.
What you got spaghetti for, right.
So understanding, the schema
and the tech lock in is important.
If I'm locked into a schema
where all the microservices
have to use the same schema
and they can't migrate independently,
I just created another monolith
and just a distributed monolith, right?
True.
Microservices lets
you use different languages
for the different microservices,
let you modernize incrementally.
Also I can change the,
type of database
maybe I have on the back end
and I can even change schemas without it
affecting,
other, microservices.
Okay.
Another big problem.
And we saw this in Conway's, law.
If you haven't listened to that lecture,
go check it out
and that's misaligned boundaries in teams.
So this is when, teams are constantly
in the same code areas
or a feature comes in
that is spanning multiple microservices
need changes or,
I don't know who owns the code, right.
For that microservice.
Then I know this is, a problem
that I have.
You find this in monolithic, modules
or modular monolithic
as well as in monolithic
as well as in microservices.
What people think they've done
as a microservice, where they really have
a modular monolith, right?
Or distributed monolith. Right.
So watch out for those sorts of things.
If you don't have good
boundaries on your ownership.
All right.
What microservices can't do automagically.
Right. They don't fix stupid.
I hate to say it that way
or poor engineering practices.
So if you have bad domain
modeling and unclear requirements,
it won't fix that for you.
If you have bad engineering practices,
it won't fix that for you either.
It may, it may, expose it
earlier on in the development cycle.
But if, it may actually hide it as well
late in the cycle.
So it'll catch a lot of things up front,
but some more,
nuanced, coupling between, microservices
are not found until, once you go way
past, deployment a lot of times.
So you got to watch out for that.
Also, it does not fix performance
problems, without good
architectures and good algorithms
for queries and things,
it, requires more observability.
So you gotta put that in.
That's more work.
You have to do.
And it does not fix organizational
dysfunction or misaligned incentives.
They amplify all of these things.
So the good news is, is
you'll find these things, more readily.
They won't be hidden for years.
But bad news is,
is hopefully you find them early
instead of late in the development cycle.
All right.
There are some costs
to working in microservices, right?
If you've got a very large team,
microservices allow you to very easily
segregate, your teams into, easily easy.
Ownership of certain modules
or certain microservices.
Right.
Reasonable
domain boundaries are great for that,
but you need to make sure
you have operational maturity,
meaning you have good Cicd,
monitoring,
traceability, secrets management.
All these are need to be mature
to take real advantage of microservices.
The cost you're introducing
are operational complexity,
distributed system issues like timeouts.
Debugging is much harder data consistency
challenges across multiple microservices.
And then it's harder to test and debug.
As I've already mentioned, there are
some frameworks out there that help,
but it is very complex,
especially if you're developing several
dozen microservices that are spanned
across a cluster of machines.
It can be very difficult
to, debug and handle timing issues.
Those tend to be the biggest issues.
All right.
In summary, microservices are great.
They can help with a lot of things.
They can help, with detangling
large code bases and segmenting them and
enforcing some good engineering practices.
You do have to look for,
coupled release cycles and coordination
overhead that you have,
it can handle uneven scaling,
and the need for a better isolation.
You can handle those with, microservices.
Really well, you want to avoid,
tech and schema lock in.
And if you want true microservices,
avoid the schema lock in.
I see people do this all the time
where they create a schema
that all the microservices are using.
It's like, oh, but you've just created
coupling between them
and you created a distributed monolith,
so you don't want to go that route
and make sure that you, have aligned
your microservice architecture,
with the system and team boundaries.
Right?
These are all important things to look at.
Remember, you're adding complexity
and cost, but you're getting some gains.
So anytime you make architectural
decisions, you've got to,
understand
the gives in the takes on either side.