All right.
We're going to talk in this lecture
about load balancing strategies.
So the reason we have load balancing
is because I want to be able
to take requests coming in
and spread those across multiple instances
of the same microservice.
Let's say it's an ordering microservice.
And I want to handle orders
as they increase,
because I want my business
to be successful.
So I know that I have
if I just have one microservice instance
that's handling 20 10,000 orders,
it's not going to handle it.
I'll start getting some delay.
That may delay that the user
will go to a different website.
So I want to be able to scale
and add as many instances as I need to
on that back end and and make sure that,
I'm spreading those request across
all those different
instances of that microservice.
Now, there's different techniques
in spreading those things out.
And we're going to talk
about the difference between a layer four
and a layer seven approach on that.
And then we'll talk about some common,
routing algorithms
and using health checks and draining
and things like that.
Okay.
All right.
So the idea here is that I'm distributing
my traffic, those requests that come in
across a set of microservice instances
of the same microservice.
Right.
And we already talked about this
improves availability
throughput and enables horizontal scaling.
That's what horizontal scaling
is where I'm spinning up new instances
of the same microservice
it supports also roll out
deployments as I have new updates
to those, order servers.
For example, I can update some of them.
And as I'm, I could,
I can process through the whole thing
without having any downtime,
which is a great way to go
because it gives me that ability
to do rolling deployments.
Also, I can remove unhealthy nodes
if I have unhealthy nodes
that maybe they need a reboot
or a patch or whatever.
I can distribute my load across
multiple machines this way.
Also, it removes any hotspots
or overloads on individual machines.
Okay, so the difference here.
Let's talk about layer
for layer for balancers connections.
So this is down at the TCP level
in the network stack.
So it's going to handle network traffic
specifically at that lower level.
So I have connections
I can have multiple connections to a load
balancer that anytime we get something in
it just goes to the TCP port and rotates
through those ports to from the,
the load balancer itself
layer seven is on handling
Http requests at the application layer.
So with this
I can do a better job at saying,
given this route, I can route it
to this specific type of microservice,
and I can
even look even more into layer
seven at not just the routes,
but I can also look at maybe
parameters are being passed,
and I can segment that across
different microservice instances
of microservices that can handle different
types of a data coming in as a request,
which is really kind of interesting
because that gives me a lot
more flexibility at the application layer
at layer seven than it does at layer four.
Okay.
So this is another way to look at it.
I've got a client.
He's making a request
into the load balancer.
If I have a layer four load balancer
all it's doing is spinning up
by it's it's connecting
via a route connection policy.
That is based off of the,
the TCP IP packet itself.
And this is really good.
To use this, if I have the exact
same application on the back end, then
my policies are really easy,
and I just I'm just spreading it
across all that whole back in there,
all the same instances.
That's an easy one.
Otherwise
your layer 4th May have to do a little bit
of negotiating,
of looking at the packet and deciding
which application or microservice
instances it's going to, leverage.
And that could take a little bit of time.
So you got to take a look at that. Right.
But the key things that it looks at there
tend to be connection
stay the protocol being use the port
and an IP address typically.
So that's some some tricks
you can play layer seven
as we talked about before
this is application layer.
And decisions can be made off of host.
The path the method headers cookies
query strings.
Because I have access
to all of that. Right.
So I could route
the requests come in into different
sets of microservice instances
based off of any of those criteria,
which could a means
for some really interesting
optimization and load
balancing across, your applications.
I think I
talked about some of those
in another lecture,
where the algorithm becomes more complex.
Where I can have,
I can route things based off a query.
For example, let's do address lookup,
and I have the zip code in there.
I could have the zip code
go to a micro, address lookup,
microservice for all the zip codes
and start with zero, for example.
And all the ones that start with one
go to a different one.
Now all the ones that start
with to go to a different one.
You could do that. Right.
That's that could be a very interesting
algorithm depending on the type of load
that you have.
But the most popular load balancing
algorithm out there is a round robin
which says I've got 1000
going to hit the first one
with the first request,
the second with the second request,
and so on
and so forth, through through all of them.
There's some downsides to, round robin,
you know, especially
if the microservices are not running
on all the exact same hardware.
I could overload one server
that may not have as much power.
Another one, and I could be starving
another server that has more power,
that I could do a lot more work.
So one trick to to get around
that is to have weighted routing.
When I've got uneven capacity, let's say
that I've got my microservices running on
a, first gen Z on chip and a fourth
gen Z on chip and a sixth gen Xeon chip.
I'm going to weight
those differently, right.
Because the sixth gen can handle
a lot more than normal.
Gen one
and the Gen four can handle 50% more.
So I can have weighting on here.
So now when round robin comes through,
it's waiting things and saying,
all right, for every, ten instances,
Xeon one gets one,
Xeon six gets,
you know, six, Xeon four gets three.
Whatever the case may be, I could do
I could do that.
Another trick that you can say
is these connections for bursty traffic,
maybe I have some jobs that are running
or some requests
that are running out there
that are taking up
a little more time than I thought.
I can look at the number of connections
that I already have on
individual microservices
and route to the least.
Connections
to handle any of that bursty traffic.
There's less latency for performance
focus, there's hash based for affinity
needs.
That's that's putting in the concept,
reading that query string or header
to do that.
And, and this is really,
a lot of really cool things here.
The good thing about, about this,
most of you are never going to write
a load balancer or an algorithm
to do this, because most of the time
round robin is good enough,
which is amazing when you think about it.
Okay, so
but engine X, which is a load balancer,
allows you to do weighted,
which is really easy, easy to do.
I have my server pool here.
As you can see in the example, and I just
put weights on them and it's that simple.
So almost all of the load balancers
have some ways of configuring things,
and also allow you to add in your own
scheduling algorithm in into them.
And it will call that.
And then you pass in which
which one of the servers you're going
to connect to or microservices,
you're going to connect to said simple.
Okay.
There's also another way of doing load
balancing, which is on the client side.
Now typically you don't want to do this,
but if you don't have a load
balancer,
there's no shared load balancer here.
This can be somewhat useful,
especially for smaller applications or
it's an interesting way to go.
Let's just put it that way.
But the client must track the health
of all of the microservices
that it's going to attach to
and then do retry.
So basically
all you've done is you've moved
the load balancer up into the client code.
Right.
We can use this
for internal service calls.
But it requires
consistency, in discovery as well.
Which means now
you've got a client in a server,
and the server needs to notify the client,
when things are happening,
and you could overwhelm your client,
so you got to watch out for that.
But, and, yeah,
you could amplify the blast
radius if something happens, right?
All right, so all of a sudden,
I've shut down everything,
so this this could be an issue,
but you can use back off
and circuit breaker, techniques
to make it more resilient.
Most of the time, I suggest to people take
the hit on a little bit of complexity,
put a load balancer in there
instead of trying to do it yourself.
I have done this where I've done it myself
on the client side,
and it's really cool because there's less
microservices running.
But when you go to debug it, it is a pain.
It is really a pain
is better than pruning.
It's it's all so kind of talked
about these trade offs already.
Scalability.
This does allow horizontal scalability
but got load balancer in the middle
is adding one more on network hops.
So if I do that that means that
I could have higher latency.
There's some latency that I got to deal
with, which means there's additional cost,
there's
additional complexity,
and there's operations I've got to handle.
Observability is required for this
fine tuning.
If you do your observability right,
you can auto fine tuned things.
And as,
you're looking at your load balancer
and things are very dynamic
in these systems.
So you'll have the ability to add
and remove instances,
dynamically, through the load balancers.
Okay.
So remember
don't forget to do health checks.
Make sure your health checks are quick.
Don't.
If someone asks you for a health check,
don't go out and say,
I'm going to grab all the system
resources.
I'm going to run some special AI algorithm
to determine how healthy I am.
That's too slow, right? You need quick.
I'm alive
and I'm running five jobs right now.
Something simple. Quick.
Enough for the load balancer algorithms
to do what they need to do, right.
And watch out for sticky sessions
without any real need.
Right?
Because as I do load balancing on the back
end, I've got to share those sessions
between different instances
of the same microservice right.
Make sure that you
drain your, connections
when you shutting things down.
You can leave sockets
open, can cause problems.
You also want to make sure
that you have your weights across
different zones appropriately set up
if you're using a weighted algorithm.
Right.
So using engine acts or there's
lots of them out there, using any of them
out of the box is probably good enough.
For what? For what you're going to do.
Most of the time,
but realize that it's there
if you need to change and
fine tune your performance.