Okay.
In this lecture
we're going to cover OAuth and Oidc
and what they are,
how they build on top of each other
and how to use them and and look at all
the risks and tradeoffs
in, using these in your design.
So the key thing
that we want to understand here
is that why we would need a loss
and oidc in the first place?
A lot of times I've got server to server
interactions that need to carry with them
user information.
And specifically you let the user log in
and then the backend
has to act on behalf of that user.
And so I need some way of delegating
that access across the back end,
which becomes really important
as the number of microservices increase.
You don't want just blanket microservices
accessing whatever,
there needs to be context in scope
a lot of times, and a lot of times
our scope is tied to the user
that's, logged in, that needs
specific information and things like that
without a standard there.
Then what we end up having is passwords
that are shared across multiple apps.
Or each app rolls its own login session
model.
It's hard to centralize a bunch of it.
So coming up with a common way of,
authorizing and identifying is
is really important.
And that's what OAuth two and Oidc does.
So first off, Oauth2 is a framework
for delegated authorization.
So application X can call application
or API y for user Z.
Within the scope that it's gotten.
So it defines roles, tokens,
grant types, things like that.
It does not define identity.
It just identifies,
the roles, the tokens, the grant type.
So open a OpenID connect
sits on top of OAuth two.
And it shows you who the user is
and where they login from.
So it gives more identity.
It adds ID tokens,
user informations and discovery.
So it extends OAuth 2.0.
So think of OAuth 2.0
is kind of the framework.
And OpenID connect has more data
enriched data on top of that framework.
So that's the easiest way
to to think about the two.
So core roles
in OAuth two I've got a resource owner.
So someone that owns
some data on the back end.
Right.
I've got a client that's an app that's
requesting access to the user's data.
They're back in data through.
And it could be a web app.
It could be a single page application,
a mobile, another service.
Whatever the case may be,
they don't have an authorization server
that authenticates the user.
It issues tokens to the client.
It handles
what we normally see with authorization.
Do I have a resource server?
It's an API hosted protected server.
Resources on the back
end, it validates the tokens
and enforces authorization.
So real easy
a resource owner will talk to a client.
It's using the app in the client,
whatever the case may be.
And it wants to access something
on the resource server
on the back end before it does
that it goes to the authorization server.
And then I get a callback,
to the, resource
owner that says you need to authenticate
and consent access to this.
Right.
And then it will do that,
and then it will put
that token back into the request
back in the client.
And then it now has access to to it.
And you're going to see
if you've ever done a OAuth to workflow,
the kind of a little bit of a pain
because the client itself
has to have a callback, so that it can,
it gets tokens back that then it can
then create access tokens,
based off of the ID, so it adds that,
extra layer in into setting things up.
It's a little bit of a pain at first,
but once you get it running,
it works really well.
So tokens, we've talked about
tokens in other lectures,
but real quick I've got access tokens.
They're used for calling the APIs
and they contain
the reference in the scope
and the
I everything that you need in order
to, let that client do something
specifically on behalf of the user.
I refresh token is a long lived token
that's kept in the client,
and it's used to get access to new access
tokens.
The new access tokens are generated
when a user comes in.
I take that long live, refresh token.
I pass in the ID to the, OAuth server.
The observer then creates a new access
token for that user and that client.
Right. It's never sent.
The access token is not set or
the refresh token is not sent to the APIs.
Only the access token is right.
And then the ID token for
oh idk, this is a JWT
that's set up about the user, right?
So so it has the username
maybe authentication time,
ID and things like that.
So this is, this sits on top of that,
OAuth
two layer to provide a more standard
way of identifying the user.
Okay.
So what OAuth two is it's a framework.
And then and an authorization flow that
contains roles token types and grants.
It does not define the token formats JWT
with with OpenID connect really
does that part.
It does not define how a user
authentication is implemented just yet.
They have been authenticated and
how the identity identity is represented.
It's not part of the last two hours.
Two is all about authorization, not about,
authentication or ID.
We see that in open ID,
and connect.
And that's really where you're going
to see ID claims discovery
and user information.
Common grant types
that we see are authorization code
plus a PKI, for browser
based and native apps.
The user gets redirected
to an author authorization server.
They say, yes, I am going to allow someone
to work on my behalf.
The client then exchanges their,
code for access token,
as I've already mentioned.
And then, it's a
just a modern way of of securing those,
Securing those
interactions on those back end
APIs to, act
on the behalf of a user,
a client, a specific client.
Right. Different types of credentials
here.
I could do machine to machine credentials.
A client can, authenticate itself
to an, authentication server,
and then it gets that access
token has the client identity, right?
And that client identity includes
the user. Right?
If it's machine to me machine,
it will just return the client identity
and the identity of that,
possibly that device,
if you want to go that far.
Right.
So why do we need OpenID?
Connect or Oidc?
Because, Oauth2 focuses on authorization.
It doesn't focus on who's logged in,
and, standard way of identifying that.
So that's where open ID see shines.
Right.
It reuses the flows of OAuth two
and it has ID tokens.
User information discovery.
Any other kind
of metadata that's out there.
Okay.
So I've got an ID token and an access
token.
ID token is for client application.
Who the user is
when they're authenticated,
when they drop all that stuff.
And it's used to establish user sessions
so that the primary sits in the client.
The access token
also can sit in the client as well,
but is for calling back
end APIs and resource servers,
and it grants access to those resources
within the certain scopes.
And with, for that user
that you've already been identified.
So this is how the exchange works.
So I've got a user that says, hey,
I want to access this app with no session.
The client app will then, log
into the authorization, server.
It will pass back to the user saying,
hey, I need you to log in
and consent that this client application
can work on your behalf.
So the user then goes, okay, I'm
going to let you do that.
And then it redirects.
So the the user gets
that, that callback, once it does that,
it will
then exchange the token
with the authorization server
and the, credentials
that were passed in by the user.
And it creates a local session
in the client from the ID token.
Typically,
the access token will be in there.
And now the client can now call
the backend server on behalf of that user.
Because I've already created that access
token for that user with the proper scope
on what data can access
and what operations that can perform.
So it's important here that you understand
that we have architectural separation
between the authorization server.
That gives me a central way of authorizing
against multiple clients
and multiple backends, servers.
Right.
Your client, app
does not handle passwords or the directory
that's handled by the authorization server
or the authentication, gets called
and then the authorization server
says, yes, they've been authenticated.
So your client apps doesn't handle that
at all.
It just consumes the ID tokens
and manages sessions in that case.
And then the back end resources,
they validate the access tokens,
by by asking the authorization
server, hey, I got this access
token is a valid.
The answer is yes, it's valid.
And this is what you're allowed to do.
Then your resource server will
will enforce the scopes and permissions
on the back end.
Okay.
When when does this pattern fit?
Well, when I have multiple apps and API
needing that single sign on concept.
Let's say I have several backend services
that might be calling
third party services.
You're going to see a lot of third party
services.
You use OAuth two,
especially if you're limiting
the kind of data
that they're accessing on the back end.
If I want consistent token validation
across all my microservices,
this is a really good pattern
to use, right?
And also, if you can avoid handling
passwords directly in any,
native or single page applications,
that's a good way to go.
Let the authorization service, handle
that for you.
When do you want to move with something
simple?
If I have a simple app
with no external calls and seeing
limited scope, then is simple username,
password and session might be okay.
Internal only like non
user workflows,
API keys work pretty well for that.
But if you have user workflows
where a specific user
needs to be valid, then you should will
certainly do a swath right.
But also if you get this under control
and you using maybe a third party,
OAuth framework that's already there
and you start with this,
then it's not a pain to integrate it
later, which it can be a major pain
if you do this, post facto here, it will
require a lot of reworking of your code.
Okay, here's some risk and complexity.
It's powerful, but it can be complex.
So you can do indirect, incorrectly.
You could set up your scopes wrong.
You can have token leaks,
if you're storing those in the URL itself,
like in the query
parameters or logs
or even in the front end.
So sometimes, you can skip validation
if, you do it wrong and you don't want
those sorts of things right.
So use some of the vetted libraries
that are already out there.
There's great ones for almost every,
language.
It's out there.
Avoid any legacy flows like OAuth.
You need to look at OAuth two,
not just author OAuth.
And and set those up.
Always validate the signature,
when you're grabbing,
those, requests that are coming in.
Okay.
Another important thing is token lifetime
and revocation,
short lived tokens.
I have a lower impact
if things are stolen.
Right.
But they require
the refresh in the report.
So if you have a two short
like five minutes, you're going to be
reporting all the time.
If you do like 30 minutes,
I see a lot of external APIs
doing like a 30 minute ripoff.
That seems to be a sweet spot
for a lot longer live ones.
There's fewer round trips,
but if someone gets your, token
and they can go to town for a longer
amount of time, that's the only downside.
And then if you're going to go
full blown JWT,
they're harder to revoke
because they, you know,
they, they move around, and
you probably want to have shorter
lifetimes and increase
the refresh tokens,
the number of times that you refresh. So.
All right.
Front channel versus back channel.
So important front channel
is that client that the user is getting
in, is getting in.
That client
is acting on behalf of that user.
So when you setting things up,
you'll get some browser redirects and URLs
and career parameters
that are going to come in,
to the user browser
when they authenticate things,
the back channel is primarily
handled to server to server calls.
It's safe
for tokens and secrets on on the back end.
So on the front channel, use
very short lived codes.
On the back channel you can use
a little bit longer codes right.
So that those are some tips. There.
We talked about sessions.
You can store tokens in your sessions.
And in fact Oidc supplies
an identity token
that you can easily store
in your session on the browser.
Just be mindful
of cookies and Csrf, attacks.
So make sure that you, check out
the lecture on Csrf and how to avoid them.
And then, so just make sure that you're
handling, that all appropriately
and make sure you're handling your er,
contracts, appropriately.
If they're not authorized to do something,
you must throw the appropriate, error
in, in there and make sure that you're
handling that appropriately
so that you can give the client the,
the appropriate information,
because if they're not authorized to work
something on the back end,
then that's important
for the client to know that.
So it doesn't just keep retrying,
things over and over again.
Okay.
That's that's really it on OAuth two.
Like I said,
there's lots of libraries out there.
There's lots of great materials.
On how to set these up.
There can be a little difficult
at first to understand,
but once you get your head
wrapped around it
there, it's a very powerful,
architectural design pattern.