All right.
In this lecture I'm going to talk about
API keys, tokens and certificates
and the differences between them.
So the goal is to understand
what those differences are.
Explain each mechanism
an architectural level
and then recognize
when they use each coin.
And then identify
any key risks or trade offs like we do
in any of these architectural decisions
that we make.
So first, the most important thing is
to figure out where all these things fit
in, right?
So distributed systems
and microservice architectures,
remember
we have to first identify who you are.
We have to authorize
if you're allowed to do something.
And then can I trust it. Right.
Can I trust the connection that I'm
with as confidential and integrity.
And then there's different mechanisms
to do that.
API keys were the color
API keys are where the caller identified.
And it gives me course,
course access.
So I can say you're allowed
to do certain things with the API.
And each API has a set of keys. Right.
A token claims the identity
of an individual
or a, services coming in.
And the permissions
that they're allowed to do.
So. Token contains our identity
and the permissions
that they're allowed to do certain things.
And then certificates are secure
channels
where machine and service identity
and where they can exchange certificates
between, two different things.
So we'll go over these in more depth.
The key here is that
if I've got a, user action,
I'm going to say,
authenticate the user
so I know who they are.
Then I'm going to authorize
what they're able to do.
And that typically is all handled
in the API gateway.
That then communicates to the backend
services that I need to do the work with.
Okay.
Let's talk in depth about API keys.
So first it's a secret string
that's issued by a service to a client.
Now a client could be a person
or another machine.
Right.
It's sent on every request,
typically in the header
and typically in something
called the bearer.
And so if, if,
you want to access my service, I'm
going to give you a key that says, hey,
here's a key that you can always access.
That service.
So that's kind of how it works. Right.
So whoever has the key
can access the service to.
I know who they are.
I do not I only know that
they're using a secret string
that I gave them.
They're using a key that I gave them.
So if someone were to grab that key
and use it somewhere
else, I would have no idea,
what happened there.
So that's kind of how it works.
Okay.
There's lots of different types of keys
that are out there.
Typically, it's used for public and paid
APIs.
It's simple service to service type
of calls, scripts, classes, batch scripts.
These these sorts of things
all the time. These keys.
Right.
So that's where you have to be
very careful with your keys.
They should be stored in a secure vault.
Not in open text.
Sitting in your,
sitting in your environment
somewhere on file or whatever
the case may be.
Someone hacks your system now,
they have your keys and they can act as,
you, they can act
not as just as you, but they can access
any of the APIs that you've been given
access to with these keys.
Okay.
Some of the strings, they're very simple
to issue and to verify.
I give you a key.
It works in in the key in the
to unlock, the API.
So it's really easy to integrate.
It works,
without full identity in the system.
So it's very easy to do.
But there are some limitations.
They often act
like a password, for the API.
So if someone infiltrates that password
now, they have access.
They usually are long
lived with a broad scope.
I have access to your application
instead of individual microservices.
And it's hard to revoke keys. Right?
Once they're out,
I can change it, but then.
So they typically are long lasting
and there's no built in user identity
as I've already explained.
All right.
The best practices treat them as secrets,
scoped them per client or per environment.
If you can use least privilege.
So read only versus read right.
You should distinguish between the two
and support rotation and revocation.
If you can. Right.
Since you're architecting these systems,
you absolutely should be looking
for these sorts of things.
And also don't put them into query
strings.
Put them into the headers.
That's a preferred way to do it.
Okay.
So typically what happens for issuing
keys is
I have an API key store in my public API.
I look up the key, I check the status,
and then I go, yep, I gave that key out.
Someone came in with the key.
They have access to, the application
that I want them to have access to.
And there you go. Right.
So I issue the key.
They access the key, it comes back in
pretty straightforward and simple.
All right.
Let's talk about tokens right now.
Tokens a little bit different
because it has more information in it.
It's structured data
that's issued by an authorization server.
All right.
So typically this is going to be
another microservice sitting out there
that authorizes access.
Right.
So an authorization server,
it typically represents a subject
which is the identity of the user
or the client.
It has permissions in their scopes
roles, whatever
permission scheme
you decide to use and a lifetime.
When is it going to expire, when was
it issued and when is it going to expire?
This is all jammed into that token.
So all this information's in.
That token
when it's sent right is presented to APIs
as proof of authorization.
So I am authorized
to perform these things,
and it's all contained inside
at the bundle. There.
There's there's different options here.
The most popular is JWT, which is is
used in a lot of protocols out there.
But you can also have opaque tokens.
You can have your old things.
It's basically an encrypted string,
with all this stuff in it.
There's lots of different
techniques that you can use.
Okay.
Typical uses.
I'm sure you have heard of OAuth
two or Oidc.
Those are access tokens for APIs.
They're ID tokens for user identity.
And they're great for microservices
when user identity is important.
When I know who's accessing it,
maybe I'm keying off who's accessing it,
like in the order entry system
or in an inventory system where,
this user has specific, data
that they're allowed
to see, maybe their own waters
or maybe their own work.
In the inventory system,
when you have those sorts of things,
this is a good way to go.
Also, authorization is very fine grained.
I can, depending on your architecture,
you can pin this down to certain
types of data, certain rows of data
in a database, certain documents,
and certain
functions that can be performed
on, on the data, certain API
calls.
Okay.
Some of the strengths.
It has richer semantics than API keys.
As I mentioned before, a key I don't know
who's turning the key right in the door.
Right.
With tokens, I know who the subject is,
what they can do when the token was given
and how long it's given for.
So this really fits well into zero
trust architectures as far as time
based access is is critical for that.
They're typically short lived by design.
We're talking
maybe a half hour, maybe 15 minutes,
maybe it's a one time shot.
Right?
There's lots of different options
for this.
A lot of times
people will go send out tokens,
they'll they'll want a token that lasts,
you know, 3 or 4 days or whatever.
It all depends on what your application is
and how secure you want your system.
And the tokens are typically issued
centrally and consumed by lots of,
lots of different servers.
So I typically will have.
And I'll authorization service
that is generating these tokens.
And then also checking against them.
Hey, here's some of the, the risks,
and some good practices.
Bearer tokens.
Whoever has it can use it.
So that is another issue, right?
If you're not keeping, track,
but because,
they're time bound, you know,
you're not going to have
that key out there for a long time,
but you have to decide lifetime choices.
How long are they going to last?
If it's too long,
then you give access longer.
If it's too short, you're
spending too much time authorizing over
and over again, by hitting the OAuth
server and, and all this stuff.
Some good practices
keep the Tor token short lived.
You have to define what short lived is,
use scopes claims for lease privileges,
and then validate the issuer,
the audience expiry and signature,
and then protect signing keys
and rotate them regularly
because you're going to sign these tokens
and make sure that,
that no one can just generate
these tokens, willy nilly.
Okay.
Because that is another concern
if you don't rotate your signing keys,
if someone could figure that out,
they can start issuing their own keys and
and spoofing you and becoming, you,
very easily, very quickly.
Okay, so here's the high level flow.
A user will log in and, and access,
with an access request,
and then an authorization
request comes out
to an authorization server, server.
It will send back an access token.
Then the client application will then send
that access token in, through the bearer.
It typically
that's in the header of, of your,
https call.
And then I'm going to go and
check that against the resource server.
And if the token's good
then I can go ahead and give the response
back or, or run the application,
whatever the case may be.
So a little more than before.
Right.
Because I'm passing the token back
and then sending the token
in where before I get a key,
I just boom, get the key.
So you can see there's
a little bit of overhead involved here
that you have to deal with.
Okay.
Let's talk about certificates.
So the concept here is
that I've got a certificate.
It's digitally signed document.
It's it's tied with a bind public key
and an identity.
So, typically in the identity, it's
not just the identity of the person,
but probably the host, the,
the host that they, are accessing it
through an organization,
a service, whatever the case may be,
it has all that identity built in.
It's issued
and signed by a certificate authority.
This is someone outside of both the,
authority, service that you have
and the client stuff.
This is a third party that's saying, hey,
I'm going to issue these certificates.
And and so both people, our game,
that certificate from me,
right, is typically used in a https,
server certificates,
mutual TLS client server certs,
and it works at the transport layer.
So not at the application layer.
All right.
So it's I'm going to encrypt data
going across my transport layer.
So I'm going to have that concept
of that CERT certificate there.
Right.
The idea here is that
if you're given a public key
with the right identity,
you're able to decrypt
and get access to the data
that I'm needing at the transport layer.
Right?
Typically it's used to,
prove server identity.
Ever for example, both
software server
and also hardware servers as well.
We see that a lot.
It it's used also to encrypt
traffic between client and server,
authenticate services to each other.
So, I can authenticate.
You're a service or a server
and you're a server
and you know about each other,
you're using a third parties.
Say, I know about both of you.
You two can talk to each other
where before it was kind of one way.
I want to talk to you.
And you go, oh, I know who you are, but
what if the client needs to know that I'm
actually talking to the right thing?
So you don't want someone to spoof
you there?
So it's, it's
a, it's a very common pattern
that you see in high secure and server
to server, types of communications.
Right.
It's very strong,
well-understood cryptography.
It's independent application protocol.
It scales with automated cert management.
It doesn't scale well, is automated
because you're issuing all these,
certifications.
Right?
It's it's used in almost every public
server out there that uses agency types.
I have to have a certain cert, cert
in order to, run in that protocol.
So and that's typically,
creating certs through, a third party,
certification, service.
Okay.
Here's some operational concerns.
Insurance and renewal
and revocation, can be difficult.
And key rotation is another thing.
I've got to protect the private
keys that are generated.
I also have to make sure
I understand the TLS configuration
and versions,
and ciphers and all that stuff,
and make sure that I have
correct validation of those certs
as, as I'm coming through.
Right.
So those are some things you build in
more operational, capacity
to do that in your services that you have.
All right.
So it kind of works like this.
This is a typical TLS handshake.
A client says hello to the server.
The server?
The server sends back a hello cert.
It validates the certificate.
And then it says, okay, you are who you
who I think you are,
and then will exchange keys and secrets,
and then it will now, encrypt
on the server side.
The, the data that gets sent over
the application data is encoded
and the application data
is encrypted coming back.
So a lot of handshakes
going on there, but,
it is much more secure
than the other, methods that we use.
But more operational overhead.
Okay.
So let's compare the differences.
API keys are simple client identification.
Long live course scope tokens.
Rich claims, shorter lived central OAuth,
OAuth two or oh IDC architectures,
and then certificates are
primarily used for secure
channels, machine to machine identity.
And it's the basis for TLS and Https.
So the certificates you see
primarily used for attestation and
also for comms at the transport layer,
that's
where you primarily use them.
Okay.
Here's just another comparison table
that you should be looking at.
The primary purpose,
typical long, lifetime,
long lived for API
keys, short lived for tokens,
medium days or months for certs,
and then operational complexity.
The lowest is API keys, medium for tokens
and then higher for certificates.
But certificates are more secure.
All right.
So when you choose what this is
where you've got to use,
some intuition
and you've got to, play the trade offs.
How much is going to cost in CPU cycles
and your time.
Right. Who's calling? What services?
You could have, you could use all three
in the same architecture.
I've seen it before.
So you you got to look at that.
Do you have the ability
to rotate credentials as you need to?
You know, typically what we see in this
pattern is certs are used for transport.
Layer tokens are used for use your client
identity and authorization.
And API keys are typically used
for simple third party integrations.
But we're seeing more organizations
kind of move away from that even
because they're not as secure,
and they'll move into tokens instead.
For that.
Okay, what if an API token is stolen?
An attacker can call any API
they want and tell us is revoked, right?
If a token is stolen, the attacker can act
as a user client until expiry.
So that's where you want
a shorter, lifetime on those.
If a private key is stolen,
the attacker can impersonate a service
and decrypt track traffic all day long.
All right.
And that's one of the biggest concerns
with, like, quantum computing.
They can they can hack those private keys
that in theory,
that's that's what's going to happen.
All right.
Some things you can do to mitigate
all of these shorter
lifetimes, rotate
your keys and revocation.
So if someone's outside of,
the time frame revoke their key,
blow it
away, don't let it be there anymore.
And then make sure that you're
securely storing these API keys
and that you're monitoring,
what's going on?
Okay. That's it.
That's a lot to unpack
in this one lecture, but,
now you've got the information
you need to make good design decisions
for your architecture.