All right.
In this lecture we're going to talk about
how to take a program and slice
it and create service boundaries.
So the purpose is to take a monolithic
or large program space
and break it into discrete microservices.
This is part art,
part science, and it's called slicing.
And you typically base
it off of data flow and responsibilities.
Or if you go to like the object
oriented analysis and design models
that are out there, you can find
those boundaries pretty easily around
a package or a logical packages
and or classes themselves.
Model classes, this is another technique.
So those are some things to look at.
So outcome outcomes of this is that you're
going to know what program slicing is.
You identify natural service boundaries.
In the architecture.
And then apply those slicing
to domain models
and understand
the trade offs and risks between them.
There's lots of different techniques
to do this, and it all depends
on the program space that you're
working in on the best approach.
But there are some guidelines
that will give you.
And then you need to know what the trade
offs are, the pros and the cons,
and articulate those in your architecture.
Design.
So traditionally,
what a program slicing is, is
I simplify programs
just by focusing on a subset of behaviors
or behavior based.
So the microservices,
there's two ways of doing it.
Vertical slices of functionality
and separating concerns
for independent change.
And then you're going to shift
from horizontal slicing,
which we've seen a lot of,
and you see a lot of horizontal
slicing in monolithic programing
or in modular programing,
shifting that to a service
which is more vertical, which includes
maybe an, interface,
maybe even a web interface,
business logic and storage
all in the same microservice,
which is really fascinating
because it goes almost contrary to,
the way that we've done
modular programing in the past.
Okay.
So if I look at horizontal, right,
I got my UI
layer,
my business logic and my data layer.
That's monolithic, right.
Because I've got three different layers
and and I've seen people do this
I've done this myself.
I have a program I'm working on right now
that I've done this horizontal.
I my UI sitting out there,
I got business logic running
as a, as its own, application.
Then I have a data layer
that's running as its own application.
This is a distributed monolith.
Okay.
Vertical slicing says that, hey,
I've got a UI and API logic and data
all in its own little bundle,
and it's specific to catalog,
and I could have one specific to ordering,
and another one specific to customer
right.
Or customer care could be another one.
Right.
So it's a mindset that you have to change.
So finding the gaps and boundaries
this is really important right
to find where
those microservice boundaries should be.
Look at business capabilities first.
You know that's a good place to kind of
look and say, hey, I'm doing order entry.
Hey, that's a that's a business capability
instead of order management.
That might be too broad, right?
You can also look at data ship ownership.
And that might lead to a
an order manager.
It might I it depends. Right.
Depends on how you set these things up.
Also look for change in patterns.
And look for things that change together.
So if I change one thing
in one microservice and it causes
a cascading effect to other microservices,
then my boundaries are off.
So I've got a
I've got to figure that out
and then go back and look at Conway's Law.
We've talked about this
in previous lectures.
And maybe for your microservices
around the,
organizational boundaries
that you already have,
that might be a good place to start.
So find those gaps and boundaries.
This take this takes some investigating.
It takes some architecting, work
that you have to do, but
it will make your life a whole lot easier
if you find those boundaries first.
Okay.
Here's some of the
the issues, that we're going to talk
more in depth
about in other lectures over slicing.
I've seen this when people move to
of a pure function as a service.
There's a lot of network overhead.
And then you get distributed transaction
hell,
where I've got a transaction
that has to flow
through a dozen different microservices
in order to do something
that's, that's nano services.
And the overhead and managing
that can be very difficult.
And then I have under slicing, then
this turns into your distributed monolith.
Right. It's hard to scale.
I've got, you know, omnipotent services
that do everything.
That's bad. Typically.
Not typically always.
Right.
Or if I'm looking at that,
I have a lot of data duplication
where I'm copying data
a lot between services.
Then I can run into inconsistency
in my data models
and the, the
the problem
it just is, is really difficult to debug.
So in those cases, you may want to,
adjust your boundaries appropriately.
Okay.
Here's a really good example.
That's a pattern anti-pattern.
So in the real world
Amazon went from this giant bookstore
monolith that they had, and they had this
Amazon two pizza team rule,
which said, hey, if I can't feed
my team with, two pizzas
or less than the T, the team is too big
and they're doing too much information.
So you slice the,
you slice the problem space down
into where,
team of 60 people can handle it
without without issue.
Okay.
Now, this works really well
if you have an overarching architecture
that shows,
and controls coupling,
inadvertent coupling that happens.
And we've seen this, work very,
very well with AWS,
but at the same time,
without that overarching architecture,
we see major failures
and we see issues with coupling it,
averting coupling as these teams go off
and do their own thing without any guards
or checks on where their, their keeping,
with microservice best practices.
And we've seen some major outages
because these teams go off
and do their own thing,
but they actually, set up these
dependencies between lower level
back in microservices and create a web
that turns into a monolith,
distributed monolith.
So you got to be careful.
You need some oversight on these teams.
And, and these microservice teams
that are working out there,
you can't just let them run wild.
So it's a pattern anti-pattern.
All right.
For assignment one, the goal is to define
some logical microservice boundaries.
Make sure that it's a vertical slice.
I don't want to see horizontal slices
in there.
Avoid creating those horizontal slices.
If it's just a database wrapper that is.
That is not good, right?
All you've done is created a horizontal,
which really turns into a distributed,
like, a distributed monolith,
not a microservice.
Remember, microservice
needs to be able to stand on its own.
It can run and work all on its own,
even in the user interface.
There are techniques
you can use to serve up individual,
components and elements
for that individual microservice
into a, a
in, into a framework
that can serve up multiple
user interfaces
from different microservices as you need.
So take a look at those.
Okay.
Remember
find the right scenes in your application.
Find those boundaries.
Slice
vertically along business capabilities.
The best that you can and then aim
for high cohesion and loose coupling.
Remember, the goal here is a microservice
can be autonomous at stand on its own.