All right.
In this lecture
we're going to talk about circuit breaker
and bulkhead design patterns.
Now it's important to understand
what a circuit breaker does.
And bulkhead does with respect
to microservice architectures.
We're going to talk about that
in this lecture
where explain why cascading failures
happen.
We're going to identify breaker states
and thresholds and what to set those out.
And we'll also describe what a bulkhead
and bulkhead isolation means.
And then
when to apply each one of these patterns.
And of course the pitfalls and tradeoffs
of doing it like we always talk about
in these lectures.
So first all circuit breaker, basics.
So a circuit breaker actually protects
upstream services
from failing, dependencies.
So if I have an upstream service, service
a that depends on service B,
and service B is locked up
or it looks like it might fail,
I fail fast.
Instead of waiting for a response,
comes back.
I come out of resource whatever I do a
fast fail instead, which frees up service.
A to go on and do its behavior
that it was doing before.
So this prevents like,
errors in service B or service
B depends on the service C from cascading
all the way up through the things.
Instead I get a timeout.
Instead I get, an error right away
instead of it just sitting and blocking.
Right.
The key states to a circuit breaker
that you should have are closed,
open and half open,
just like a normal circuit breaker.
If I get overloaded, I throw the breaker.
The power shuts off
and saves things from catching on fire
or exploding or whatever
the case may be, or locking up completely.
And that's
what we're doing with this half open means
that, probes are allow for recovery,
but I'm not taking any more requests.
So it's like
you can do a health check on me,
but I'm not going to take
any more requests right now. Right.
So that's the concept behind, and these
work really well with short timeouts.
They're best with short timeouts
so that I, can't combine
with the circuit breaker.
I can easily
get back to a well known state
right when the breaker is open.
It means I can take,
I can take, requests coming in.
And it also means that I can also send,
errors back appropriately.
I also need a fallback position.
So I need to know what to do in case I do.
Kid a circuit breaker.
And I get that back.
I need to know on the client side
and also on the server side,
what my fallback position is going to be.
Right?
That's why we use that half open as well.
So I can still have some observability,
and see what's going on.
With the health of the system
that gives me some observability
that I can automate,
some things to do, like kill the server
or service and, and continue
on spinning up another one.
Whatever the case may be.
Right.
Another thing that you want to avoid is
don't aggressively retry in an open state.
Right.
Because you could end up
in a race condition that you want to do
treat the, the breaker state
as a US, signal.
Right.
That's a good way
to think about it, because everything is
asynchronous under the covers.
So this is what it looks like in, but,
sequence diagram that we have here.
Client sends a request to service a,
I call a request under
the needs to covers service
B, which has a circuit breaker
inside there, right.
Or it could be just a dependency on
an external resource,
like, the, file system or something.
Right.
I'm going to call that dependency
through the circuit breaker.
The circuit breaker is going to forward
the call on to like the file system
or whatever it gets. The response back.
All right.
I'm closed at that point
because I'm not going to take any more.
And the response comes back,
I can open and and I'm good to go.
If I'm in a closed state
and I get a request in,
I can fail quickly with the fail fast
fallback.
I mean, that's
the idea of the circuit breaker.
If another request comes in and I'm saying
I can only take one request at a time,
I can fail fast, possibly service a can.
Then I request some, requests,
another resource, or actually send it
all the way back to the client and ask it
to hit another service for the same.
For the same information.
Okay, here is an example
of what it looks like in Node.js.
So I have a class that's called
Circuit Breaker that I can create.
And the key elements that are in here
that I have are the state,
the number of failures, a threshold on
the number of failures, reset timeouts
and things like that.
So on this one,
I have a failure threshold of three.
Once I hit that failure
threshold of three, the circuit breaker,
goes to a closed state.
I also have a method here called exac.
So, the exact method here
is just handling the state.
And then we'll call
whatever was passed in, to the exact.
So it's like a, it's like a proxy
to a function
that's, that's going to be running.
Right.
And in here you can easily see the state
when the state is open.
I'm going to go go ahead and,
hit my fall fallback
when the state is closed.
I can go ahead in and do a
I got that backwards.
When it's open, I can access it.
When it's closed, I get, I get the,
Get the the fail quickly.
Okay. So that's the Node.js.
Let's take a look at go.
Same sort of thing.
I have a structure here where I store
the state, the failures, the threshold.
And then next time
I want to try and it's a proxy call here.
So I'm going to check the states,
see what I'm allowed to do.
And if I'm allowed to do it,
I go ahead and do it.
And I count how many failures I have.
If the failures are there, then
I switch the state appropriately, right.
So you can see the circuit breaker
is kind of in the middle and intercepting
any of the calls
to the underlying resource.
Okay.
So that's the circuit breaker.
Let's talk about bulk bulkheads.
So a bulkhead isolates resources
per dependency or features.
So where a circuit breaker
is all resources,
the bulkhead is like,
hey, I'm, I'm going to isolate
the resource to the specific type
of requests coming in.
It prevents
noisy neighbors from starving each other.
And you may even with a bulkhead,
you may even start
a new thread that just handles
those types of resources.
And, you're going to put a bulkhead
with probably
a circuit breaker on it for each bulkhead,
which could be pretty cool, right?
So, that's that's one of the things
that you can design in your system as,
as you're doing it.
And this works really
well if you have very well defined,
requests that come in
that are hitting external resources
that, you know, could be blocking
and things like that,
the idea here is that you want to keep
the pools of those,
connections
or those thread pools, small.
So you're not spending all your time
managing threads, which could be,
kind of a pain.
All right, so
here's an example of a thread, pool
in, Python care.
And they do have, thread pools,
which is really kind of nice.
Where I've got my pool of threads,
I'm going to go out and use those,
threads
appropriately for the different types
of, calls that are coming in.
All right.
So that's, that's kind
of, the, idea behind, bulkheads there.
Right.
So make sure, though,
that when you, have your bulkhead
and you're using pools for that,
you want to separate the pool
per dependency that you have
so you don't get,
dependencies on these external resources
that can block each other.
And that will limit the damage
from slow services on the on the back end.
So let's say that I am accessing
another microservice on the back end.
I can set up a thread
to just go and talk to that microservice.
And another thread to talk to
microservice C or D, right.
So that's the concept behind it.
This this allows you to scale,
more effectively
and that your one service microservice
in the middle, is it, the same causing
all the back pressure on a pill,
or a stream, calls
to your microservice architecture.
All right.
When best to use this primarily.
You want to use this
when you have unpredictable latency
or or it's latency
that you do know what it is.
And it takes a long time,
but most of the time
it's going to be unpredictable, a latency.
And this can easily happen
if you have a lot of microservices.
And because the networks involved. Right.
And if you've got a noisy network, it
could take some time to get things back.
So you got to watch out for that.
You can also use it
when you've got one feature that, can,
exhaust shared resources very quickly.
That's another way of isolation.
If you need a safe degradation
or partial failure,
that's another way to do it,
because you've almost like taking
your microservice and split it into
into these different pools.
To do it, it's really good to handle high
volume traffic spikes that are common,
handle critical paths to stay responsive,
or require clear isolation boundaries
which could be if you're dealing, with,
secret or, encrypted type
data and things like that, or if you're
dealing with those sorts of things.
So that's another way to use
some of the architectural trade offs.
This is important to understand.
Scalability is one of those. Right.
Because now the isolation
improves resiliency.
But it could reduce any shared capacity
that you had.
Right.
Because if you have a set of
pool of threads out there
and you've only allocated
a certain number to a one bulkhead,
that could be an issue.
Right?
And reliability
could, be a trade off here too,
because you have fewer cascades but
partial feature outages could be common.
So you've got to be able to,
program to handle,
not getting all the information inspected.
Only part partial. Right.
Fail fast is quicker,
than this, like a short circuit
or a circuit breaker would be faster.
But fallbacks, can be limited.
So latency could be an issue,
using bulkhead.
But, that's something
you've got to determine, right.
What's your trade off there? Feel fast.
I know I'm going to fail faster or latency
because I'm going to spin up
other, other pools of threads
and things like that.
I could be blocked for a little bit.
The cost could be higher
because more pools or more,
queues increase the baseline capacity
of your microservice, which means maybe
instead of a one gig microservice,
you've got a five or 6 or 8
gig microservice running in the cloud.
I may need a bigger instance.
Things like that.
Complexity, is another issue, but
you're trading complexity
for all these benefits.
So these are the sorts of things
that you're going to have to weigh
when you're designing your system.
Okay.
One thing to also avoid some pitfalls.
Avoid one global, pool because that
negates the whole isolation concept.
If your thresholds are too low,
then you're going to create
a frequent opens, of new, threads.
That could be an issue as well. Right?
Because you're introducing overhead.
Make sure you don't miss any
the fallback, causes
and make sure you have the appropriate,
fallbacks when things fail. Right.
What are you going to do?
If you just have one catch all,
that might not be the right thing to do.
You may need to know why things failed and
and fallback appropriately,
and then make sure you don't ignore
the breaker
metrics because they can actually hide
instability there.
So put those in your observability
in your health check
saying hey, of of all of
if you're running like a 10
or 20% fail rate
on everything, that could,
that could be pretty high, right?
So you want to look and see why
that's happening.
Also, aggressive retries
can actually fight a circuit breaker.
And then you'll actually
get thrashing on your network.
So you got to watch out for those okay.
Breakers fail fast and bulkheads
isolate load.
Those are the two main
things you need to remember.