Okay.
We're going to talk about
er strategies and contracts.
That we're going to focus on how services
can represent and communicate failures.
Between each other or even between server
and a client or user.
Right.
So by the end you should be able
to explain what is an ER contract.
And you should be able to recognize
common error handling techniques
to distinguish between client server
and transient failures,
and then map errors to appropriate Http
status codes.
Right.
And then identify any risk and trade offs
in your ER strategies,
which we always try and do when we're
architecting these types of systems.
Okay.
Why do we need an er strategy.
Why not just use a try catch block.
Right. And and catch errors on. Yeah.
Well that's an interesting question
because you're dealing with microservices.
You've got things in the middle
on one thing in the middle is called that
network.
And the network has a tendency
to drop or delay or reorder requests.
The requests go in in different orders.
They can time out.
There's a whole bunch of things
that can go wrong in that API call
where if it's all in a monolithic,
you don't run into those issues
while you're all in the same memory space,
you're all in the same CPU.
You're not you don't have drop and delay
and reorder requests problems.
Right, are very, very rare
unless you're doing like
super API type programing,
but which we're not.
Do it right.
But with these microservices
you have a network in the middle.
So we got a we got to deal with
how do I handle er situations.
Right.
And they're inconsistent.
Everything's very asynchronous.
So I got to deal with this
in a different way.
It's very hard to debug as well.
So I need to make sure I'm
giving enough information.
If I have two microservices
talking to each other
and there's an error,
I need to know where the error is at
and and how to deal with it.
Okay.
So that's what an error contract is.
It's just a shared agreement
on how errors are classified,
represented and communicated.
It covers Http codes for Rest
and er body
structure, and client expectations on.
And whereas I'm going to retry
fix it or escalate it.
Right.
The goal here is to have predictable
actionable failures.
When something bad happens I know what
to do instead of just guessing.
Right. So it's,
it's kind of a way to do
try catch block across,
across a network
for no better way, way to put it.
It's a way of handling
the errors across the network.
Okay.
So here's some categories
and a very high level.
And Http support
says I've got client errors
where the client is sent me bad input
or it's an invalid state transition.
It's missing data.
Whatever the case may be,
that means it's the caller's fault.
We're going to blame it on the caller
on the server errors.
That's our fault, right?
I got bugs or misconfiguration
or unhandled exceptions.
Unhandled situations.
I didn't know about, and then I got
transient or environmental errors.
These are network timeouts,
partial outages, overloaded dependencies,
whatever the case may be.
So those are the three types transient
server client transient
or environmental network problems.
Right. Server.
My server code failed client.
He didn't pass in the right stuff
or you passed in the wrong stuff.
Whatever the case may be.
Okay, client errors.
The callers always have fault.
Not usually. Oh,
they're always at fault.
It's bad input or bad,
invalid state training.
Change.
Whatever the case may be
on the server side,
they aren't transient errors.
The server
errors, need to be fixed at the service.
Transient dependency errors.
Maybe I'm going to retry
or I'm going to back off,
or I have got limits
or fallback situation.
So that's how I handle server
and transient errors on the client side.
If I'm sending in the wrong thing,
then I don't want to retry
if I'm sending in the wrong thing.
All right.
So client errors
typically you're not going to retry on
it means you've done something wrong.
You got to rewrite your code.
Okay.
There are status codes that had FTP
will throw
all the 200 codes are success codes.
All the 400 codes are client error codes.
And the 500 codes are server errors.
So 200 success,
400 client side 500 server errors.
Right.
So the clients from these numbers,
they can infer a lot of times
the root cause of failure
whether to retry,
whether retry may help or not
by the 500 numbers.
If it's a 400 number, retrying
probably is not going to help you
as it's just not right.
That's a client error.
You've done something wrong.
It might help if
you've got some timing issues.
But, typically not right.
Typically you've got a client error and
someone didn't fill out a field, right.
Or whatever the case may be that
that you're sending information across.
Okay.
So here's here's a high level of some of
these are the majority of the codes
that you're going to see at 200 okay.
Successful.
And the body has the result
on whatever call you made
a 201 means I created something
on the back end in the server.
And I'm going to often
give back like a pointer.
I was calling it a pointer.
It's an
ID to the resource that you just created.
And then a 204 is a that was success,
but I'm not going to pass it back
anything because there's
no it was fully asynchronous.
You're not getting any information
back like a delete.
Yeah.
You said delete and a deleted.
Don't care write a 400.
These are client errors right.
It's a bad request.
You send in something
basic validation failed.
Maybe the wrong parameter
or a parameter that was required
wasn't sent in unauthorized meaning.
You did not have the,
it's invalid authorization.
So when you're setting up your security
and someone tries to access something
that's not authorized,
you should send a 401.
This is important, right?
Because now I know on the client side
I'm not authorized to do that.
I need to get authenticated.
So I maybe need to go back
and authenticate.
There's an opportunity on the client side
to really indicate and try again.
A 403 says forbidden.
You're authenticated
but you're not allowed to access that.
Done.
No bueno.
No good right can make that happen.
A 404 means it's not found.
Whatever resource you're trying to access
does not exist.
Right. So don't try it again.
That will be bad, right?
A 409 means
that you have a current state conflict.
Maybe you're trying to do something
out of order, and the server on the back
side says you're not allowed to
move from state aid to state B,
or maybe you're coming in
with a different version number
on the API call, and I can say, not good.
I'm not going to let that happen. Right.
And then there's a 422 which says, hey,
you gave me a bunch of stuff,
but I didn't like, the semantics of
of what was coming in.
You gave an ID, but it was just a number.
Amides have letters and numbers,
so I'm going to throw a semantic invalid.
So for 22.
All right.
So I'm validating it. It, it you know it.
He had all the right parameters
but it's not the what I expected.
So I'm going to send that back as a 422
and then a 429.
I get this a lot.
If I'm uploading a lot of stuff in an API.
Too many request. I've hit my,
my window.
I can't go beyond that.
Okay. Those are the client ones.
500 server side internal error.
The server caught it completely.
We broke. That's the generic we broke.
Typically
you're going to see a lot of that right.
You may also find a bad gateway
which is A502.
That means an upstream returned an invalid
or bad response.
I send something back through the gateway
and it said,
yeah,
you're not really allowed to do that.
So that could be a bad gateway.
And then I could get a 503, meaning,
hey, the server is overloaded right now
or it's down.
We want you to retry, okay?
Give us some time and retry.
Same with the 504.
The upstream didn't respond
in time. Right.
So you know I got a gateway timeout.
You can go ahead and retry on that one.
Give it a little bit of time.
So those are common codes
that you're going to see right.
We already talked about
405. And remember 400 are client errors
500 server errors
okay.
So remember those two treat
the 500 ones like I'm telling you
there's something wrong with the server.
Do not.
And we'll talk about this later.
Do not pass back.
Take, stack traces in your 500 errors
in the body,
which we're going to talk about here
in a minute.
Okay. I have the error codes.
Is that good enough?
Typically that's not good enough
in order to debug what's going on.
But it's good enough to know
maybe what my strategy is moving forward.
My fallback strategy was,
whatever the case may be.
So the stable error codes
are pretty much locked in.
Okay.
Then we want a human readable message
that helps debuggers, that helps humans.
Right.
And some genii
that are making these calls,
they can understand human language now
and then some details in there
that could be here are the invalid fields.
Here are details.
And that's typically in Json
or something like that.
Then there could be a correlation
or a trace ID
so that the client could possibly call
or when you're
debugging this I can see which trace ID
is, is calling on the server side,
maybe a session ID or whatever
the case may be.
And then I could also pass
in a retrial hint like,
hey, retry in five seconds type of thing.
The key is that whatever you do,
make it consistent across all the services
so that you're not guessing.
Oh, when I connect to this service, it
uses this, sort of information and when.
So don't do that.
Your error codes are going to help out
a lot, but make sure that your other,
body in your, error code
is, consistent as well.
Right?
So again, make sure that I have the status
in there, a structured er body.
Right.
A human readable, message.
And don't forget a correlation ID,
which could be a session ID,
whatever it is
that helps you see what's going on.
In, on the server side,
in the interaction with the client.
Okay.
Service to service, er, flows.
This is really interesting because you can
have one service propagate errors
all the way up to the client or decide
to retry and fall back on its own.
So if a client makes a request
and it calls downstream to service B,
but I get a hey, unavailable body error
service, a may say I'm not going to pass
that all the way up.
I'm going to try myself again.
So it's going to try and then if it tries
maybe five times or ten times, then
it will propagate that, up to the client
and say, hey, hey, we got issues.
You need to do something about.
So this is
a common service to service airflow
that you see,
I remember, when you,
are checking for like for
400 errors,
client side errors on the server side
that you are, validating
input at the API boundary right up front.
Don't wait
until you're halfway through something.
Validate everything up front
and throw your errors early.
And make sure that you're not processing
part of it
and you have to do a rollback, right.
It gives faster feedback to the user, less
downstream
load, and clearer client behavior.
Where sometimes it may get through, know
you want to make sure
you're checking all those required fields.
Right. From.
Map internal errors to a contract.
Right?
You've already established your contract,
right?
You catch internal errors early,
classify them as client server,
transient nap.
Those to the status
do not pass in stack traces, class names,
or any sensitive data.
Right.
You may you may do some of this
when you're debugging
because you go, hey,
I can look in one log to see that.
But a lot of times you forget to take that
stuff out and you end up with,
leaking your internal architecture
up to the real world.
Now, hackers have a way in.
They can understand
how you work on the back end better.
So be careful.
Those sorts of things. Right.
Transient issues.
You want a retry strategy
in their timeouts?
503 some network failures
use exponential backoff.
Plus a jitter exponential backoff says,
and I'm going to try right away
in maybe, second or two.
And then I'm going to try in four seconds,
and then I'm going to try
an eight seconds.
Then I'm going to try in 16 seconds,
give or take,
you know, a little bit, there
and then when I hit a certain,
threshold that I've established
on number of retries,
then I do a fail over a fallback, right?
Or I do a circuit break
right where I fail fast and downstream
and that the downstream is unhealthy
instead of flooding the network
with a whole bunch of traffic right?
Okay.
Only retry when the operation is safe
to repeat into potent.
We've talked about this before.
I need to make sure that if I do
call it again,
that it's not going to do something bad
on the back end.
Right. Explicitly designed for retries.
Right?
So make sure that you're checking
your state on the server side.
If someone retry something
like purchasing something
and you're failing on,
not on getting the money,
but you're failing on the inventory step
because you already got the money, don't
keep charging them over and over again.
That's a bad design, right?
If it's too risky to retry,
if you can't do
independent updates, right.
So be careful. Those sorts of things.
All right, Mark,
which operations can be retried.
In in your code
and then that that'll help you
to make sure that you're not making,
those kinds of, mistakes.
All right.
I can't emphasize enough
using stable, documented error codes.
Use the Http error codes, use
a common, detail payload
and error messages, human readable
error messages, and in for observability.
So if I have a session ID,
I'm passing through this whole thing
or whatever correlation ID,
make sure that those are consistent,
then I can check on those things.
This would be great for monitoring tools
like Prometheus or things like that,
and do not leak any internal, secrets.
Okay.
Be careful of overreliance
on retries. Why?
Because you can have
a thundering herd of outages as you
as you, completely a swamp.
The network with retries.
And that server is not coming back.
There's an error there.
And if you've ever tried to shut down
a microservice,
a thundering herd,
it is a nightmare, right?
Because, oh, all of a sudden
I've got all these retries going on
and maybe I'm, I shut down a service
and start up a new one and retry it.
You can get stuck in these very difficult
loops to,
to shut down and stop them from happening.
So make sure that, you're not masking
any deeper problems
on reliability on the back end
by doing this and mitigate your,
retries with limits
and back off and monitoring, techniques.
And I can't emphasize enough on
leaking your abstraction on the back side.
Do not return
low level database error codes,
internal hostnames, stack traces.
It it causes a lot of problems
with security
and tightly coupled internals.
It's hard to evolve your API, so there's
a lot of issues involved with that.
Make sure you put the right abstraction
layers as you're moving up through,
through things,
and make sure that you're consistent with,
your details in your error
and make sure you're using the IR
codes, correctly.
I don't overcomplicate things,
because that will over complicate
your client side, whatever it is.
Right.
So keep things simple and consistent,
okay?
Putting this all together
as a reference pattern at the boundary.
Make sure you validate inputs and return
clear 400 errors
on failure right inside the server.
Classify
your errors as server or transient
and and possibly client right.
And then map to the Http codes
and your IR body
that you've already decided on
for dependencies,
look at retries, fallbacks,
and circuit breakers
and then only where it's safe
and use it intentionally on that retry.
Right.
So make sure that it's safe
to retry an action.
Right.
And then for observability
and debug ability, use correlation IDs.
So if I have a flow
through a several microservices
I have the same correlation ID.
I can see what's going on,
with other tools that are out there
to help you debug things.
Okay.
That's it.
There's a lot there's a lot to do with,
error
handling in microservice architectures.
But if you do it right, it makes it much
easier if you're consistent.
So go out there and architect
a really good solution,
spend some time
coming up with those, document them
so that you can easily, work
through your debugging cycle.
In this.