Okay.
In this lecture
I'm going to talk about async patterns.
Kind of just a high level overview.
There'll be several follow on courses
for each one of these patterns.
But I want to let you know
what those patterns are and the benefits
over synchronous
and the drawbacks as well.
So we're going to compare
some of the common asynchronous
communication patterns.
We're going to choose async styles
by business need right.
And that's a that's a big deal.
So you can't you got to understand
the business side of things as well
and understand reliability requirements
on asynchronous flows
and recognize
any operational debugging trade offs.
In in using asynchronous.
So let's talk about asynchronous.
We already learn with synchronous calls
or blocking
type calls that I can end up with
a lot of issues.
Right.
One is coupling between,
coupling on performance
between one microservice and another.
So if microservice A is making a blocking
call on microservice B,
I'm blocked.
And if microservice B is slow,
that makes microservice a slow.
And there could be a cascading effect
with asynchronous.
I decouple that, request
I and what happens now
is asynchronous or microservice
A can absolutely continue to process,
even though it might be waiting
on something from microservice B
is just going to catch that later
on when it's done processing.
So microservice
A can continue to process, right?
So it absorbs a lot of that traffic burst
with, you know, queues and streams
and different techniques
that are out there and reduces that tight
coupling across the service boundaries.
And people are like, wow, this is awesome.
We should just be doing everything
asynchronous.
There are some trade offs
which I'll talk about in in a minute, but
eventually, it,
it does a great job
for like a long workflows,
but you now have to do some coordination
between the microservices.
So let's look at it
real quick. Synchronous.
The caller waits for full completion.
Then it can continue on.
So it's a simple control flow right.
Just like we're used to
with normal block programing.
Call this function wait for the response
and then continue on.
Right.
But that means there's higher
coupling and dependency latency here.
Right.
Doesn't handle burst tolerance very well.
Synchronous,
but easier to debug because a control
flow simple asynchronous.
The caller gets a fast acknowledgment.
I got what you sent me.
I'm going to work on it later. Right.
The processing finishes later.
I already said that.
And then better throughput under load
because I can
I can handle a lot of things, but
I have to explicitly track,
status of that, request that I sent in.
And I can easily overwhelm,
if I'm not blocking, I'm
just sending a bunch of asynchronous stuff
I can easily overwhelm,
a downstream microservice
with millions of requests.
And, I just keep sending them,
so I need some back pressure.
Concepts here.
Synchronous gives me automatic back
pressure. Asynchronous.
I got some different techniques,
so it's more complex,
but the benefits are pretty huge there.
All right.
So here's here's, five common
async patterns that we can look at right.
Fire and forget where I say
go do something.
And I don't care
if I ever hear back from you again.
Right.
Not my responsibility anymore
type of thing.
Then there's a queue
a plus worker consumers.
So this is where I'm using message
bus in the middle where
I'm publishing and saying,
hey, go do this work.
And there's a queue of work
that's out there
that's keeping track of all the work
that's being done right.
Another technique is to say request
acknowledge with the status endpoint,
which says, hey, go do this.
And then the microservice worker
microservice from microservice
B in this case would say,
I got your request.
Here is a, you are I right here
is a, a path
that you can check the status.
So then, sir, a microservice
A would then just
periodically pull the status
and things like that.
Right.
Then there's another technique.
It's very similar to that one,
which is a callback or webhook
or a topic.
You can use any of those, concepts.
And it's an async request
with a reply via, you know, a callback.
So what happens here, you know, in these
three different, types is I can say,
here's my request
and notify me on this RESTful
endpoint on my, on, my,
microservice microservice
A says, hey, make this request.
I'm going to make this request
microservice
B and microservice B, when you're done,
call me back on this endpoint.
Tell me that you're done.
Pretty straightforward.
Webhook is very similar to that.
And topic is similar to that too.
But instead of a direct, restful call,
you're now putting it on on a message pass
that I'm looking for.
Right.
And then another one is orchestration
with explicit workflow states
where I and this happens, a lot
when I've got multiple, microservices
working on stuff
where I'm just handing off,
the workflow to someone else to do.
And inside the package
that's being passed around contains
who's going to be notified of
what, when, how, and where.
Okay.
So let's take a look at order flow here.
Because order flow is very different
with asynchronous right.
Let's talk specifically about a
a request
and a response with back end processing.
Right.
So in this case a client submits an order,
to the order API, microservice.
Then the order API
microservice says, I got it, I accepted
the order, sends it back to the client.
The client can continue doing stuff
in the background.
What happens next is the order API service
then sends an event out on an event bus.
So I'm using event Bus here.
I'm going to publish
the order was created.
And then I've got a payment worker
and an inventory worker,
microservice
that are consuming that order, created
a message off the message bus
and doing its work in this state.
Here you can see I'm not showing,
but in the end,
when everything is satisfied, then
the final status of that event
would be sent back to the event bus
and then pushed back out
to whoever your order has been complete.
That goes back out to the order API,
which in this case probably calls
a callback or a WebSocket connection
back to the client saying, hey,
your order is done.
So but in the meantime,
the client could be doing other things.
During that time.
So that shows you a kind
of a real asynchronous, event going on.
You know, here are some things
you have to worry about.
Reliability of these things
can be kind of iffy, right?
Because I, I never get full.
I kind of fire it off
and I never receive back that it happened.
So if you do care that it happened,
then you may want to put a timeout
in the client itself that says, hey,
in five minutes, if I haven't heard back,
then I'm
going to assume that it didn't happen.
But we all know what assume means, right?
So I got to make sure that all the calls
and I'm making this way are important,
which means that it can handle
duplicate calls
to the same thing without creating
duplicate things on the back end.
Right.
So I need some correlation IDs in there
so I can trace, these distributed flows
because maybe somewhere in the flow
no one picked up that event which happens.
So I need to I need to figure out
what to do with that.
Or maybe it's partially done
and never finished.
So when that new call comes in, what am I
going to do with that partially run,
workflow that had to happen?
Do you even know where it is?
Right.
This becomes, you know, some orchestration
of things got to deal with.
Right?
So I need some persistence, some state,
which we always talk about.
I don't want my microservices
to have a state, but they do have state.
And that's something
I, especially in these types of things
that I have to deal with
and I have to be able to handle it
when, same request comes in again.
Okay.
Other things that you should look at,
if you're doing asynchronous,
you may have to beef up your API design
to handle
status and read, in endpoints or oh.
What's another good one
that you can do a response.
You know, something something like that.
So if you are using asynchronous,
you're they're handling those events
or you are opening up more Rest APIs
that can handle these more asynchronous,
hey, I finish what you asked me
to do type of things right?
Also, make sure that
you are publishing
what those events, could be.
And explicitly
say that in your API definitions,
if it's not a what I would call primary
kicking off something,
but kind of a response type of,
API, endpoint,
make a note of that, so that people know
don't call this directly.
Right.
Here's my forward facing,
rest API, and here's my response
kind of back in.
All right. So here's some trade offs
that we see here.
You do have better resilience
for burst handling.
But this is much harder to program
it because things happen out of order
all the time. Right.
And it's going to be really hard
to debug across these async boundaries.
This is where you get really good
at looking at distributed logs.
And because timing
is all kind of wacky here,
because you're not exactly sure
when things are going to come back
and how to handle them or in what order
they come back.
So you have to be
somewhat cognizant of that.
And when you are developing your code
that you are,
not writing sequential code,
you have to write asynchronous code,
or you have to write code
that can be entered in at different points
based off of the events
that are coming back.
So those are some things
you have to worry about. All right.
So to recap, async improves
some of the concurrency problems.
And decoupling a promise of dependency
but at a cost.
And you got to understand what that cost
is and when to use which one.