Okay.
In this lecture
we're going to talk about go concurrency.
And that's the language go.
If you didn't know all right.
So the idea here is
that we're going to explain
what go routines are
what channels are worker pools.
We're going to recognize the go
concurrency model
and how it can improve throughput
and apply
ization and boundary and concurrency
safely across, your, microservice.
Okay.
Now go.
Routines are lightweight concurrent tasks.
They're not as big as, like, starting off
a whole thread where it's like,
you know, it's a OS thread.
So they're they're very small.
They don't take as much resources as
a full thread, which is good news, right?
Channels allow me to coordinate work
across the different
go routines that I have or through
explicit communication.
Right.
So this is kind of like a placeholder
to a bucket where I can store
the information and I can communicate
between the different, go routines
that are running there.
Select lets me handle
multiple async events
and, and gives me, the ability to,
can, handle, the,
interaction between them.
And then context gives me cancel ization
and deadlines, for the individual tasks
that are going through.
Right.
And then I've got the concept of
worker pools which bound resource usage.
So if I have a worker pool I can bound it
to I'm only going to run ten of these
instead of 10 million of these or whatever
the case may be.
Now these concepts all build up
to this concept of concurrency,
which is a pretty good way of handling
these io heavy paths.
And concurrency
doesn't mean run in parallel
per se,
it means handle things in parallel.
And what we'll show
you what the differences.
Okay.
All right.
So let's talk specifically about
some of these like the go routine here.
It's much cheaper
than a full blown OS thread.
It's great for waiting on like, network
or disk IO.
It doesn't block the whole process.
So it's very similar to that promise
async and await type thing right?
Go routines.
I can schedule go routines
on many blocked or runnable.
I can have a lot of them running
at the same time.
Right.
Which is,
which is great because it mimics,
asynchronous city or concurrency
in that case,
it's go is really a strong candidate
for like gateways or aggregators
or event consumers.
So you could use this
in your architecture,
you could have some go,
app applications out there
and microservices written in go
that can handle these things, very easily.
All right.
So the mental model on concurrency
does it
does not mean make everything in parallel.
It's I'm going to split independent
waiting work into separate flows.
So I'm handling them in parallel.
It's not I'm doing the work in parallel.
That's the main difference okay.
So channels are used to coordinate the
handling of the results as they come back.
So I can have channels
that I can have a channel
sitting there
waiting for all this concurrent work
to get resolved,
and then come back into those channels.
And then you can use context and select
so that work can stop when,
it no longer matters when I'm selecting,
the tasks that I can cancel or whatever
or context can, I have cancellation
policies in there and things like that.
So that's the concept behind these things.
All right.
Let's take a look at, use of this.
One of the good uses of this is the fan
out fan in pattern that is out there.
So in this case, here I am.
I'm going to handle,
ordering something. Right.
So I have a request
come in that says, hey, I want to order.
I want to order, this product
and I need to hit the inventory
microservice, and I need to hit
the pricing microservice.
So in this case, that handler
will will call a fetch inventory
and a fetch price as go routines.
And those go routines will go out
and do that stuff
and put their results
into the results channel.
And then the handler says,
when you've received both of those,
then I know I'm done.
And I send the response
back to the client.
So very easy and very simple.
So that channel sits there as kind of
a bucket to store all those results
that are coming back from running your go
routines inside the go routine.
I could be calling another microservice
on the back end.
I could be doing anything in that go
routine, but they are going to be handled
in parallel,
not run in parallel, handled in parallel.
It's still running things
secret asynchronously.
Okay, but this will reduce
the total latency time.
Instead of saying hey, go run the fetch,
get all the fetch inventory first.
Go get all that information first,
then come back and run the fetch price,
and then go get that information
and bring it back.
I can actually run,
those things in.
I can handle those things in parallel.
Meaning I'm going to call the fetch,
and I'm not going to block and wait.
I'm going to call the fetch inventory
and fetch price, and I'm going to get
whatever comes back, comes back
in, gets dumped into the channel.
So I'm not waiting for the, the,
other microservices, the inventory
and the pricing, microservices
to finish before I'm moving forward
with each step.
Okay.
So that channel concept lets me aggregate
multiple results together,
which is actually pretty slick.
So in this example here I've got two
downstream calls in parallel right.
Calling inventory and calling price.
And I'm waiting for those results
to come back in to that channel
which is in the results, variable there.
And I'm combining those together,
saying I need both
the inventory and the price to come back
before I respond.
So it's really that simple.
I love these constructs where it looks
simple and it is simple, right.
I can use real services when
I normally, need to know
which result has come back or arrived.
So it might be important
that I put a little structure there.
To say, hey, I need to know
which results have come back
so that I can, look at those results
and before I move forward.
Because it may be
that I don't want both of them.
Because
what if inventory comes back at zero?
What should I do?
Right then?
I could react right away
until the pricing, call
and say I don't need pricing anymore.
So that would be important
to know which one came back.
And that's
that's this concept of having a structure
that has that information in it.
And then I don't have to guess
on which order things are coming back,
which can be very hairy
because you have no idea when you're doing
microservice architectures.
Okay.
Now let's talk about not having
too many worker, workers out there.
Right.
So this is when I build my worker pool,
so that I don't blow things out.
This is this can happen
if I've got a lot of requests coming in,
and I'm going to fire off a goroutine
for every request, I can create a pool,
so that I can cap
how many, go routines that I can.
I can, run at the same time
through a a worker pool.
So in this case here,
I create basically a channel
that has those worker pools in it.
And, when I grab that channel,
I can grab a, a worker out of that channel
and run a job in there.
And this way,
I can limit the number of coroutines
that are running at the same time.
So it's pretty straightforward.
This is great when I'm protecting
how much memory I need to use,
and it can protect any other,
resource dependencies that I have.
It also gives me some pretty stable
behavior under sustained load.
Right?
I know that this, microservice
can always handle
like, 100,
concurrent, requests at the same time.
That gives me some consistency.
Right now let's look at select.
Now select remember select lets me select
those workers.
Those goroutines.
And I can do things with them like I can
if I timeout after a certain
period of time, I can return a timeout
and I can set the context,
to hey, failed or whatever
the case may be.
I can also, set up
something like in this case here,
whatever event,
whatever goroutine comes back first
that wins and I'm going to cancel
the other ones, which is kind of neat.
Or I can timeout after a certain certain
period of time.
And this, this really avoids,
these goroutines from sitting out there
and hanging forever.
Forever. So you want to make sure
that you're looking at select.
All right.
Another thing I
want to do is when I set up a worker
that's handling these go routines,
that I want to give it some context
on what to do in certain situations.
Right.
If I get, done, like, hey, I've got this
workers done, then what do I do?
Right?
Or are there more jobs to process,
whatever the case may be,
when do I shut down,
these go routines or these workers?
When do I keep them up?
Do I only process one thing
and then and then shut them down?
So I need to make sure that I set up
these contexts appropriately.
Otherwise I can get, coroutines
that link leak and keep doing
useless work and just,
chewing up, resources that are valuable.
Right.
So when do I use go and when do I use,
these go routine concepts
when I need to make independent
IO calls per request.
This is a good way to go, right?
If I have background processing
with, like, I can control
with, concurrency here.
And when I have services that need,
like robust timeout
and cancellation of behavior,
go is a great place to go.
That's why we're seeing more people use,
go for gateways and aggregation.
Things in like that. All right.
Here are some trade offs and pitfalls
you need to work through as an architect.
The benefit and we've talked about this
with like Node.js as well.
It's perfect for like heavy IO workloads.
This is great.
It it does add some complexity
with race conditions and deadlocks
that you have to handle.
If you have unbounded
goroutines, it can cause a lot of memory,
leaks that you need to watch out for.
And always make sure that you're
propagating any context to downstream
calls.
If you've got goroutines
that call go routines, a call routines,
you want to propagate those context, down
so that, when a cancellation happens,
that I'm canceling all of the go,
routines that are happening.
And remember,
not every flow needs that concurrency.
Sequential logic is a whole lot simpler
to debug than running,
you know, concurrent, items,
that, aggregating the results back.
All right.
So only use concurrency
when there's a true benefit there.
And then also if I've got channels
that are out there that are running
without timeouts or shutdowns,
they can sit and block forever, right?
Waiting for that channel
to fill up before I move on.
So make sure that you set
some of those timeouts and shutdown paths.
All right.
So go concurrency.
It's a practical way of scaling IO.
Channel and worker pools
provide explicit control over,
those how that concurrency
in those go routines.
And then make sure that you, have bounded
concurrency
plus cancellation
to keep your services stable.
If you don't do that,
you can chew up a lot of resources
and have some instability
in your microservices.