In this lecture, we're gonna
talk about cookies sessions and cross-site
request forgeries, or CSR
and how to avoid them.
So that's, that's our goal of, of this.
It's going to be an interesting
there's a lot to unpack again in this one.
But by the end of this session, though,
this lecture, you should be able
to explain how cookies work
at an architectural level, explain
how server side sessions are represented
and states can be stored.
Describe what is a CSR ref
and how to prevent it from happening.
And then identify any risks and trade offs
on using sessions and cookies
and,
compare any mitigation strategies for CSR.
Okay.
So first off why do we want cookies.
Well Https is stateless.
So if I'm a client let's say in a browser
and I, access a service
on the back end of something,
I, the server gets that one request
and then if another request comes in,
it doesn't know it can't remember
what the prior requests were.
So if I log in as a user
and I want to look at my account
information,
I would have to pass
that account information in each time
so that same user across
multiple requests is an important thing.
I need to store that state somewhere,
right.
And one of the ways that we do
that is through cookies and sessions.
It's a way of persisting state,
from the browser and also in the server.
So but because I'm storing that state,
that opens up the door to these cross-site
request forgeries, right.
They can abuse, cookies. Right.
Because the idea is if the browser
has the my identity in there
that I can send to the server
and I can send multiple requests
to the server, couldn't
someone grab my identity from my cookies
and, pretend like they're me?
That's the whole idea behind, Csrf.
Okay, so big picture.
This is how it works.
A client submits a form,
it goes into the, through the browser.
The browser.
When it asks for a request to the web
server, it sends in the request.
And cookies,
if there are any, in a response back,
it's going to set cookies in the headers,
back into the browser.
The browser is going to store that cookie.
Oh, the user had this,
log in or use this name.
Whatever the case may be that's
set back in the cookies in the browser.
So now when the user submits
something else,
it has that information, goes, hey,
this is the person that's logged in.
Pass that information from the browser
into the web server.
So the browser stores the cookies
locally per domain and per path,
and then sends them automatically
when the user asks for more.
Information through the web browser.
Okay, so what a cookie is, is,
is just a small piece of data
that is stored in the browser per domain.
They use cookies
for a lot of different things, right?
It's automatically sent with
matching requests when they go through.
Well, some applications, some websites.
Scour your cookies and,
they will, pass those cookies
into your Http request.
That's going through.
That's why you get some of these, like,
Amazon website
that if you were searching
on another website for,
gloves or a snow
shovel all of a sudden on Amazon,
it knows about gloves and snow shovels
because there's a cookie
that's set there with some common language
that it can, that it can use.
Right.
So that's kind of the
the sorts of things that are there.
It's great for storing preferences.
When I go to a website,
maybe I always want it to be dark scheme
or themed and of light themed.
It can remember those sorts of things
that can be passed in
in these cookie session,
or these cookies that are being passed in.
All right.
Another common thing that's passed in
is something called a session identifier,
which we're going to talk about sessions
here in a little bit.
Now here's some cookie attributes.
Remember it's a key value pair basically.
And so here are some attributes
that you can set in your cookies
secure
which says only send the cookie over.
Please only do that.
That's it helps prevent leakage.
And it helps prevent against CSR.
Csrf attacks.
And then also Http only.
This means that I can only access it,
via http call now via JavaScript.
And this is important right.
So it's only going to happen
through the browser.
And so through a JavaScript
acting on your behalf.
This limits many, XSS attacks
where a JavaScript tend take your identity
and start acting as you.
That or take a session
and start acting as you,
directly inside,
your, your browser itself.
So that prevents that from happening.
Some other attributes, same site
which controls
sending cookies across
cross-site requests.
And that's a very important thing
to put in your Csrf, which says,
this cookie can only be used on one site,
not being used on multiple sites.
Domain and path.
What host or host or URLs are received?
Receive the cookie.
So this could
this could lock things down even more.
And in expiry age and and time on that
are some other core attributes of cookies.
All right.
So we talked about cookies
are some of the browsers site.
I'm going to send information about who
I am my preferences whatever session ID
oh session ID
sessions are on the server side.
This is a data structure per user state.
It contains the user identity
and authorization states.
Sometimes roles and permissions.
When we talked about tokens,
it would store token on the server side
in that session.
And other pre user states
like a cart I can store our cart,
I can store,
this is great
when you've got, multi-step transactions
that are going on
on, on the server side, remember
I don't store state in the Http
server itself
when a new connection comes in, it's
like a brand new, oh, you're brand new.
Let's start where you left off.
I need to know where you left off.
So this is where I'm going
to, store state for that session, right?
You typically want to key and have
a unique identifier for each session.
With a random session ID has to be random.
I would seed your random because you don't
want someone guessing session IDs,
because then someone can become you,
which you don't want, right?
And it's usually stored the session ID
is usually stored in the cookie
on the browser side.
So when someone logs in, maybe a hotel
reservation, log in to marriott.com,
a session ID is created.
It's stored as a cookie.
And then when I'm working through the I'm
trying to find the exact right
hotel for my trip to the Bahamas.
Wouldn't that be great?
Then?
I don't have to log in each time.
I don't have to go back
and look at what I've already looked at.
All that information
can be stored in session,
just with the session ID, which is great.
Okay,
so like I already said before, the server
creates a new session with a session ID,
it passes it back.
It's stored in on the cookie
with a set cookie
from the browser
or from the server up to the browser.
Right.
The server can then look up that session
ID every time a new request comes in,
and I know where my state is and
and what I've been doing on that server.
All right.
Now here's some trade offs on
where am I storing the state.
It could be in memory, per node.
Now, this means that a session cannot span
multiple nodes.
So if, if I, have a short span
here, that works fine.
But if I have a long span,
I may have that server.
That web server may have been recycled.
Right.
Or maybe I've got,
100 or 1000 web servers that are serving
up, you know, a million users or whatever
the case may be.
And if it switches between,
you know, calls,
maybe the user stepped out for,
five minutes or something.
They come back now,
they're attached to a different server
then in-memory doesn't work.
So I need like a shared store, right?
Like a cache or a database server.
A central place for storing session state
that can work across multiple servers.
That's important.
And then there's another one
called stateless.
With which could be JWT based,
where I'm actually storing the state more
in the cookies and the tokens that are
that are being passed back and forth.
So it's, it's almost like this circle
that goes around in that
I create that JWT, on the server side,
I pass it back into,
the cookies, that, cookie is stored
and then passed in again,
from the browser if they keep working.
And then I just update this JWT
as it cycles through and that's it.
That's more complex.
And you got to deal with tokens and
validation and all that sort of things,
and you can't really store
too much stuff in a JWT.
You can say I get, but you can store
as much as you could like
in on the server side storage.
So those are trade offs
that you need to look at.
So simple.
Flow diagram on this a user logs in,
they do a post log in.
It creates a session with a session
ID and a user state
now is stored in the session store.
I pass that session ID back
as set cookie into the browser.
Now when the user clicks on anything else
like a profile,
the session ID is passed in as a cookie.
I look up the session ID,
I pass in the user state
into the web server, and the profile page
comes back in this example.
So pretty straightforward stuff.
Okay, let's talk about some risks
because now I've got state
that's stored in the server.
And I've got a way to access
that state or to
yeah a way to mimic
that state in the browser.
Say hey, is your session ID, right.
So this is where things
could get really interesting.
So through an access,
I can steal cookies.
So this is a script
that's running on your site.
It's a cross script. Cross-site script.
Can steal that session ID
and then, it can then, act as you
and in that script to be running
right there in your own thing.
If if you're not using Https,
then it could be intercepted.
Your session ID
could be intercepted as well,
because you want that encrypted,
that session ID going across.
Right.
People can look at your logs and other
leaked, leaks that are in there.
So if you're storing the session ID,
I would encrypt the session ID in logs
and things like that. Right.
With the session ID
man, the attacker can impersonate the user
and and they can stay
impersonating the user until that session
is expired or destroyed.
Okay, so here are some, session
hijacking.
The attacker obtains the session ID.
I already talked about this
as a duplicate.
There you go.
All right. No. How do we fix it?
Here we go. How do we fix this?
We use https
for all authenticated traffic.
We marked session cookies
with secure in HTP only.
That will prevent the XSS.
XSS stealing cookies. Right.
Because a script can no longer act as you,
it only has to go through a browser.
You strong random session
IDs don't just increment your session IDs.
Session one. Session two. Session three.
Someone's going to guess what
the next session is going to be right?
So you want to
randomly generate session IDs
and then regenerate session IDs on log in.
And any privileged change for example,
maybe I want a new session ID
when I'm taking money out of my bank,
or when I'm paying for things
different than when I'm just accessing,
how much money I have in my bank account.
That could be a
completely different session.
Okay.
Session fixation, mitigation risks.
The attacker can set an influence,
or influence a victim's session ID.
The victim
can, logs in using that session.
So this is where they're spoofing
the session ID of front.
Right.
And then the server buys the identity
to that session ID that it was given.
And the attacker
can use that over and over again.
So this is where I have given
a session ID.
And on the back end I'm like oh
yeah I session it here.
I'm going to use that session ID
you never want to do that.
So how do we mitigate that.
Well we have to regenerate
the session ID after login.
Don't take a session ID at login. Right.
And don't accept any session IDs.
From external the session IDs are created
on the server, not the other way around.
Don't do not expose your session
IDs in query parameters
or public links or locks.
All right.
This is the best way to fix this problem
okay.
All right let's talk about Csrf.
So Csrf is really interesting right.
This is when a browser
automatically automatically adds cookies
to matching domains.
Attacker can trick the user's browser
into sending a request
as them to a site
where the user is logged in.
These cross these cross-site
attacks are have were much more common.
Now there's some great,
things that you can do
to prevent these, like when the server.
Well, we'll talk about that.
So what happens is
the server is going to receive a valid
cookie, and session ID,
and then the request can,
looks like it's coming from that user.
So what happens here and is
a user can log into like their bank
in one tab on the same browser.
And then a user visits evil
dot example on another tab.
Right.
The evil example sends a
post to the bank example with
the session ID
because it's in the same browser, right?
So the attacker now can become that user
and can transfer money out.
And the browser includes.
So the browser, because the browser
has all those cookies, there.
So this this can be a problem. Right.
So the interesting thing about it is
the victim is authenticated.
The cookies are they're the sessions.
They're all valid.
But now I've got a one browser
that is actually
or one page
that is actually accessing those cookies,
sending it a request back
through the browser, an Http request.
So it's coming from the same browser.
And then going off
and doing the transfer.
Right.
So this is very insidious.
And could be very hard to detect.
And very hard to, fight against.
So we're going to show you
some techniques.
So here's a diagram
that shows how it all works.
So user logs into the bank
on the browser,
it gets its authorization, it gets,
cookies are coming back.
And the session
ID, it's all authenticated.
I do it,
and the browser has all that information.
Right. I'm good to go.
Then the user in another tab
in their browser
visits evil dot example.
Right.
Well evil dot example.
On the server side it goes, hey,
there's a hidden form in there
that does a pose to bank
example transfer.
So they visit the site,
it grabs that cookie information
of back into the browser. Right.
So it's sending back to the browser.
Hey, I want you to do this.
The cookie information is there.
It fills out that form.
It has the correct session ID,
it calls transfer
on the session ID
and then the transfer is complete.
And the attacker
just got all of your stuff
right.
Pretty insidious.
So what can I do?
How do I get,
how do I get around all of this?
Well, let's take a look at that.
Right.
First off, the attacker is triggering
a cross-site request.
That's what is called a cross-site request
right now.
There are times when you when you would
really like a cross-site request
in some of your architectures,
you may run into it, but you got it.
You got to prevent these things
from happening
because this can expose you
to a third party.
Getting access to your
information and passing in,
passing in APIs
that you don't want to have happen.
Right.
So the attacker site, if you set it up
properly, the attacker site can't read
the CSR have tokens,
so you've got to set them correctly.
It can and it can't correctly guess
the secret token without a valid token.
The server will then reject,
any dangerous requests that comes in.
So in this case here,
I load a page in the browser,
I'm getting my settings, I'm passing back
the form and the Csrf token.
So if someone's passing a form,
I know what the Csrf token is.
I can submit the form
I'm passing back in the Csrf token
and the session ID, I validate both
and then I can pass on.
So anytime I'm doing a post on my server
side, I should be using this, technique.
Okay, here
are some of the,
things that you could set in your cookies.
Same site attribute.
So if you say same site lacks
then you're sending top level
Nat navigations.
This works great.
I can block any cross-site posts
and iframes,
so I don't allow any iframes in there.
If I say strict, you always send
same site request period.
No top level navigation
if I so strict strong Csrf protection and.
But there is some UX impact which
I have seen, I can tell on certain sites
when they've turned this on completely
because the user experience isn't as good.
Right.
And then another option is,
when I do have some cross site like,
single sign on flows,
I need to set that to none
and then say secure.
But you must set secure because that will,
that will help with your encryption.
Right.
Some additional Csrf, defenses are
you want to re authenticate
or set up auth for any critical actions
like transferring money,
launching weapons,
you know, whatever the case may be
on your microservice that you're doing,
use custom headers for APIs and Csrf
tokens that the people would know,
a little bit of obscurity there
and then make high risk operations,
multi-step where possible.
Right.
And then monitor for usual and unusual
patterns and around sensitive actions.
Monitoring is is key here.
All right.
So putting this all together
cookies are stored where in the browser.
Right.
They're very convenient primary but
they're also the primary surface for csvs.
So you got to be careful.
Local session
storage is not automatically set.
Common history
is to store those in a cache.
And most browsers
allow you to do that now.
Right.
Typical secure pattern is session cookies
for logging in on state.
Make sure you set
secure is GTP only and use same site.
And then, make sure that on the back end
that I can take a Csrf
tokens in forms and headers.
I can pass those back in.
So the browser, is, verified
one more time
that, hey,
this is actually coming from the browser
and not from a third party
going through the browser.
Okay,
that's cookies sessions and how to protect
against these different,
hacking techniques that are out there.
Make sure that you look at the trade offs
on these, you're adding more complexity
and overhead to things,
but you are creating,
more secure applications.