Okay.
In this lecture we're
going to talk about back pressure
and two different techniques.
I guess they would be called techniques
of back pressure push versus pull.
So the goal of this lecture is to define
what back pressure is
and why it's required.
It's primarily for asynchronous of course.
And then distinguish the difference
between push and pull flow control models
and then select overhead policies
or overload policies
based off of business activity.
And business criticality.
This is important thing
to understand the business
in order to choose what you need to do.
And then look at, the different
trade offs between each of them.
So first off, that pressure prevents
really fast producers of, requests to.
Oh, that from overwhelming
slow back end consumers or workers
that need to work on something.
So the producers are saying,
I need you to do something for me.
And the consumers are saying,
I'll do that work for you.
That's the idea here.
So producer in this case is my requester
and the consumer is my worker
B he's doing the work for me.
Right? So
this typically
happens if I've got a lot of,
requests coming in from someone
requesting work to be done on a back
end, microservice
that just can't handle, the amount
maybe my, my back in microservice
can only handle a 100 requests per second,
and the front end can produce,
at 10,000 requests per second.
There's a major mismatch there.
It's going to slow down.
Everything
all right, including a microservice?
A the one producing all of the,
requests that they're coming out.
Okay.
So I need to figure out the best way
to put some back pressure
on the producer, the one that's saying,
hey, I need you to do more.
And the one on the back
ends just can't handle. So I need to.
I need to throttle that guy somehow.
But I have to do it dynamically.
I can do it statically where I'm saying,
hey, I'm going to have a certain fan
out of this number,
but the loads are different
in different time, so
there's a better way to do it dynamically.
And that's
what back pressure kind of gives me.
That's the idea, right?
If I don't have any bounds on demand,
then I can easily overwhelm things.
And then latency goes through the roof
and memory becomes highly in predictable
and now I you can have major issues
with that single, microservice.
You can spin up more instances
of the same microservice,
but you need some time to do that
without cascading delays.
So, you got to look at some,
some different, strategies to do this
where you can handle it gracefully.
Right? That's the key. Right.
So why this matters with no back pressure,
it increases my latency dramatically.
And my queue depth,
which increases memory,
which then increases number of resources.
And people go, look,
I can't run this microservice
on a tiny instance in the cloud.
I need this bigger one.
And you're wondering,
you're scratching your head. Why?
Because the amount of memory it's
using up in these buffer
queues, things like that
could, could cause that sort of things.
Right.
Also timeouts and retries kind of amplify
the load during these types of incidents.
And we're running these asynchronously.
Right.
So one of the reasons we went to
asynchronous is to get away
from the problems
that come with timeouts and retries.
Right.
And I can have cascading failures
if I don't put some bounds
or some back pressure
on the calling, client on things.
Right. The producer of of the request.
All right.
So here's the two techniques.
One is called push
and the other one is called pull.
Now on the push
this is where the producer,
the one asking for the request of work
to be done on the backend
microservice, emits
when it's ready, it just emits.
Hey, I need you to do this work for me.
This works out really well, right?
This is pretty typical,
low delivery latency under healthy load.
This works very, very well, right.
But if I'm producing more
of those requests than what the backend
can handle, then I can really
easily run into, some issues there.
So I need some back pressure
or I need some bounded cues
that can I reject or drop,
those requests as they go in.
Right.
Because if I send it off,
I'm doing a fire and forget
and, the backend can't handle it.
It may drop or reject some of those,
those, requests that are coming in.
So this is where policy, and business,
criticality, have a big play.
Another option is this
instead of the producer saying, hey,
I need you to go
do this work for me instead, the worker,
a consumer of that request, says, hey,
I can do some work.
Anyone got work for me to do?
And it typically and in this case
it says I can do five things right now.
So can you give me five things.
So it's going to pull those off
of the message bus and handle those.
And then it will naturally,
keep up that concurrency control.
And you can easily throttle
the back in this way.
Right.
This pull method is hey, I'm
going to go pull those request processing.
It gives you better stability,
but you have some higher latency.
From the, from the pooling.
Right.
Because I've got to go out and ask,
hey, I, can I do some?
So there's some, there's some issues there
and there's some leases
on, on those socket connections
and things that you have to worry about.
So those are the sorts of things
that you have to deal.
Pooling is a little more complex
than just a straight up push.
So let's let's take a look at it.
Now if I marry the two together,
then I can have a hybrid demand
signal flow.
So in this case,
what happens is the consumer,
the worker be here, right.
He's saying I can handle this
many things right now.
Okay, great.
You can handle those many things.
The producer will then only emit
and only ask for up
to that number of requests of the amount.
So if the consumer on the back
end, the worker
B says, I can take 100 things right now
and the producer doesn't have 100 things,
is still going to admit up to maybe 80
or 10 or one, whatever the case may be on
a minute, because he's he's got plenty of,
spare time to do this for me.
So that's the idea behind it, right?
There's no new demand.
Means on the, for the producer to pause,
he can just,
you know,
he can just do whatever he wants.
But if, let's say I have 150 items
I need to do
and,
this one worker said I can handle 100.
I'm going to give it 100,
and then I'm going to wait.
And, for those other 50, I'm going to wait
until I get another demand signal
that says, hey, I can take another
hundred, or I can take, one at a time.
And then I would start pushing it through.
Right.
That's the that's the idea of for this.
This works really, really well for strong
for high concurrency.
IOB paths where maybe I have a chain
of several microservices that I'm pumping
lots of information through
and they're flowing through.
This works really
well for those sorts of things.
And traditionally you see this sort of,
concept in ETL flows,
right where I'm doing a lot of data
transformation now through things.
So it's the same kind of concept.
All right.
So let's take a look at pool
with some back pressure.
Right.
Remember pooling is where the worker be
the consumer
is saying hey give me ten things to do.
I said, okay
I can give you ten things to do. Right.
So in this case the producer writes
a bunch of stuff out to the queue.
Hey, I need, I need,
I need you do requests, a bunch of stuff.
I need you to do all this stuff for me.
And the worker says, okay,
I'm going to take ten right now.
So I take my ten, I do my work, and then,
you know, I'm done with my work.
And I say, all right, I'm. I'm done.
And,
send those requests back out to the queue.
And then, you know, the producer,
the worker, the not the producer.
The requester is actually,
going to get those responses back
and potentially can get another signal
saying, hey,
I can take another five if you got five
for me to do type of thing.
Right.
I okay,
so here are some issues
that arise in this one.
Right.
Let's say the producer, says, hey, I need
I need to do a thousand things.
And the consumer,
that worker be on the back end.
He's like, I really can't handle
a thousand things, right?
And that queue starts growing really
large,
especially if it's a repeat type of thing.
If, like I mentioned before, the producer,
the requester here, can can run
10,000 requests per second,
but the worker be on the back end,
the worker microservice, our consumer,
another name for it
can only handle a thousand
that I'm going to
just have that queue
grow super huge and possibly crash.
Right.
And then I don't know the state of
anything, the things that are in there.
So, so if I look at demand signaled,
then what it says is, hey,
the producer is only going to produce,
those requests, how many requests?
It has based off of of the number of slots
that the worker says
I can handle what this does is
it pushes the queue into the producers.
All right.
So if I have a whole bunch of producers,
maybe a thousand producers,
they're all keeping their own track
of the requests that they need to make.
Right?
Which that's a natural back pressure
that goes back to those, producers.
Okay.
There's
lots of different techniques to use.
This one is through an API gateway.
So in an API gateway, we can, handle
like these inbound requests.
I can put a limit and say, look,
you can only handle 1500
requests per second,
and I'll give you, up to, like,
a 300 burst on that, like 300
all at once type of thing.
And if you go beyond that,
then I'm going to send back
to whoever made that call a 429.
Too many requests were made.
So you need to slow things down. Right.
So this is at the API gateway.
So this way kind of that back pressure
logic is sitting in the API gateway.
Another option
here is where the worker is pushing back.
Right.
It's saying, hey, I am only going to take
ten things at a time.
So in this example
here in this Python code,
I'm going to say
I'm only taking ten things at a time.
You can give me ten things.
That's it.
So the concurrency is built
into the microservice,
or that concurrency limit is built
into the microservice itself,
and it tells that, hey, this is the max
number of things I can take out of time.
This is a you see this?
You see this even in some,
synchronous calls where there's a limit on
how many things you can, request off
a big list and pagination happens.
These are pretty easy,
straightforward things.
Another thing is where the subscriber
sets the initial demand.
So this is the guy
I remember the subscribers
one requesting all of the work to be done.
He goes, yeah, you know,
I got 1500 things to do.
And then what happens?
Next is the worker bee says,
well guess what, I can only take 100.
My can give me the 100.
I'll. I'll give you 100.
And then, you know,
I'll wait till, I hear back from you
whether I can take anymore.
And then it can say, all right,
I can take another ten,
and then you can go that route.
This could be really interesting, too,
if I have multiple instances
of the same microservice running,
and maybe I've got 100 of them
and the, the front end is smart enough.
The subscriber here, right
now, the requester of these,
work to be done is smart enough to,
to get all these requests back
and send them back out in batches.
That could be very interesting as well.
Okay.
Next thing you need to look at,
because there's drop offs are because
there's drop offs, there are drop offs
with just a straight up, pool.
Our push method A but it's easier.
The logic is easier.
I need to look at all of the different,
business semantics.
Is it okay to maybe drop a message or two?
It might be.
It might not.
You have to make that determination.
So in this case,
I got to look and see things
like payments, orders,
financial track transactions.
I want some guarantees.
I don't want those things
dropping off. Right.
So. All right, so which technique
would you use their mascots in here.
Think about you could say, they may drop.
I'm just sampling things anyway.
Like in debug logs, high cardinality
telemetry type of thing.
Where there's me then.
All right, that might be okay.
Other wins where? Hey, it's.
I can expect, a delay in retry. Okay.
To do that, I want never drops, but,
but I'm going to I want some assurances.
So, I'm okay to take some delays
and retries instead.
Dead letter.
This is.
I send it out.
I don't care if it gets processed or not.
And the.
Believe me, there are times
when when you can do that.
Just make sure that you're keeping the
policy explicit per topic or per endpoint.
And that's a decision
that you have to make as well.
I suggest topics, but if you're over
using topics for multiple things,
then that's when you may want to separate
multiple topics
on your message boxes.
Okay.
When do you use what.
Oh, this is
this makes you an architect, right?
You want to choose push for low latency.
Fan out where there's some drop
that is acceptable.
You want to use pool
for like highly durable jobs with strict
throughput controls.
You want it very strict,
then you want to use that pool technique
and then you can use the hybrid,
which is a little more complex
for more stable high
concurrency streaming.
This is great if you're, setting up
pipelines to pipe data
through and do data transformations
across multiple microservices.
Right.
And also look at per
domain policies over one glob.
Global strategy, for the,
the, the different techniques
that you're going to use.
Right.
And document to document the overflow
behavior of your API endpoints.
And what happens if things go outside
of the boundaries that you've established,
and make sure that you're validating
those policies with load tests,
and get rid of any
assumptions that you have.
All right.
Lots of things that you have to decide on
as an architect.
Is data loss acceptable?
Do consumers have variable processing
times?
Those consumers remember the consumers,
right.
They're the ones that are actually
doing the work. Right.
I know it sounds counterintuitive,
but in a published and subscribe,
they're consumers.
The workers do
they have variable processing time?
If so, then there's some techniques.
Poor probably or hybrid.
Is low latency
more important than strict durability?
Push or pull.
Right.
Our queue depths lag
rejection rate and retrieves observable.
Right.
So and then,
what's your overflow behavior?
What are you going to do?
You're going to just drop things quietly.
Are you going to do,
allow them to do retries
or are you going to do a 429 and say,
stop bugging me?
That's what 429 basically says too much.
Stop bugging me. Give me a break.
Okay,
so all of these architectural trade offs
you need to look at.
So here here they are.
Stability throughput.
We talked about those next.
The next one is interaction freshness.
It's like buying fruit right right.
If if I am concerned about
how fresh the events are
and I've got big,
huge buffers of queues of things,
and I normally process things first
in, first out,
then am I getting the freshness
if I do, last in, first out or, life.
So then I can have starvation.
So you have to understand freshness
on, on those buffer things.
And so I handled that complexity.
We've talked a lot about complexity.
Operations.
You're going to need some dashboards
and alerts
that are required for tuning these things.
And tuning them is very tricky. Right.
How much back pressure?
How many times do I retry.
What am I timeouts?
What am I intervals between time,
retries, all those sorts of things
and most importantly, cost as we moving
things more and more into the cloud.
Every time I spin up a new
instance, it cost me money.
Okay, big pitfalls
don't look at unbounded.
Cuz they're there. Uses hidden buffers.
You can blow those puppies out once you
start scaling for very simple things, man.
No big deal, right?
Make sure that I'm not applying, one
policy globally and that policies
are applied appropriately.
I don't want a policy
applied to every single message,
but every single message type. Absolutely.
Okay.
Critical events make sure they're not
dropped without some kind of audit trail.
Aggressive
retries can really slow things down,
especially during active, overload.
And then make sure that you're
capturing those metrics
for lag and saturation, things like that,
and then look back.
Pressure is there as control contract,
not as optional optimization.
So it's a control contract between the
the producer of
the request and the worker.