Okay.
In this lecture, I'm going to talk about
why blocking systems
fail specifically
in microservice architectures.
So a lot of times
what happens is
when I've got a microservice
that doing work,
it can block any other requests coming in.
This is an important
thing that we need to look for,
and we need to be able
to handle these things.
Where I get a latency spikes,
because maybe some underlying
processing that I have to do
is going to take longer than the normal
for some reason, whatever the case may be.
And I need to be able
to handle these sorts of situations.
So we're going to talk about latency
spikes, connection
queue growth and timeout cascade problems.
And we're going to identify
some practical mitigation patterns.
And then we're going to talk
more in depth in other lectures
about some of the techniques.
So a blocking request model
is this when one request
comes into a microservice from another.
So let's call it microservice a
we'll ask microservice B
which is a worker, to do something
when it sends that request in via
Rest interface,
yet is waiting for that response back.
This is a typical synchronous
processing problem, right.
So what happens is,
is if microservice B takes some time,
then the response coming back
takes time as well.
Now we normally see
these sorts of things happen
when we're doing
traditional block programing.
In one process, when we have a monolithic
process where I call a function,
it runs through that function get
and I get the result back.
The difference here is that that's a pure
synchronous.
The difference here in microservices
is you've got an event loop
and things are somewhat asynchronous.
And we're kind of forcing
some single synchronicity on there.
So what happens is is these active workers
because multiple things can attach to it.
They can become very active
and overwhelmed
on getting all of the results sent back
to all the different microservices
that are calling them.
And this latency on return
ends up cascading a specific way.
If you have like timeouts
that are not long enough and you've got,
microservices very active
and with a lot of work going on,
you can get those timeouts that happen
and then you can get cascading timeouts.
If you've got microservices
calling microservices.
So that's the sort of thing
that you have to watch out for.
So very simple.
I've got a client out
there is calling service A.
It's requesting something
and service A does some processing
and then it goes and it calls service
B to say, hey, I need to do something.
In this other service over here
and service
B is busy doing something else.
It could take some time.
That's called a latency spike.
Right.
And it's a
that's one of the harder things to
to deal with is latency inconsistency.
These spikes, cause timing issues
in your own microservices.
And if you're used to doing everything
purely synchronous
and you want things
happen in a certain way,
there appears to be delays,
and then you don't know
if service B actually went down.
And you need to,
you know, send out an alert somewhere
to somebody to, hey, try this
or do I need to do a retry?
And you can get cascading failures,
cascading latency spikes this way.
So things to watch out for.
But you can see that service
now has this coupling,
even though it's runtime
coupling with service B on, it's,
potential behavior
based off of, latency on service B.
So we need ways of solving that problem.
Right.
And there's lots of different techniques
that we're going to talk about.
One of the issues though
with these latency dependencies,
imagine having a dozen microservices
and almost forming a mesh
on how they communicate with each other.
You can end up with these
really funky ways
that, latency is popping up in different,
services at different times.
That then just slows everything down
dramatically, right?
And it's really important
when you're doing,
microservice inter communication
and process communication
that you have timeouts
that, are sufficiently long enough
but not too long that now you're blocking
everybody else.
Because if I'm sitting
waiting for a response from someone, then
unblocked waiting,
and someone else could be waiting for me.
So you gotta play around
with those timeouts a little bit
and make sure that you retry
after those timeouts.
And we've talked about retry timeout
feedback loops and
and having different times in there,
like a sleep
or wait before you try again.
If you don't put a weight
before you try again, then you could just
exacerbate the problem by retrying
in a very tight close feedback loop.
Okay.
So this is where things get
really interesting in your architecture.
You gotta take a look and see
what, capacity
each one of your microservices
can handle.
And whether you need to fire up
multiple instances
of the same microservice to handle things.
And yeah, a lot of times
it's trial and error, but
you should be planning these things out
front, earlier than than later.
Just keep that in mind.
Something you should be looking at, right?
Longer wait times means fewer
requests can be completed per second.
So if I have a timeout, that's longer
and I could be blocking right now
some, programing languages
like Java, for example,
they actually have threads per request.
And now there's some trade offs
and there's some benefits to that.
Adding threads can increase memory
and context
switching overhead
inside the processor itself.
So if I'm doing if I'm doing threads
per request, I can actually slow down
the whole machine,
which is an interesting concept, right.
Because now I've got so many more context
switching
going on inside of the CPU,
which means I'm
moving memory in and out of the CPU,
possibly virtual memory.
It could,
it could bog the whole system down, but
it could be much faster
than, handling things
and less complex than handling things.
With single threaded.
So you've got it.
You've got some trade offs here
that you got to deal with,
and different languages
handle it differently.
Good news is, is all the other languages
have the concepts.
Some of them bake
the concepts directly into,
the, the language itself
and the frameworks that they work in.
Okay.
Also remember, adding more threads
does not remove dependency latency.
Not at all.
You still have a dependency latency.
It's just now I can run
multiple things in parallel, but I still
I still have some latency,
especially in something like Java.
When it hits garbage collect.
Then it could slow everything down.
All of your threads.
So you got to watch out
for all these sorts of things.
Okay, so here's some here's some
mitigation options that you can look at.
You can tighten down your client timeouts.
And you can have retries
that are bounded with timeout jitter.
So it's not the same.
It's not oh try again
in 5 seconds or 500 milliseconds.
That, you know, those sorts of things
take a look at circuit breakers
for fail fast behavior.
These are important.
Look at bulkheads,
which we've talked about in other,
lectures to isolate resource pools.
Right.
So I don't have the effects of,
part of my program
affecting another part of the program.
And look for back
pressure and bounded queries.
So instead of saying,
give me all of the orders,
say I'm only going
to pass back 50 at a time.
And then you can paginate,
the rest of the rest of the,
orders that, that you want.
So these are ways to reduce that back
pressure or the to produce back pressure
so that the clients aren't asking for more
than what it really needs.
Decreasing the amount of, work that has
to happen on the microservice itself.
So remember, there's lots of trade offs
we have to deal with.
The blocking style is not just
simple, straightforward, right?
It's great for simple workloads,
but debugging these things can be really,
really, difficult.
And especially if I move to fully async
so synchronous it's easier to debug.
But there's trade offs here. Right.
So we have to watch out
for those sorts of things.
Also make sure that you're
looking at, resilience in this
and what what
resilience plays inside this.
If I have a microservice
that's kind of flaky and goes down a lot.
I want to make sure that I'm not blocked
on, the client side
or the client microservice side
that I have some options.
And then, also,
if I have really high concurrent
workloads, typically
I don't want these blocking things.
So I will need to move to some async,
technology async, techniques here.
Okay.
A recap blocking systems,
making RESTful calls.
They're easier to debug.
And they fail
through, resource saturation.
So you got to be careful there.
They can create slow dependencies,
between you know, queuing up
on the microservice side and timeouts,
and you can have timeout cascades,
but they are a whole lot easier to debug
and to program in.
So if I got a microservice
with just a few, maybe a thousand,
requests, a minute
or less, then this is a really good, easy
way to go.
It decreases the complexity
and also makes it so I can easily move,
in and out of my,
microservice architectures
where I always making that decision on
do I create a new microservice to do that,
or do I keep it in the same code?
So that helps out a
lot with that sort of thing.