Okay.
In this lecture we're
going to talk about graceful shutdown
and draining of your microservices.
Now this is unique to distributed systems
because if I do a graceful shutdown
in a normal application, I can handle
all that in the application itself.
Like, hey,
I'm going to do a shutdown close
on my database socket command,
you know, finish writing things out.
It's pretty simple.
In microservice architectures,
it can be a lot more complicated
because I've got all of these processes
that are running.
I need to shut them down, but
they may be partially processing things.
So I need to have a strategy to do this.
So that's what we mean
a graceful shutdown right.
Instead of
even if someone did a kill or a Sigint
on, one of your processes,
that's a microservice,
you need to capture that and shut down
gracefully so you don't get corruption
in your database.
That's one of the reasons
why we need to do that. Okay.
There's lots of different reasons
why us, microservices could go down.
We want to make sure
that if it does go down hard,
that when we come back up
that we can handle things appropriately.
And then also,
if there's any outstanding requests
that we handle those,
appropriately as well, we want to drain
any of the timeouts or ordering on
any upstream requests that are coming in.
All right.
So those are the sorts of things
we need to look at.
And then we can talk about any, pitfalls,
with doing this. So
here is the order of operations
on a graceful shutdown.
First stop accepting new requests on that,
microservice.
It's not just good enough
to just turn everything off
because you still have some things
to finish working on.
So that's the next thing you stop
new requests from coming in first,
then you say, I'm going to finish
any of the things
that are in in flight to finish.
So maybe I have some requests
that are out there.
They might be requests out there
for some underlying service.
I need to wait for those to come back.
Okay.
Then the next thing I need to do is
I need to deregister myself
from the load balancer. Right.
And you can either do that
before the in flight or after.
It depends on
how you've architected things.
But either way we'll do that.
And then you want to enforce the maximum
drain timeout.
Right.
Because I can't sit there
and try and drain for minutes or hours
when someone's asked me to do this.
So you want to
you want to give a limit to it
so that you do shut down,
even if you lose some of the requests
that you may have outstanding.
Make sure that you do close
any of your resources.
Maybe you have a
socket open to a database or
excuse me,
to a file system or something like that.
Make sure that you close those resources
appropriately.
Also, omit
any logs and metrics for the shutdown.
I'm shutting down.
I'm finishing up X number of requests,
whatever the case may be.
Right.
And this will also protect
the user experience to the deploy.
They're not going to have all this stuff
laying around sitting there.
Right.
Also remember
you got to watch out for partial rights
because that could cause corruption
in your database
or in your file system
wherever you're persisting.
Data. Right.
And then you want to keep
all your background jobs
that you may have running consistent here.
So that they're all kind of shutting down
the same way.
All your microservices. Right.
So this,
this whole concept, we got to look
at all of these, different things.
Another thing that you may want to look at
is reduce your timeouts for clients,
so that they're not sitting,
waiting on a five minute timeout
that, you know, hey, I didn't hear
from this thing in 15 seconds or 30s.
And I know the right thing to do,
and it enables safer rollbacks
and things like that.
Okay, so this is what it looks like
in sequence diagram.
A request comes in to the load balancer.
It's going to, route
the request to a service that's out there.
And all of a sudden I get that,
I get the hey, you need to shut down.
First thing I'm going to do, deregister
and then drain.
Right?
Which means I'm going to tell the load
balancer I'm not taking anything else.
I'm going to stop any new requests
that do, sneak in
and not do those and reject them
right away.
And then I'm going to finish
all my in-flight work,
and then I'm going to tell the load
balancer I'm completely done
de registering.
I finish my drain
and I'm going to shut down that instance.
It's pretty straightforward.
Okay.
So you want to make sure that you are
separating readiness from liveness probes.
So so
I may still want to give a health update
and say the health update maybe,
I'm actually, shutting down right now.
That might be a good health update.
So if someone's, hitting you
for your health check,
you should return something and say,
hey, I'm.
I'm shutting down.
That's a good thing to give to, like,
a load balancer
or, an external observer
to see what's going on
so that that makes it, important.
Also, make sure that all your handlers
and any retries are independent,
which means that if they run
the same command multiple times,
my state does not change on the back
end, right?
That I'm guaranteed
the I'm guaranteed the same state
regardless of how many times
I call the same thing right?
And then,
make sure that
you are closing
all the shared resources last.
So I got everything done.
Now I can close all the
all those resources that I have in there.
Okay. All right.
So here's a simple example in go,
where I can see,
un listing for this
sig term or sig int right.
Someone does it forces a shut down.
I call server shutdown with a timeout,
and then I stop
any new requests immediately.
And then I let in-flight work finish.
I log the start and end of the training.
So I do that at the start,
and then at the end,
and then I exit with a clear status code,
say why did I shutdown?
Which was that
sig, sig or sig term that I got.
Pretty straightforward stuff
okay.
Node.js example very similar.
I handle the sig int I call.
I stop accepting any new connection
requests.
I let everything finish,
then I need to have finish.
Then I force close
any remaining sockets at the deadline.
I close shared client.
I close the shared clients
I have somewhere else
after the server drain
and then I exit cleanly
so everything goes through that shutdown
method that that I've, created there.
Okay,
one more example.
Python example.
Same thing.
I captured this Sigint,
which you can see here,
capture the Sigint.
I marked the app as draining to reject
any new work.
Right.
I'm draining, my app.
I finish any active request within
a timeout, so I put my timeout in there.
Once I hit that timeout, I stop serving
before any closed, dependencies.
I keep the timeout
bounded to avoid any struck exits,
and then I emit logs
on the shutdown phase.
So very similar.
And you can you can use these patterns
in each one of the languages.
Just a little bit
different implementation for each one.
Now in Kubernetes I can do
Kubernetes draining as well
when I'm draining,
actual requests to spin up new instances.
Right. So this is actually pretty cool.
I can show I can show this with a simple,
Kubernetes,
method here where I've got a pre stop,
I'm going to sleep for 10s,
then I'm going to kick it in the can here,
where I'm actually going to force
the microservice to stop from the outside.
All right.
So it's kind of it's
really an interesting design pattern.
This one.
All right.
Architectural trade offs.
So this is a big one. Reliability.
This is this is an important one because,
I'm reducing the dropped requests.
Even though there could be
a timeout still. So
my reliability could be a little bit
questionable.
Latency is an issue here
because I'm doing a longer drain windows
for slower rollouts.
So if I'm shutting something down,
I could take a little bit longer
to finish shutting that down
before I spin up the new instance.
Right.
Cost could be an issue
because there's extra capacity
for staying online during a drain,
but maybe not to too much scalability.
Safe scaling in leads to,
my load balancing coordination.
As I got, maybe I have five instances
running of a certain microservice.
And I called shut down on two of them,
and they take a couple of minutes
to shut down.
I'm still holding on to to those, slots,
which means I'm
only accepting three at that time,
while the other two are shutting down.
When they're completely shut down,
the new ones will spin up in their places.
So I'm losing some scalability
for a short period of time.
And then also complexity
is an issue with these,
with these shutdowns.
Right.
I have to handle, signal handling,
which is kind of a pain.
Sometimes I need to handle order
ordering of finishing up requests
and all those sorts of things.
So you got,
these are some architectural trade offs,
but the benefits are pretty substantial,
which is, consistency in my data
on the back end.
And things like that. Right.
All right.
Some pitfalls to, to watch out for.
Don't forget to deregister
from the load balancer.
Right. This instance is running.
I need to say I'm going to deregister
because I don't want any more instance.
I don't want any more stuff
coming to me. Right.
Make sure that your drain timeout
is not too short
or you're going to consistently get bad.
State out of out of the back end of it.
Make sure that you close all those database connections before responses complete.
Make sure
that you don't before they're complete,
but make sure that you close them
at the end.
Otherwise you end up with open sockets.
You can run out of sockets
on your operating system.
All right.
And make sure you're not ignoring
any background jobs that are spun up,
or you end up with a bunch
of zombie processes on the back end,
which could, pollute your process space
and cause
a lot of issues
on using resources that you may not have.
All right.
So remember, drain your traffic,
finish the work, and shutdown cleanly.
Those those are the key
things on shutdown and drain.