Okay.
This lecture is on cohesion and coupling.
And these are key fundamental software
engineering things
that you need to understand.
And make sure that you are always
keep it in mind when you're designing
your microservice architectures.
So the golden rule on
these is high cohesion.
And low coupling.
So what do what do these really mean.
Well let's go through that.
Let's define what cohesion is
and then what coupling is.
And then let's identify
any risk by having
low cohesion and high coupling
or having any kind of mid-ground compared
to high cohesion and low coupling.
And there's some trade offs
that you have to deal with.
Here
complexity is one of those big trade offs.
So cohesion.
When things belong together
they stay together.
So that's the
that's the best way to think of it.
So high cohesion is a service
that does one thing really, really well.
It does one thing like a payment service
or an inventory service
or a oh, a video serving service.
Right. Something that serves up videos.
It does one thing
and does it really well, right.
Low cohesion is where I've got multiple
unrelated responsibilities
that are doing something together.
Like if I have a management service where
it manages users and catalogs and emails.
So think of it almost like
go back to your object oriented
programing and analysis
and design concepts.
If I have high cohesion,
it typically means
that I've got everything
that can act on those individual objects.
All all together, right?
If it's doing one thing right.
Payment service. Right.
A management service it's managing users
catalogs and emails.
That's very horizontal
thinking where, hey,
I've got a more functional
management is the is it?
So if you have verbs and things like that
and as across multiple
types of objects,
tends to be low cohesion.
So think of cohesion more from the data
side than from the functional side.
And you'll typically go
pretty pretty good in that direction
of why it matters.
Well it mostly matters because it's much
easier to understand and test and maintain
because I'm dealing with one,
type of object
or one concept that,
I'm working with instead of,
a bunch of different, things,
and also means that I can isolate changes
without it affecting other things,
like a change to a payment system.
Doesn't it affect breaking emails or users
or things like that?
So instead of grouping everything
in a big management service
where one change
can affect a whole bunch of things.
If you have that,
then you know that you've got,
low cohesion and high coupling,
which is the bad.
That's very bad. You don't want that.
So let's talk about coupling.
Coupling
means that you have a dependency on others
and you're not very independent.
Now with software we want
we want, low coupling so that,
if one change occurs,
it doesn't affect, other things.
Now there's lots of different ways
that coupling happens.
Right.
But, it's important to understand that,
all those different ways.
So you cannot inadvertently create
a coupling between two services.
So loose or low coupling means
that services can change independently.
Via stable APIs.
Now, some I've seen, coupling
where the APIs are so tightly coupled.
Right,
that one change is affecting everyone.
And I also see it with like,
shared databases.
Oh, the database schema changed for user.
Why did that affect payments.
Shouldn't
shouldn't affect payments at all.
If you do
then you know you've got coupling there.
High coupling means that one changes.
Can one change can force multiple changes
throughout, the architecture.
So that tends to mean
you've got a bad architecture.
And we've seen we've seen high
coupling in major
cloud service providers
that cause massive power outages.
And some of these couplings
were inadvertent, like,
high coupling on,
domain name services
or dynamic naming services.
Right. Poi, I have high coupling.
All of a sudden
everything falls apart and fails.
That's a bad design.
All right, so here's
some, coupling to avoid implementation.
Coupling?
Meaning I have dependency on internals
between different things.
Now, we see this primarily
in monolithic programs or
modular monolithic, where I've got central
libraries that I use all over the place
because, hey,
that was something we were taught to do.
That's still really good.
But you've created a coupling, so
you have to understand the that dependency
and make sure that you, avoid coupling,
between two modules.
If instead put a third one in there.
So that decouples
these two modules from each other,
but inadvertently through the third one.
But your changes can be more isolated.
You can have temporal, coupling
where, all the services are required
to be online at once.
This one I have seen time and time again,
as sometimes you universally put them in
as an admin check, where I'm saying, hey,
I'm going to do an admin check
before I send anything across.
And then you can get a propagating,
health check that now
tightly coupled everything together.
Typically a bad idea, right?
Deployment
coupling is if you deploy a microservice
and it won't operate at all
without another microservice, there
you have a deployment coupling
that's going on.
So you got to watch out for that.
And then domain
this is when models are too intertwined.
Whether it's your user model
compared to your,
payment model
or your inventory model, if you can have
foreign key fields
in there that can, introduce coupling
if you're not careful.
So you got to watch out for those.
Okay.
So the relationship between cohesion
and and coupling,
if I have low cohesion
it tends to lead to high coupling.
But not always.
But the relationship
is pretty strong there.
So if a service lacks clear purpose
a lot of times
it must reach out to someone else's,
logic.
And you've now created,
dependency or a coupling,
so you got to watch out for that.
It creates just this really complex
web of tight dependencies,
and it can be very difficult to debug,
very difficult
to build,
very difficult to maintain as well.
So you gotta watch out for that.
Oh, here's a, here's
a great world example of a user service
where I've got,
authorization, profiling and billing
all in one service.
Now, these really should be,
three different services
when you think about it.
Right?
Because if I make any changes
to the, billing updates, it would require
redeployment of your authorization logic,
which could be very high risk.
Right.
So the fix is to extract that out
into its own service.
Now my authorization is standalone,
the profile standalone
and the billing is standalone.
So now they are highly cohesive.
No, there'd be a tendency with this now
to move to something called Nano.
Microservices or nano services.
We'll talk about that in a little bit.
All right.
So for assignment
one that, I have for you guys,
make sure that your services
don't have more than one responsibility.
So take
a look at it and think really hard.
Does this have more than one
responsibility?
Does, your open
API spec leak database field names?
You're doing an implementation
coupling then.
So if, if you put in here, a foreign key
that's a, that's a common one
I've seen where someone puts into the API,
foreign key or a database
field name directly that typically is,
an implementation coupling
that you're passing around through an API.
So you gotta watch out for that.
So the key here is
high cohesion,
low coupling.
Right.
Cohesion is that the services are small.
And focus on one thing.
And low coupling ensures
that they're fully autonomous.
So you kind of balance this is
this is why this is kind of an art.
You've got to balance
how small you make it without it
having dependency
on other things to get its work done.
And that's kind of
you kind of move the bar up
and down on that one to figure it out.
And you can tell that you have,
high coupling.
If when you make one change, it ripples
through several different microservices.
Or you can find that
you have low cohesion
if your microservice can stand on its own,
and be able to, to do its own work,
without another microservice
sitting there.
So that means
you probably have low cohesion
and you've created some kind
of the high coupling, more than likely.
So keep these things in mind
when you're out there designing your
microservice architectures.