Okay.
This lecture we're
going to talk about data ownership rules
that you should be using microservices.
As we've mentioned in earlier, lectures,
that I have two microservices
with high cohesion and low coupling.
We should have a database per service.
Most of the time you can do this,
but not all the time.
So we're going to talk about
some different strategies here.
But the goal is that through microservices
each must have its own data.
All right.
And in this lecture we're going
to explain why that's the case.
Identified problems with shared databases
and discuss cross boundary access
and handle a referential integrity
where I've got some data that's in my one
microservice that is referencing data
in another microservice.
And how do I handle that appropriately?
So first off,
a service must, have its data private.
This is this goes back to object
oriented analysis and design,
where you only access the data of a class
in through its interface.
Now, this same concept exists here
with microservices.
I should only be accessing
the private data of that microservice
through the Rest interface,
not through database calls
or anything like that.
That's internal.
And those internal details
have to stay internal,
not through, direct public interface.
So if all you did was write update table
in your microservice,
then you're doing the wrong thing, right?
You need to make sure
that you have your access layer
that's there, and make sure that you have
the appropriate abstractions there.
So if you do change your database
on the back end, not every single
other microservice that depends on
you is going to, have a problem.
So why don't we do shared databases?
Because it,
it, it should be public enemy number one.
First off.
And we don't want these shared databases
because you have
schema lock in, which means I'm
locked into a schema that can't change
or one change in service
A will break service B
and or any other service
that access that service, say.
So that could be a problem.
Performance could be, an issue,
especially if I have service
B accessing the same database, a service a
and service B is pretty chatty,
then it could actually interfere
that called the noisy neighbor
with, extra queries
that it really doesn't need to do.
If it was going
through the appropriate interface
on service A so performance is an issue.
And then last is security.
If you want to do least privilege,
then all of that access
and authorization controls should be
handled through the microservice.
Right.
The authorization
comes into the microservice.
The access is there.
And I know what part of my interface
I can access instead of
accessing the database directly,
or instead of pushing
all of that access to the database
into another database server,
all you've done is uncreated coupling,
which we know coupling is bad.
So what about foreign data?
Now this is a great example.
This is like on my podcast that I do
I've got episodes
episode is pretty well contained,
but an episode
belongs to a podcast,
while podcast has a lot of other data.
So I have a podcast microservice
and I have an episode microservice,
but the episode needs to know
which podcast it belongs to, right?
So in this option, I can say, hey,
if I need to know more information
about the podcast, I can use an API call
or service A or my episode.
Microservice is going to call service B
and say,
here's a key to my podcast
that I belong to, podcast ID and I need,
who the author is or who the,
who the host is of the show, right?
I don't know why I need that.
Maybe I need that for when I'm generating
show notes or something.
I want the host name and
maybe the guest of the show or whatever.
So I'm going to go ask with the ID, I'm
going to go ask, hey, here's the episode.
I need the host name for that.
So that's one way of getting that foreign
data into that out of the microservice.
I'm not accessing the data directly.
I'm going through the API.
Another option is called replication.
This is where a service b
if an event happens, service B
will publish an event
that will be out on an event bus
and service
A will save that into a local projection.
It's almost like a cache
you can think of in some respects.
If I don't if if I need that guest name,
or the host name quite a bit.
I don't want to keep hitting service A
or my podcast service constantly. Right.
So I can bring that in.
I can save it in a local projection,
but there's some downsides to this, right?
There's temporal
coupling that, could happen,
were lots of plus.
Right.
Because I don't have to hit them,
but I can at the con
is that if the host changes,
if it goes from Darren
Pulsifer
to Doctor Darren Pulsifer, for example.
Then all of a sudden,
I have, inconsistencies in my data
in the episode server or,
service B in this case.
So you gotta you gotta, look at the pros
and cons of each of these options
so that you have now referential integrity
is is really important.
This is where I have foreign keys
that I can access across.
It's typically in database systems.
I have a, foreign key in a table, right,
that says, hey,
this, relationship of this element,
there's a row in my table,
refers to this row in another table.
Right.
And so they use foreign keys or IDs
that, integrity
on these, on these foreign keys
is the responsibility of the application,
itself.
Right.
So you have to someone
still has to own those foreign keys,
make sure that they're correct.
And you need to use logic
to handle any deletes
or accept partial inconsistency
throughout your, your architecture.
So you got
you got to understand these, foreign
keys, your IDs, make sure that you're
handling them appropriately.
Let's talk about, a real world
example of the Netflix title
metadata service.
So I've got a metadata service
that owns the titles
and the descriptions
of all the movies on Netflix.
Right.
Then I have a playback service, and a
playback service needs the title to show.
Now, playing,
you know, one of the Marvel movies, right.
Doomsday that's coming up. Right.
And then so what Netflix does is
what they do
is they have a playback service
that caches its own metadata
instead of
constantly hitting the metadata service.
So when you first started up, the playback
service now caches that title.
And this works really well
because the Metis,
the metadata service crashes.
I can still watch my movie.
So I've kind of decoupled,
that dependency, this doesn't work.
Well, if the data is changing a lot
and that you're, asking for, like,
if the metadata on,
the titles and descriptions changed a lot,
then I could have a lot of inconsistency
of data in my architecture.
But if I'm grabbing it once and caching
it, this is a good way of decoupling,
deployment, decoupling,
which can be a problem, right.
Especially if you've got
a lot of these services
and you have a lot of interdependencies
between microservices.
So there's metadata
caching is a is a good, method to use
in most
situations, depending on
how often that data is changing.
If it's changing a lot,
this could be a detrimental.
Okay.
So when you guys are working on assignment
one A,
you should I need you to diagram
in your architectures
what services have what data
and what your dedicated,
DV is going to be.
It can be a relational database.
It could be a, document database.
It could be a file system for all I care.
I just need to see that you are,
isolating the data
and the data can only be, accessed
through the microservice.
And then I don't have two microservices
accessing the same data.
If you have that,
then you didn't create a microservice
architecture.
You created a distributed monolith.
So be more be mindful of that.
Also, I want you to document
how you're handling foreign IDs
like the user ID and your schema
or whatever the case may be, right?
You need to say this is a foreign key.
I decided to do, replication.
I decided to do the API call.
And why did you decide to do that?
So these are important things that
you have to decide for your architecture.
All right.
So in summary data,
ownership is foundational
to autonomy, which is one of the key
elements of a microservice architecture.
It helps you enforce strict boundaries
of the data layer and services.
I should not be accessing.
Underlying data microservices directly,
which means that if you do this right,
your schemas can change.
You can enrich your metadata
on your schemas inside your microservices
without having any effect applied.