Okay.
In this lecture I'm
going to talk about environment promotion.
This is really important for your CI
CD pipeline and the way
that you can deploy microservices
most effectively
and in a consistent manner,
which is really important.
Right?
So most teams run
their software on multiple environments.
You need to have a development
environment, a test environment
and a production environment.
And when you do monolithic programing
this is really easy, right?
Because I've deployed one big application
and it can go through those environments
when you're working in, microservice
architectures.
These environments
have become very important
because you are running
multiple applications.
You are running on a network.
So all these things need to be set up
appropriately.
Luckily, we've got tools like Kubernetes
and Docker,
Ansible all and Terraform.
Those things help set up
these environments
very easily and more effectively
than doing everything by hand.
So you should look into, automating
your CI CD pipeline in your environment,
set up without promotion,
without going through this.
There are some dangers, right?
You have un repeatable releases.
There's no clear ownership for broken
deployments.
We've seen very large companies
struggle with deployments.
Oh, I deployed a new,
patch to a database, and all of a sudden
everything goes down.
These sorts of things, if you look at them
all, can stem back to poor,
environment management,
poor CI, CD pipeline,
rig, governance is the right word.
I'm looking for.
So the core definition of an environment
and environment promotion
means that the same build artifact
can move through the different
environments in a fixed order.
I am not adding when I go in from
development to test and then production.
I should not be adding any code,
any changes to my microservice at all
in those environments.
Otherwise, what you've developed
and what you released
are not can are not repeatable.
And this is a problem
that I've seen in large corporations
in the past, even small ones.
I do this myself sometimes.
Oh, this real quick patch.
I'm just going to plug in after test
and I'll go back to development,
make sure everything's running through or
I see it in test.
I add the patch
and push it into production.
That has cost millions of dollars
for lots of different companies
all over the world.
Remember that artifacts.
You use these environments as stage gates
to protect you from any failures
in production, because that's
where you want to save things
the most is in production.
So a typical pipeline, there's a lot
you can put a lot in here.
I have my build.
I have my unit tests,
I have my integration tests.
I have UAT, user acceptance testing.
I can deploy it into a staging area
to be deployed once
it goes through final approval.
Typically call
those my gold repos, my gold repositories
where I know whatever's there has passed
everything in my test environments,
and then it can move on
to full production.
This is a pretty typical pipeline,
right?
The key here is immutability.
Those artifacts must not change.
And in the past, when we were doing more
lower level code like C and C
plus plus and things like that,
where I've got compilers and other tools
that help generate the code,
those tools
are checked into my pipeline as well
and checked in and all that so that I can,
a year or two years later
if I need a build
with a specific patch on it,
I can go back to that and get that,
repeated.
That tends to be a very, big problem
that we've kind of ignored
because we moved to more software
as a service type of things
instead of deploying
a software on people's, own own devices.
But I can see a big shift
happening in that area, too.
Some common pitfalls to avoid.
Build it once and you're done. Right.
You should have, the ability to build it
over and over again without a problem
and make sure that you promote the exact
same artifact across the environments.
Don't change them in any way, shape,
or form as they move
through the environments.
Common practices are using container
images with tags.
Coming up with a tagging version
scheme is really important.
Having checksums
and signatures for security
and then having artifact repositories
that are locked down.
We had a big,
infiltration by, Russian operatives
in a CI CD pipeline where between test
and production,
they injected code in there.
They got into the CI CD pipeline,
injecting code after the test between test
and production.
Crazy, crazy that that happened.
The company that got attacked
was not using checksums and signatures.
Right.
Because if the checksum was there,
it would have, it would have been caught.
Right. So, well, I could have been caught.
It depends on when the crew created
the checksum.
In this case, it would have been caught.
Okay.
Configuration versus code.
So promoting the same artifact
does not mean
every environment has to be identical.
In fact,
we'll see that there aren't a lot of times
in typically in test environments.
I could have different environments
for test.
Maybe I am doing, testing.
That's doing unit testing,
but no performance.
So I turn all my logging on
for performance.
I'm not going to turn my logging on.
I'm going to turn my logging
at a different level.
So the environment may actually change.
The differences could be,
running environments could be different.
Database endpoints can be different.
Feature flags be turned on and off,
depending on which features on testing
API keys and secrets
most definitely will be different
in the different environments.
Do not just turn off API keys
and secrets in your test environment,
because it's a pain to work with.
Oh, I don't need it in my test
environment.
Still have them,
but you can use a different schema
for for those,
you can use longer lasting keys in those.
What happens sometimes is people
turn them off and then they go production
and forgot to turn back on.
Authentication and authorization.
So that could be, you know, really bad.
Okay.
There are some different deployment
strategies as well.
So once everything gets through to test
and I'm headed to deployment,
there are some different strategies
to deploy,
especially if you want higher uptime.
And microservices are great at this.
One is called the canary release
where I, I take 5% of my users
that are using it and I put them into this
canary production environment.
Right.
So if the production environment
goes south, I can easily turn that back
and then,
wait for the next production cycle.
So instead of just deploying everywhere,
the canary release is all about,
limiting how many people get that,
that new release for a period of time.
And then when it's,
it seems to be full production
for a designated time that use, designate,
then you can switch everyone else over.
There's also blue green environments
where I switch everyone over.
Post, validation.
And now everyone's on the new thing.
And if it starts failing,
I can switch back from, blue to green.
All right, so I can easily.
I can easily make this, I have two
operating environment center running.
Those are some interesting ways to do it.
Also, I've seen this in the past
where I have feature flags
where when I'm deploying,
I can deploy based off of some features
that I've already touched.
So I've already tested
all these features in test,
and I can turn on and off
different features as I deploy,
as I have higher reliability
or higher confidence for my reliability.
I can turn those features on.
That's another option.
Make sure that you set up
your verification
gates in each stage in dev.
There should be some kind of gate,
a test gate
that you have to pass
to get out of dev into test and QA.
Right?
Whether it's a static analysis
or some simple unit tests or whatever
the case may be,
you're probably have a stage gate there
and then you've got testing QA.
Those should all be fully automated,
with some
some stage gating, that goes in there.
And then as we've
already talked in staging,
these are production like checks making.
Everything's
ready to go until I get into production.
Make sure that you have the right
approvals.
Not too much approval,
but just the right amount
before you release into production,
especially if you're in a large system
working for large company.
It can be devastating.
It can be even worse for small company if,
if you have a massive outage
and your first launch, for example,
you need to be able to step that back.
I have been in a major fail launch.
It is devastating.
And if you don't have a way
back, it's even worse.
So watch what you're doing there.
Make sure that you have your checklist off
before you go into production.
Okay.
There's some risks and trade offs
doing this with multiple stages.
Slower feedback to get everything through.
And you can have bottlenecks
in any of the manual processes
that you may have in your, in your four CD
pipeline.
Right.
Common risks that we see,
also are environment drift.
So if development is working forward
thinking
and they're working on new technologies
that may those technologies
may not actually be
in your test environment,
whether it's new silicon features
that the coding against.
And maybe
you don't have all those features
in all the silicon that you're running
in your test environment.
You can get environment drift
and then production.
If you're developing things
that you don't have in production,
that could be, a real pain as well.
And then watch out for manual fixes
in production.
I kind of get this back up
and running quickly.
Make the change in production,
and it never gets propagated
back to development
and runs through the test cycle.
Okay.
When you are developing your services,
come up with,
really good Cicd
or configuration management practices
developers
merging code back into main.
Be wary of that.
There should be some stage gate.
There should be, something there.
Promote
being able to promote something to main.
Make sure that you have
your build numbers,
you know, piling up that
you don't use the same number
for every single build.
Automate your tests as much as you can.
Use the same image
that is deployed in test as you do
in staging and in production.
And then canary.
If you are going to use Canary,
it's it's a great strategy.
Limit how big the traffic is.
But make sure you have enough traffic
there, to test, the things that you need
to and make rollback as easy as possible
in case something really bad happens.
Okay.
Hopefully this will help you, when you're
developing your, microservices.
Because if you put this in up front,
when you're iterating
through these microservices,
you don't have to worry
about your environments anymore.
All that can happen automatically.