Okay.
In this lecture we're
going to talk about Node Express and Async
as a microservice event
loop and asynchronous
and programing technique.
So we're going to use the express server
as our Http
server here,
which is key to handling these events.
Right.
So we're gonna explain the event loop
behavior in express services.
We're going to use async handlers.
And we're also going to talk about
streams just to touch on streams okay.
So real quick node executes JavaScript
in a single threaded event loop.
And this is important to understand
this, that it's single threaded.
Right.
And a lot of people go
that's one of the limitations of node.
It's also one of its strengths
because it handles
IO operations completely asynchronously.
Even though I'm in an event loop,
I don't have to fire up
another thread to do it.
So it's it's they're pretty good for
lightweight small microservices, right.
I can use this
concept of async and async await
that keeps non-blocking, logic
readable instead of through its callback
mechanism that it normally uses.
In fact, it hides the back end,
processing that it's doing,
through callbacks
by putting in these logical,
syntactic sugar in the,
in the language. Right.
And then another thing that it does really
well as the concept of streaming.
So I can stream information
from the back end,
whether it's from a big file system
or even a database
or even a video service, I can stream
that information through this microservice
without, blowing up my memory
and buffering all that memory.
It just it's a pass through,
which is really slick.
Right?
And, you know,
I need to also make sure that I am dealing
and remember that
I am dealing with an event loop and that,
you know, if the event loop is lagging,
then that could be a key,
signal that I've got,
health issues in the process.
Right.
And concurrency limits are protect
any downstream dependencies.
And we'll, we'll go over those things.
So I request flow. Very simple. Right.
I got my express server up there.
It's my handler. Right.
When a request comes in on the Http,
socket that I've opened up,
I get as an async
IO on the event loop, right?
And it's going to go
do something on the back end
and it's non-blocking
so other events can come in
during this time when it gets resolved
and I pass that information
back out to the Http response.
And this is built
in into express, right out of the gun.
Now, if I want to do other things
inside my event loop
that are non-blocking calls,
even though they look like blocked code,
I use this concept of async and await.
So await means async await,
which in so the concept,
the promises are introduced.
And if you don't understand
promises, there's a lecture on promises
that you can take a look at.
But basically a promise says
I'm going to go do something
and I promise to get back to you
when I'm done.
That's the easiest way to think about it.
So in this case here, the promises
all says,
only return back
when all the promises are done.
So, user client get is going
is an asynchronous call,
and there's a promise
there that I'm going to return something.
And when that's done, it will return.
And then when order client list
by user is called.
And this could this is an async call
to another back end process or somewhere.
When both of those get resolved then
and only then will this await get resolved
and I will get user and orders
passed back into these variables.
So if I were to write this code out,
with the callback
mechanism that, Node.js has,
this would be
probably three times larger than this
and it would be very hard to follow.
So this is syntactic sugar
really, beneficial here.
And they've done a great job
at making this easy to understand.
So only
when those both promises are resolved
do I go on to there, respond
with Jason back
to whoever called me in this,
handler of the express, server.
Okay, here
is an example of handling streams.
So this is actually pretty cool as well.
It's an async call.
I create a stream here
called an export stream.
And then I can just pipe
whatever is coming in into that stream.
And I'm just a pass through.
In this case this works really well
for exports of large responses.
Maybe, maybe I'm downloading,
from my microservice here.
Maybe I'm downloading a audio file
or a video file.
So instead of it
bringing it all into memory
and then sending it, it just pipes this
through to whoever made the call.
So this makes it a very fast
and efficient.
It's not,
pulling everything into memory,
which means I'm not using extra resources.
I don't need to.
Okay.
When to use the,
when to use Node.js express and async,
when I have heavy
IO bound, types of things.
Aggregating APIs. This is great for that.
When I have high concurrency
or connection counts,
these all work really well.
Especially the streaming. Concept.
It's a straight pass through, concept.
And it works really, really well.
All right.
Here's some trade offs
that we need to talk about.
If I have blocking CPU type things,
remember, I'm
single threaded right in in this stuff.
So you can
and if I'm, if I'm heavy CPU bound,
then I could actually block
on that event loop.
Remember, the event loop
only relinquishes control
when there's IO
that it's waiting on, right?
But if I'm heavy CPU bound,
then I'm single threaded.
So most of the time
most of the Node.js stuff
that I've worked on are heavily IO bound.
So this ends up
not being that big of a problem, right?
Also make
sure that you bound your fan out,
because you could overload
a lot of dependencies.
If I have a lot of stuff
going on in the back, back, processes
or back microservices that are out there
and make sure that you don't
miss any time out or cancels
cancellations
because you could increase, latency
because you are running
in a single thread.
Don't forget that.
And then you want to monitor
the event loop for lag and heap growth.
Because you can find, people that are
not freeing up memory appropriately.
That way you can blow out
a lot of memory as well.
Okay,
so to recap, Node.js with async and await
are great for high concurrency IO paths.
It keeps handlers on non-blocking
concurrency and concurrency bounded right.
I don't have to set up worker workers
to do this.
Like in some other languages.
I just use that async and wait.
And if I combine, if I combine
these patterns,
I get some really good resilient controls.
However, it can be complex if I don't
handle those promises correctly.
Right.
So handling those is is important.