Okay.
In this lecture I'm going to talk about
idempotency and distributed systems.
This is really unique
to these distributed systems.
And the concept behind.
And we'll we'll describe it idempotency is explain
why it's important in distributed systems.
And with Rest interfaces
there are some that by
default are into potent
and some that are not by default.
And so we'll we'll describe
which ones those are.
And we also want to avoid
the whole idea behind idempotency
is we want to avoid duplicate side effects
when calling the same
the same Rest interface
multiple times with the same
parameters.
So the reason why we have to do that
is because I could get multiple requests
coming into a microservice or
into multiple instances of a microservice.
And I should get the same result
coming back
if I have an endpoint,
a message call, like, get,
then it should give me back
the same thing, no matter how many times
I call it.
The reason why is because remember,
those requests could be retried.
And sometimes there's some timing issues.
I could get the same request
multiple times coming to the same server.
So I need to make sure that I'm always,
returning
the same, thing and that the behavior
on the back end is the same.
So this is essential
for things like payment in order, things
you don't want to have someone pay twice
for the same order.
Right.
And no,
those are some, some, examples of that.
Right.
So also remember your clients
are sitting there trying and retrying.
So it may remember,
RESTful interfaces is a request response.
So if I hit a request and the server runs
and does something,
but doesn't send the response back,
the client may try that again.
Saying, hey,
I timed out, I'm going to try it again.
And the server needs to be able to handle
that coming in multiple times.
So that's the whole concept
behind idempotency okay.
So here's here's an example
in a nice sequence diagram
I've got a post of orders.
Now post happens
to be a non into potent call.
But I can make it into potent
by passing in in idempotency key
which will we'll talk about here.
Might as well talk about it now.
So if I say post orders I may have an a
special ID that I send in with it.
I'm going to check that ID, see if it's,
see if this has already happened.
If it has, then I just return the order.
In this case, if it hasn't
then I'm going to create the order
pass back and ID add
that I'm going to match
to the key that was passed in
when someone gave me the key.
So now I have the key
and the order ID stored in there.
So now when someone calls post order again
with that same in the potency key,
I can check that key against
what happened last time,
and I can send the same response back
and I can say, hey, it was created
and I've already run this like a replay,
message in in the message coming back.
So that's the idea
behind in in opponents is pretty simple.
It can get difficult though.
This is so when you're writing
your functions that handle the different,
method calls in the Rest interface,
get put and delete
by default,
those are independent by definition.
So it means that if I call delete
and I call delete again
on the exact same item,
whether it's an order or user or whatever,
and that is not there
because I already deleted it.
Your answer should be
good.
It's it's deleted right.
Put same thing.
Right.
I've put is I'm putting something
an update to the,
I'm updating the order
if I update the order
and I updated again
with the exact same information,
I should get the exact same result
coming back.
Same thing with get where I get.
I am saying
get me something and return it.
If I call, get
with the exact same parameters.
Or a query string.
I should get the exact same thing
every time I call it,
no matter how many times.
Now post is different
because post I'm actually
creating something new on the back in.
I'm changing the state
of that microservice somehow.
It's not into potent by default.
So there are tricks
you can play, like passing in a unique
idempotency key from the client, right?
The client generates
this key, into the server.
Now the server, can check that
at any time and gets in something
from that client.
It has that key
say I have already done this. I'm
going to give you back the same response
I gave you back last time.
That's the idea behind it okay.
So that will that will help.
With this in potency, remember
when you're writing your functions,
get put and delete.
Should do the same thing every time,
whether it's been called 100 times, 50
times, doesn't matter.
Right?
Post if you want idempotency,
then you're going to have to pass
a key in from the client.
Okay, so
here is an example of a client
request on a,
in the potency post.
As you can see here, I'm passing
in some random,
string that I created, which is my key.
And, that's my in the potency key
in the header.
I'm passing that in.
That's being captured by the server.
The server's
going to store that, in a potency key.
So if I call the exact same thing
again, it's not going to post the exact
same query.
So now I have two skew A123,
quantity one.
I'm only going to have one
if it's identical in potency key
and and all of the parameters
are the same.
Okay.
So that's the idea behind it on the.
Now here's on the server side
I'm going to check out
the in the potency key in the headers.
If I don't have one
you can decide what you want to do.
If you require that
then you can throw an error 400 error.
Say hey,
I was expecting in the potency key.
And if I don't get one, I'm not going.
I'm not going to do anything.
Or you can just ignore it
and say,
hey, if you
don't pass in an in the potency key, I'm
going to assume this is, non-independent,
right? That's another way to go.
It depends on how you've written
the contract that you put in your API.
Documentation.
That's very important to take care of.
Okay.
So architectural trade offs,
reliability is one of the trade offs
we have to look at.
This avoids duplicate side effects.
And it depends on storage.
Which means I have state in
that underlying microservice
which means it could be harder to scale.
Right.
Also there's a little bit of latency
because I have a little bit of extra
lookup that adds hops to the request
that says, hey, did you pass in the
in the potency key?
Not you know, things like that.
There's, more complexity involved
here in the response
replay and logic could be tricky at times.
So you got to watch out for that.
Also, on the client side, it needs
to generate these and the potency keys.
So you need to decide
what what direction you're going to go on.
This one okay. All right.
Recap treat all post as safe
without keys I hit a post
no matter how many times I get it
I'm going to I'm
going to do the exact same behavior.
Make sure that,
you have some time on your,
on your retries.
And give it
give it a little bit of time out on post
because it may be writing
something to the database
and then return something to you.
So you may want a little bit longer time
timeout there
and then try not replaying the same,
response over and over again.
And then also make sure you store
your keys with the response chain
so that you can send the response
data directly back.
Right.
So if they ask for it,
they're going to get it.
And then also don't skip idempotency
when you're talking about money
people's lives
and things like that make sure that you
are doing the appropriate,
and responsible way
of handling idempotency
for those types of things.
Okay. That's it for idempotency.