Okay.
In this lecture we're going to talk about
stateless and staple services,
what the differences are
and when to use them
and what the benefits are of each type.
So, why state matters?
First off, why do I need
your people always saying, oh,
all your microservice should be stateless.
They can't be right.
They can't be.
You need some kind of state sometimes.
Like who's logged in,
what items are in your cart,
where the workload is in its life cycle?
These are all state.
Now there's arguments
and we'll show you some techniques
where I can go actually fully stateless,
but there's some trade offs for it.
So the key here is that you have to answer
is where does the memory live
and the and the choices that it affects.
Right.
Scalability, reliability deployment strategies, costs, all those I have a play.
So core definitions.
First off stateless service
means that it does
not retain any client specific data
between requests.
It's not storing anything persistent.
Each request contains all the information
it needs to process it.
So when that request comes
in everything's in there
that it needs in order to process it,
give you an output.
The state there is no state of of that,
microservice going on at all.
A stateful service will retain the data
across multiple requests,
and the requests depend on the prior
state of what's happened.
Right?
In practice, most systems include both
full stateful and stateless services.
We see this all the time, right?
It's important to understand what they are
when it comes to scaling,
which we will talk about
in the scaling lecture.
But needless to say, stateless is a lot
easier to scale than stateful services.
Okay, stateless services are
easy to scale
because there is no data involved.
I can spin these things up
all over the place, and I can distribute
the, the workload across,
the services,
independent of each other.
No, no big deal, because I'm not storing
any state in some cases.
Some people use like function
as a service.
Great function service is stateless.
That falls into the nano service
and might not be the my most effective way
to use your resources.
And it may introduce latency,
but that that's
a good example of a simple,
stateless, microservice.
But think of it this way the microservice
is there to do one specific thing,
to take the data that comes in
and do something with it
and then produce data that comes out
and never stored state.
Right?
I can easily add and remove instances
at will when, when I do this.
So it's very it's very good for scaling.
Why do I need stateful services?
Well,
if I, if I need to store, persistence
anywhere, I'm, I'm needed.
You know,
store the database somewhere.
Maybe it's inventory in an inventory.
I'm saying I've got state there.
Maybe I want speed up.
Maybe I want to be able to speed
up, lookups and things like that.
I may have some caches in there
if maybe I have a shipping service
that is calling a back
end zip code lookup service,
I may want to start caching
some of those zip code
addresses in my cache
that now all of a sudden I'm stateful.
All right.
Anything that I'm storing in memory,
becomes stateful,
even if I have like a memory pipeline
where maybe I'm doing
several things through the process is
as long as it can go down in any point in
time and I lose information,
that means I'm in a state for a situation.
So if they're in memory processing
pipelines, that could cause problems
or long running workflows,
they are stateful.
All right.
So you got to watch out for that.
Some common examples
I think I've already talked about this,
stateless
reading, writing from a database.
The thing in the middle is stateless.
The stateful one is the actual database
and message queues.
Those are the stateful
once the stateless ones might be,
you know, read,
just reading and writing from a database
and passing the information through
authentication gateways, using tokens.
Just, authenticating and passing
the information on I can have
I can do that all day long.
That's no big deal.
Okay.
Managing state in scalable systems,
this can be really difficult if
if I have multiple,
microservices that are engaged
in some kind of a transaction where,
I need to be able to pass information
from one microservice to another.
There's lots of different techniques.
And why why do you need this?
Well,
I might need some central data control
for consistent updates
across multiple services.
I can reduce latency, by comparing,
to synchronize multiple data sources.
I can simplify my architecture
based off of,
complex state replication architecture.
I can have cross service queries that are
easier with shared aggregate data access.
These are, things that I can,
use in scaling systems
where I need to have some kind of a state.
Another technique is,
passing
in, in the request that the request,
continues to grow its context
as it's passing through.
Right.
There are some dangerous for shared
databases.
You've increased coupling
and probably decreased the cohesion.
At the same time, you need to make sure
that I have version schemas so that all
the microservices using, the same shared
schema knows about any changes to it.
And you still need to have those clear
API boundaries between teams
and make sure that you have defined
ownership.
Typically you want to steer away
from shared databases.
So it's more you should look
for another option if you can.
This should be a last resort.
All right.
Another thing that we could do
is session state and use your context.
This is another state that you would,
store typically a web
app store this session
data in memory on a single server,
and the client
side in the browser will sort store
the session ID.
If I'm scaling on the back end,
then I don't I'm not guaranteed
where this session is going to land,
where a new request from the user is going
to land if I have multiple web servers.
So I use something called sticky sessions
where I'm storing the session
in a central,
shared memory repository
or a shared repository database
like Redis is a great example,
or some kind of, server or something.
And then if a web server goes down, then,
you know,
the other web server can pick up
where they left off.
So this builds my resiliency, which is
good, but also introduces some complexity.
So here watch out for that.
Another option is stateless JWT
stateless tokens where I'm storing
everything in the token.
So anytime I get a response
back from a server I get that JWT token
back in there.
It has all the information that I need,
so it's all self-contained.
That's another option,
but it does increase the payload.
And the response, which could be
bad if it gets really large.
So reliability and failure modes.
Let's talk about this.
So stateless systems they're very easy
to recover from is something fails.
It fails on typically stateless systems.
Microservices are doing something
very quickly
not long term workloads inside there.
Right.
So you're not going to lose,
critical data very much, right?
If you don't get something back,
you just do a retry, into potent,
you know, get or put or even patch then.
Hey, I just try it again.
If it failed, it'll start up
another system.
Stateful.
You've got to protect your data
through replication, backups,
recovery procedures,
all those things you will need.
And there are systems
where you do need state.
So you got to
come up with those strategies
okay.
Trade offs. We always need to talk about
trade offs.
Stateless systems are easier to scale
and deploy, easier to automate.
In CI, CD pipelines and easier
with orchestration.
All that stuff with admin feedback loops,
all that is easier,
but they require
some kind of external state management.
All right, stateful systems,
they can be faster for local operations
like I'm caching something so I don't have
to hit a microservice every time.
I can reduce network, hops
and the amount of,
repeated access that I need for things,
but they are harder
to scale and recover from.
So you've got to make the choice
based off of your architecture
and your use models.
Okay. Examples.
Just give a couple examples.
Stateful,
a cart stored on the server memory.
It's fast.
It breaks, on server failure and scale.
So you got to be careful that a card
stored in Redis or a database, right.
Slightly more latency,
but it survives any scaling failures
because now I've, I've,
I can scale Redis or the database
independent
of the microservices themselves.
All right.
So key takeaways.
And you need to understand
the stateless services is store
no persistent data whatsoever.
Right.
And that they're easier to recover from.
Easier to scale.
All that stateful services
are sometimes unavoidable.
Now a lot of times you're unavoidable.
But not everything has to be stateful.
You can you can limit the number,
and they require stronger operations
as I have. I'm
dealing with persistent data.
Right.
The core design question here is
where does the state live?
It's got to live somewhere.
It could live in a client
generated token that gets passed around.
That's one option.
But the most common patterns that we see,
we have stateless application servers
with shared state stores on the back end
or back end, servers.
This kind of breaks
a little bit of the pattern
that we talked about, about horizontal
versus vertical, which you kind of
come up with your strategy of
how are you going to handle this?
Okay.
You want to use utilize shared databases
sparingly
only when it simplifies your architecture.
But I understand that it introduces
coupling
and which can cause for version shift,
there's a lot of,
schema problems and all those things.
So watch out for watch out for that.
We talk about shared database
in other lectures in the downsides of it.
So use it very sparingly.