Okay.
In this lecture we're going to talk
about microservice anti-patterns.
Things you should not do.
Okay.
So don't do these things right.
Well the goal is to identify
common mistakes and wrong turns that
people make in microservice architectures.
And then the strategy
is to learn to recognize symptoms
and and course correct
as soon as possible.
I'm going to introduce
a couple of really big disasters
that cost
hundreds of millions of dollars as well.
All right.
So, will,
we'll work through these problems here.
All right. Here
we go. The distributed monoliths.
I've talked about this several times.
You know, you have a distributed monolith.
When you've got tightly coupling
that requires all the services
to be deployed together.
That is one of the big symptoms.
If I can't deploy service
A without service B,
I know I have some coupling there.
Right.
And,
there could be, a lot of issues there.
Or if I'm updating one service
and I have to update another service
at the same time, then I have coupling.
I might have a distributed
monolith. Right.
You can really see this happen
if one service fails
and it crashes the entire system.
So we had a big incident recently,
at, AWS.
Right? AWS outage.
I would say distributed monolith.
Not a true.
Oh, it's some of our microservices,
but there's a big true distributed
monolith in there because one service
failed and everything came down.
Right.
That's a symptom of it
as one of the big failures that we see.
Right.
How do you fix this?
You need to make sure
that you have a stable API.
Contracts, including how to handle errors.
You need circuit breakers,
which we're going to talk about next week.
And we need a database as a service.
So I don't have all this, coupling
going on between, the services.
So API contracts critical.
You need to know what your inputs
and your outputs are for each, API call
and also what your error, codes are
and the conditions of those error codes
and maybe even a hint on what to do
if you get them.
Okay.
All right, let's keep moving forward.
The next one is called Nano Services.
Now, I have done this myself.
I, I sliced everything
so thin that instead of having maybe 10
or 20, microservices,
I had hundreds of them running people
that move into function as a service move
in this direction really quick.
And it can
it can be a nightmare to manage, right?
Typically what you see with
this is you see a lot of network overhead
and it outweighs the business value.
So you've got to move things around
where you know, that, where you know,
the best value is going to be.
How do you find those boundaries?
Look at what can be scaled
independent of each other.
Look at where your data boundaries
are merged services together that share
the same context, the same reason
for a change that you have.
So take a look at it
from that perspective.
You can very easily
go to many nano services or not.
Not enough.
And you end up with a big monolith,
or you end up with,
system that's, very complex and rigid.
That's hard to manage.
So you got to find
the, the, the in between.
Okay.
Shared database.
There's a whole lecture
on shared database.
This is when I have multiple services
that are reading,
writing from the same tables,
the same directory structure,
the same MongoDB database, whatever
the case may be in your data store, right.
If I have multiple services
accessing that, I have a shared database.
So I probably have a big issue there
that I need to do.
What do I do?
I need to kind of separate things out.
I need, how
so that there's a single owner
for the data and that should be
that microservice.
Everything else
should be going through the APIs.
The problems that cause here are
that if I do change
any of the schemas, there's
a rippling effect across the code base.
And I have a lot of changes
that happen in all the microservices.
Like I said, there's a whole lecture
on shared databases and ways around it.
Another one is called the Mega Gateway.
So it's really easy at times to just jam
a whole bunch of business logic,
in an API gateway like nginx,
and it let you have business rules
and things I can in there.
But what all you've done is
you've shifted all the business logic
into one microservice, which shouldn't
be called a microservice image
should be called a macro service, right?
Because it has a lot of stuff in there,
and now it becomes a bottleneck.
And you've just created a monolith
with a bunch of microservices
that are being starved.
And that typically happens.
Keep your gateway dumb.
It's for routing SSL,
handshaking, and rate limiting only.
Don't put any other smarts in there.
There's going to be a temptation
to do that.
Don't do that.
All right.
This is a big one too.
Ignoring observability
because you're dealing
with a whole bunch of microservices
that are talking over the network.
Failures happen
because networks go up and down.
There's a lot of variability in networks.
And when you're programing over a network,
so you've got to observe what's going on.
So you've got to log what's going on in
each of your microservices
and do it in a consistent manner.
I, centralized
logging is one way to do this.
Or distributed
tracing with Yaga is another.
But put these elements
into your architecture right up front
so it'll make your life a whole lot easier
when you're debugging.
Really complex interactions
between microservices, which can happen.
Okay, there's a great World war,
real world example of this back in 2012.
And, Knight Capital released
a brand new product, to the market
that they were using for, retail market,
trades and things like that.
And what was interesting,
they had some old code in their code base
that was obsolete,
that wasn't, completely taken out.
And when the new code came
in, it activated this,
old code
because they weren't in microservices.
They were kind of coupled, in a way.
And that coupling of that code,
that old code that wasn't being used,
but now all of a sudden was,
to the deployment
hadn't been, tested with the new schemas
that they had and all that.
And because there were so much coupling
and it caused a $440
million loss in 45 minutes
on approximately $30 billion in trades,
you know, you would say, hey, that's
not that bad, a $4,440 million loss.
That's a lot of money.
So one of the reasons why it lasted
45 minutes instead of a couple minutes
is not only the deployment
coupling that they had,
but they had no observability
into what was going on.
So they couldn't even
shutting down it for 45 minutes.
They didn't even know what was going on.
So putting observability in your code
is very important, right?
And having different levels
of observability and structuring
your logs is really important.
So for assignment one A,
make sure that you don't fall
into the shared database trap it.
And and we're
working in multiple languages.
So they should not be using the same
shared database if they're microservices.
They were doing different things.
If you have two implementations, one
and go and one in Java of your customer,
microservice
and it uses a customer database,
then I would expect them to use the same,
because you're not going to activate
both those at the same time.
Right.
And then make sure that you have logging,
use some structured logging,
to ensure that your service is observable
right from the start.
And so that when it is spitting out logs
that, you know, we can
see what's, what's going on.
Okay.
So remember microservices add complexity,
which means you've got to deal
with that complexity in the architecture.
If you establish wrong boundaries,
then you get, the worst of both worlds,
the rigidity of monoliths and the
complexity of a distributed system,
which means debugging is harder,
crashes are more.
I mean, it's
this is really bad if you don't do this.
Right?
So, stay vigilant
and work on the design patterns
that we talk about in these annotate
patterns. Check.
Use a generative
AI to check against these design patterns.
Be very specific.
Don't just say, hey, tell me if
this is using good design patterns.
Be specific and say,
am I using, the anti-patterns?
Am I using a shared database?
If I am, what can I do to overcome that?
Right.
Do I use observability correctly?
Do I have good logging?
Am I have I
created a, mana, a distributed monolith?
Why have I created it?
Where's my coupling?
Do I have deployment coupling?
Do I have data coupling?
All these things you should be asking
instead of just a broad question
across the board.