This lecture talks about Conway's
laws and time boundaries.
Now, Conway's Law is an option.
When we look at systems.
Architecture fits
really well for microservices
and these new architectures that we have.
So we're going to understand
what Conway's Law is.
See how organizational structures
are shapes systems design.
And then we're going to learn
about some team boundaries.
Make sure that they're intentional
with your architectural boundaries
that you have.
And be aware of some common risk
and trade offs when using this technique.
Now, Conway,
where Conway's Law was developed
by Melvin Conway back in 1968,
and he basically said this organizations
that design systems
produce designs
that are copies of communication
structures
and channels of those organizations.
So in other words,
the way that people communicate
shapes the architecture of
the systems that they build.
So we've seen this time and time again.
And when we talk about systems
back in the 1968,
these were not like necessarily
computer systems.
They were systems in general.
So a lot of process in engineering
and things like that was going on.
The great news is,
is that these sorts of techniques exist
today and can be leveraged when you're
designing your microservice architecture.
So why it matters.
Well, first off,
the architecture mirrors team boundaries.
Departmen one budget lines, time
zones, and locations,
vendor and regulatory boundaries.
Those are some architectural boundaries
that we can look at.
And if we can identify those
and we can do a better job at
creating our microservices to mimic
that when they're misaligned.
What happens is
I have higher coordination costs.
Slower delivery
times, longer lead times, unclear
ownership and blame
shifting starts happening.
Now you would say, well, Darren,
that's for the 1960s, 1970s.
Sorts of things were processed.
World today same things happened today
with microservice architectures,
especially when you've got teams
that are focus on one architecture.
There's a lot of finger
pointing on whose fault that was.
So these same techniques can be used
in microservice architectures today.
So when they're aligned, when everything's
aligned,
things move faster, safer to make changes.
There's clear ownership of components.
Architecture
that evolves more smoothly happens
and it mimics
what's going on in the real world.
So there's some benefits when they're
light right now good and bad alignment.
This is really easy to define right
when you when it's happening right.
When you've got good
alignment business capabilities,
are aligned to teams.
So for example payments catalog
onboarding these these sorts of things
that I've got full stacks
that are for the category team,
for the payments team, when you've got
one team that manage their part and it's
mostly independent of the other parts,
you have low coupling, high cohesion.
So which we've learned in software
engineering,
that's that's really important.
When you've got bad alignment,
what happens is teams are aligned to
technology layers UI team, API team,
database team and infrastructure team.
What happens is you create
high coupling between the components
and between the organizational structure
and which increases lots of
handoffs, slow feedback loops,
all those sorts of things happen.
So remember, you cannot architect
a microservice architecture
without understanding
the organization that you're working in.
You can cause a lot of problems.
All right.
There's another technique out there
called the inverse Conway maneuver.
Now what this says is I have my structure
of my, solution structure. Right.
My microservice architecture structure.
And I'm going to align
my organizational structure to match.
Now, this can be highly effective,
especially if you can leverage
a lot of software techniques
like reuse and,
portability and things like that.
Right.
If I want to leverage
those sorts of benefits of,
I only have to write one database
application that rules them all. Then
aligning
your team structure to that may work.
But here's the problem.
Organizational structures
have a lot of inertia.
They're very hard to change.
Especially
they've been around a long time right.
So you may want to do that, but
you may find much more difficult to do.
Now some people try and use the inverse
Conway maneuver
to kind of circumvent Conway's
Law and defeat it.
That doesn't work, right.
Because what you end up doing
is you end up putting another layer
of abstraction in there, and that can't
handle the changes very effectively.
And all you've done
is, move to the park, around the ice,
to a different place, and it really didn't
solve the problem at all.
Right.
So if you want to try the inverse,
maneuver,
then you define your architecture first,
then you create your team structure
around that architecture.
It could be very difficult to do, but,
you know, it's it's
one of the things that, is possible.
Right?
You still can't ignore Conway's Law here.
It doesn't get you around it.
It's just you're taking
it from a different angle.
All right.
Let's talk about misaligned boundaries.
How do I know that my microservice
architecture has bad boundary,
boundaries around it, right?
First off, if a small feature requires
3 to 5 different teams
and or microservices,
then you've drawn poor boundaries.
Make sense?
If I have frequent cross team meetings
for minor changes.
Bad, bad boundary alignment.
Okay.
If shared services or modules
with funny ownership.
Oh, we created this shared module,
but we don't know who owns it.
Right.
Is everyone owns it.
Bad misaligned boundary.
Walk away from that. Right.
You got to Re-Architect.
If the roadmap conflicts
with the same code over database areas,
then I've got misalignment.
If architectural diagrams
show clean domains,
but the repos and services mirror
the old architecture, then
you have misalignment in your architecture
and your implementation.
Right? Another, another symptom.
All right.
So let's look at some principles
to help us design better boundaries.
Right. Follow value streams.
Look at the value stream
of what's being produced.
And look at those value streams
to draw some great boundaries there.
Also optimize your architecture
for change.
Aim for the most changes
to be done by one team.
Instead of
I need three teams to make this change.
So look at look at your architecture
and figure out, all right,
where can I do that? The most?
That all goes into that
decoupling and cohesion.
That we want high cohesion, low coupling.
Right.
Limit
the cognitive load by giving each team
a specific coherent domain instead of
multiple domains or sets of systems.
It's very hard
for someone to keep track of everything.
And then also last one,
make sure your interfaces between
the microservices are explicit
with clear APIs,
events, and contracts
between the different microservices.
And that will, reduce the ad hoc,
coordination that you need.
All right.
Let's talk about using Conway's Law.
In practice,
when planning the architecture, go out
and find out who your teams are
and what they own,
what processes they own,
what data they own.
All those things are very important.
Also, find out how many teams are involved
in a typical feature
or typical service that you're delivering
to your customers out there.
Also, when you're planning
organizational changes,
look at what architectural changes
need to be made or what naturally emerge
from this new structure, right?
So it's almost like, a dance
between your microservice architectures
and your org change.
Remember, the org change is leading
typically, right?
They're slower to change.
I can change code much faster
if I architect it correctly
than the organization can change.
All right.
When when you know
that the change you're making is wrong.
Slow delivery.
Constant integration. Friction.
Unclear ownership. Right?
Remember, it's not just code.
You're dealing with people here.
And that's really important to understand.
All right some key takeaways.
System architecture tends to mirror
communication structures okay.
Team boundaries are very important
to making architectural decisions.
Right.
And they will actually be,
an architectural decision in disguise.
So you might as well uncover it
and identify it.
Use the inverse Conway maneuver to steer
the architecture via team designs
if you have to,
and then align the teams with business
capabilities best, which can.
This is an opportunity for you
to make some fundamental
digital transformation
changes in your organization.
And then last but not least,
watch for symptoms of misalignment
costs, explosion coordination
cost, confusion, slow change,
lack of ownership.
Those are the things
that you need to look for.