Okay.
We're going to talk about identity
and session concepts.
This is, really important to understand
when we're talking about microservice
architectures and also just straight up
client, web server type, type of things.
But what we find in the web server client,
application
applies to microservices as well.
So the idea here is that
we're going to focus on what is identity
authentication authorization.
And sessions.
And how do we use those to identify who's
talking to me, who's asking for things.
And are they authorized, to do it.
So that's the idea behind it, right.
By the end of this, you should be able
to distinguish what identity
authentication and authorization is
and identify what a session is, and
then differentiate between user identity
and service side, then the etc., etc..
Right.
Identity and
sessions matter because in modern systems
there's lots of lots of different users
and devices of services.
I can have one microservice that's used
by several different microservices
that may have differing
authorization levels that I need,
you know, to manage.
So I could have one service service
a that's accessing service,
B but can only access read things,
it can only read things, it
can't update it where I can have service
C that can read and write.
Right.
So those that
that's a simple example. Right.
And so those are some of the
the things that we need to handle.
And then also I want the concept
of a session.
Remember Http requests and Http
servers are stateless.
So when I get a request in I need to know
the identity of the person and
and what state things are in.
So we do that through
storing session IDs and being able to pass
those session IDs around
so that I know who's calling me
and which transaction they're working on.
Okay, so identity,
who or what is it
could be a user device or service.
It has lots of attributes
that I can put in there.
Authentication is
you prove to me who you are.
You proved to me your identity.
I can do this with passwords,
tokens, biometrics, whatever,
whatever the case may be.
And then authorization
is someone with a specific identity
that's been authenticated is allowed to do
XYZ, whatever, whatever the case may be.
And that could depend on attributes
or roles or permissions or contexts.
There's lots of things
I can do with authorization.
Okay.
So the easiest way to think about this
is that a user is going to provide
credentials, password or single sign
on to identity, provider.
Or I'm going to look up,
in that identity provider.
That's then going to pass down
the identity and the claims.
Right.
It's authenticated user down
into an authorization check that then will
access the API and the application
that sends it back to the user.
So simple.
The user identifies
who they are to a pass password,
for authentication.
If they authenticate correctly
I pass that down to an authorization
with the identity and the claims
and then the authorization checks. Yep.
They're allowed to do that.
And then they can go ahead
and do whatever they want.
But now a session, is a link
between the identity
and the series of interactions
that they've already had over time.
I typically and there's a whole lecture
on sessions that you need to go check out,
but I typically store those in the server.
In the microservice,
the session I, ID is generated
from that microservice
and it tells you in there who's logged in
if they're authenticated or not
when they were authenticated,
and then any security context
that they have authorization levels,
whatever the case may be.
Okay.
And then,
this session is an ongoing interaction.
It stores the ongoing interaction
with, the microservice
and that session or transaction
that it is working on.
It could be time bound.
It includes log in time
expiry and context,
and it can be revoked
and renewed all the time.
So these sessions are really important.
If you've got a microservice architecture
where you're dealing with transactions,
where a, session ID
can be passed
around multiple, microservices,
so I can keep individual state
of those session,
sessions across, the,
ness of microservices
that you've established,
right?
Typical session web flow.
A user opens up
a login login page, the web server,
validates their credentials
that pass in their password, validates
their credentials, storing a session ID,
they can easily come back in this session.
Idea is stored in the browser,
which is a client in this case.
And then they click profile
and they get the right user look up.
On the other hand
you know, in recent times
we've seen some of the big,
gen I, cloud service
providers not use session
IDs as cookies and pass in the headers,
but passed in as a query
in the URL
as a query parameter.
Really, really bad, right?
Because someone can easily take
that session ID and become somebody else.
Very simply,
especially when you've got weak security.
This is happening.
It was just fixed
in the last couple of months
on some of the really big cloud
service providers that,
obviously
didn't know what they were doing.
As as long as security goes right.
How do you
represent a session is typically a session
ID, right, that you have,
that is stored on the server
and I can pass it through.
I could pass it through the calls.
I'm storing the session
either in a cache or in, memory.
Another, concept
is a self-contained token or JWT,
and the token carries identity
claims state and things like that.
So this he just gets passed around
the servers know what to do with the JWT.
And it can have the information in there
that needs to do, whatever's next.
Okay.
Session should be time bound.
They shouldn't last forever.
You should, typically, an idle
timeout is a good way to go.
You could do an absolute timeout as well.
You could start up new sessions
if they're asking to do something risky.
Like,
transfer money from your bank,
for example, or, you know,
anything that can be, destructive.
You could ask for a new session, new
authentication and all that stuff.
Right?
But if you want some apps to remember,
then, you,
you know, you you need to, to, understand
that that's risky as,
the longer
the session goes out there, the,
larger the attack surface.
Right?
Use your identity and service
identity are,
the only thing really different here
is that the user represents a human. And,
and but underneath the covers, really?
You should be treating any client
that comes into your thing
as if it's a user or another microservice.
All right, that's how I would.
That's how I would do it.
I would use tokens or, certifications,
to do this over just an API key.
API keys are not as secure,
but they're easier to work with.
But you've got to make that decision
inside your architecture itself.
Since API keys are easier to work with,
a lot of people use those
for a microservice
to microservice, communications.
Okay. So,
you can have the case
where I've got a user identity
and a service identity, and I want to mesh
the two together, meaning
I've got a user
that's logged into a front end service,
and I want to pass on that identity
to a backend service
for, like, an order entry system.
Right.
And in that case, I can combine
the user and the service identity,
gather from the front server and pass it
into the back service so that it knows,
hey, I know the front end
service is asking me to do this,
and it's asking me to do this
for this specific user.
So it's almost like a proxy.
Not not quite a price,
but it's the combination of the two.
Right.
And this propagating of identity is
is pretty common.
We see that in a lot of applications,
especially in the e-commerce,
side of things.
Make sure that you are not
passing these things in as,
that you're
using Https to pass these things in,
and then you're
passing them in as headers,
not as query parameters.
I, you do have some issues with Csrf
and, session hijacking and cookie theft.
Take a look at the, lecture on that.
There's a whole lecture on cookies
and sessions and Csrf.
So take a look at those, for more details.
Commonly
we set the authorization headers
in the bearer token.
That's a common way of,
setting those tokens across
when you're communicating,
between different microservices.
Okay.
Let's talk about trust boundaries.
So we've talked a little bit about this,
before,
typically your API gateway that you have
that gives you,
external clients access
to your microservice,
cluster that you have, everything is going
to come through that API gateway.
So that's a good trust boundary
that you can establish
and you can authenticate and authorize
everything there at that, gateway.
And then on the back end,
you can make sure
that the services know
how to talk to each other,
and I can forward any trusted claims
through that API gateway.
So that's where I would, add the user
claims or service identity right there.
So now you're combining tokens
and the API keys together
that are being passed down in,
into handling
those internal service calls.
So that that's one technique you can do.
The only downside to
this is if someone gets through
your gateway in your trust boundary,
you know,
they have access to all those AI,
microservices that you have.
So you got you got to be careful of that
sort of thing.
Okay. Session hijacking.
This is when you can impersonate the user
by stealing their session ID.
And the only way
to prevent those sorts of.
There's lots of different techniques,
but one is don't make your sessions
really last really long.
Right.
So install the, cookie or token
out of a browser.
That could, that could cause a problem.
But another way that they can steward is
if you're doing coms that are not Https,
if it's just Http,
they can snoop on your network,
grab those, tokens and keys,
and now we come.
You all right?
And that is a big mistake.
Another common thing that we see
people doing is storing in their logs,
session IDs,
and, and tokens and things like that.
And that's another, mistake, especially
if someone's infiltrated your system.
Now, you've exposed all the microservices
as well.
Okay.
Any time that someone logs in regenerate
a new session, ID
even if you are,
he even if you've got microservices
that are talking to each other
and you want a new, don't reuse
the same session over and over again.
If it's a new transaction, create
a new session.
That's a
that's easiest way to do it. Right.
And this way you can, segregate,
if someone's got access to one session,
they're not,
infiltrating, all the transactions
that you want to make, right?
And remember, don't store your tokens
where exactly where they can easily be,
infiltrated by an XSS attack.
We've already
talked that there's a trade off
anytime you create a session.
So if I have a single session per user,
that means that,
it's easy to log them out of everywhere.
When I just shut down that that session,
they're easier to manage
when I go to multiple concurrent sessions.
That's, it's it's more secure, right?
I've got multiple,
devices, multiple browsers.
But I need a way of tracking.
Who this person is and whether,
you know,
they're going to, conflict with each other
and they're much more harder to revoke
if a user saying,
I don't trust that user anymore, I have
multiple sessions, I gotta go clean up.
So that's that's one of the downsides.
But multiple concurrent
sessions are more secure in general.
Member sessions,
can be stateless or stateful.
Stateful means of storing session
data on the server itself.
They're easily to revoke and centralize.
Stateless is where I it's token based.
And I'm storing really storing the state
in the token itself
because the state is a combination
of all the attributes.
And if they can scale out really easy,
but they can be harder to revoke
because now I've got that JWT token
that's, moving around,
my microservices
so they can be hard to track down
and revoke
because they're not centralized.
Okay.
So take a look at the other,
lectures on cookies and csrf
API tokens, inserts, OAuth two and Iirc,
which is our authorization
and then er contracts.
So this kind of pulls
all that stuff together.
Make sure you check out
those other lectures.
And remember we're starting with identity
who authorization prove it. And
or authentication prove who you are
and an authorization.
What can I do.
Once I proved to I who I am right.
Sessions helped me balance secure
and that your session architecture
is going to help you balance security,
usability and scalability across
across your microservice architectures.