All right.
In this lecture we're going to talk about
monolithic versus modular versus
microservice architectures
so that you can understand
what the differences are
and the trade offs are for each.
A lot of people say,
oh well, everyone knows microservice
architectures is the best.
There's some downsides to it.
So we need to look at each
one of these independently
and so that we can make good and wise,
architectural decisions.
So first, we want to build
a clear vocabulary
for systems composition.
We need to understand the differences
between monolithic,
modular,
monolithic and microservice architectures.
We should be able to identify
and recognize each style and where it
fits, and identify
key risk and trade offs for each.
Okay.
First off, monolithic right?
Application is one big application
with code
UI, API domain with one database, right?
A shared database, even if it wants you.
That's that's what that is.
Modular
monolithic says I have multiple modules
that can be developed independently,
but they may share the same database.
And they own certain tables per module.
But the application itself
is all built as one application.
It could be
multi-tiered too, but it's all released
together.
All, all deployed together.
Modular, monolithic microservice
architectures say, hey, look,
the application
and the database reside together.
A user database does not have order data
in it.
And the order database,
well, he has order data, and there's
an order service tied to that database.
Right? Same problem space.
Three different architectural approaches.
Typically microservice architectures.
You're
going to have a lot of communications
between these microservices.
Right.
What this does is it draws clear
boundaries between the microservices.
You can only communicate
through an API call
that is very well known
with with modular monolithic.
Sometimes you might have a library
there that you're calling.
There's ways around things.
I've seen it myself. I've done it right.
And then a monolithic it's a free for all.
It turns out to be a spaghetti code
a lot of times,
unless you've got a lot of discipline
on your engineering team.
Okay, so why does this matter?
Well, modern systems
kind of outlive the original design.
Great example is there's a piece
of software that was written in the 60s
that is managing Department
of Defense contracts
on mainframes
written in COBOL, still out there today.
Amazing, right.
We're talking 60 years
that code has been running
approaching 60 years.
Amazing, right.
So a lot of times we have to understand,
hey, we should really develop things.
And, and have the ability to add
new features and teams and traffic on it.
Right.
Architecture that works for one team
for one year fails.
All the time. Right?
If I try and scale it.
So let's look at microservices is an often
slogan and not a reason decision.
We got to watch out for that
as well. Right.
So we need to understand
the three different styles
of what's good for what sorts of things.
We've seen some major blow ups
and microservices,
especially in cloud service providers,
where, they, they use the microservice
architecture, but they didn't follow
good design principles.
Right.
And we had some major failures.
But, because of that.
Okay.
Monolithic. Let's go deeper
into monolithic.
Most monster,
all the code is in a single runtime unit.
So the UI, the business logic,
the data access is all in one
monolithic application, one process, one
artifact, one database.
Right.
Tends to give tends to lead to more tight
coupling over time.
But this is easy to deploy,
very easy to deploy.
If I have a small application
it's not doing a lot.
This may be the way to go
if I have a small cohesive team,
this may be the way to go.
Instead of a
I'm going to break up this into, you know,
5 or 6 different,
microservice architecture.
Microservices.
But it's, a small application
for a small company.
You may have created some complexity
that you don't need.
So understanding that is important.
Okay.
Simple deployment I already mentioned.
Great for small teams, easy
for local deployment.
Some of the cons on this could be,
it can become
a big ball of mud or spaghetti
if it's not structured properly.
Requires more discipline
from the software engineers.
It could be much harder to scale.
If I need to scale.
And you have a risk, factoring risk,
grows, with time and with the size.
So these are
the things you have to watch out for
and be weary.
Sometimes you say
this is just a small application.
In a small company,
what if they hit big all of a sudden?
You've got a code base
that is, rigid and hard.
Hard to scale.
It runs great,
but you may not be able to scale on to it.
So you got to watch out for that
sort of thing.
All right, let's look at modular.
Monolithic. Still one deployment. You.
But now I have libraries in there.
And with the advent of shared
libraries in 90s this was huge, right.
Because now I can have a library
that can be shared
across multiple applications.
Which was great.
But it requires, clear internal module,
a lot of, boundaries that are set clear
API definitions that are set.
And if you don't
define explicit interfaces
between the modules,
people tend to go around them
and they'll use things directly
in, in internal, calls directly,
which they shouldn't be using.
And this is when I get tight
coupling again.
So people fall back
to, hey, I really need to get this done
in a short period of time.
I don't have time to go coordinate with
someone to get a new interface, developed,
and they circumvent it.
I've seen this, I've done this.
This is what typically happens.
So some of, some of the pros.
Well, first off,
think of it as a bunch of logical servers.
Services with one physical deployment.
Again, some of the benefits
it keeps the operational simplicity.
I have one application
when I deploy it, it's simple.
It's easier to maintain
than a big monolithic because I can focus
my changes on one library.
And easier to refactor
if I divide my interfaces really well.
There's clear ownership
between the different, libraries,
and you can set team boundaries up,
for that.
And there's an easier migration
path to microservices later
if I want to go that route.
But still, I have one failure.
If that deployment unit fails.
Right. So I got one failure point.
If it fails on on toast. Right.
And requires
discipline to keep the boundaries clean.
Right to define those well-defined
interfaces for the libraries
and not circumvent them. Right.
And there is a whole industry
built around this where I can do,
I can do both dynamic and static code
analysis to see if I have,
coupling problems,
to see if I have cohesion problems.
Whole industry was built around, around
analyzing code,
both dynamically and also statically.
So great tools out there.
This is where we've been, developing
for 20, 30 years in, in this space.
Okay.
Microservices again.
Now what microservices is done
is I have multiple independent
deployable services out there.
They're independent.
They can run by themselves.
They may not be able to do much,
but they can run by themselves.
Like if I have an order service out there,
and
I don't have any users,
then I've got a problem.
But the order service itself
can handle orders all by itself, right?
When it's getting requests
from the outside.
These services have their own code base,
their own processor, their own container.
They own their own database
most of the time in their own
schema, they communicate over networks.
I mean, there's lots of different network
protocols, Http, gRPC message,
protocols that are out there
that, we're going to look at all those,
in, in lectures coming up.
All right.
Some of,
the, the best way to think about it is
each service can be built, deployed
and scaled independent of each other.
So this is really great when you've got,
bottlenecks in your architecture
and you need to scale,
maybe your ordering, process
or your inventory check process
takes a long time.
I can scale those up
independent of the ordering process.
I don't have to do them together.
So that's that's a great benefit.
So strong alignment with team boundaries
as we talk about in Conway's Law.
Right.
Independent release cycles
of the individual.
Individual microservices
and much better for, fault
isolation and fault tolerance.
Right.
If I've got one service
that's causing a problem,
I can make a change quickly
without shutting everything down.
Right now, I've shifted the complexity
to operational deployment
and and maintainability.
Because now, instead
of managing one application or one binary,
I'm managing three for a dozen,
a couple dozen.
And I'm also handling,
their different versions
that are coming through.
I also have to handle network failures,
timeouts, retries, versioning is in there.
It's easy to create a slow
and fragile distributed monolith.
I've done this.
I've seen it.
So you got to be careful of this, right?
Establish your boundaries effectively.
If you don't, then
all you've done is a distributed monolith,
which all you did
was take all the cons of the monolith
and the cons of a microservice
architecture and fold them together,
and you've got a mess on your hands.
All right.
So if I can, if I can compare them
to deployment in ops,
the easiest one by far is monolithic
and modular
microservices
a lot of artifacts complexity, right.
Code base.
Right.
Monolith.
There's nothing in there
that prevents, coupling.
So I can have tight coupling.
Modular is a little bit better
as far as, code
because I have the concept of interfaces
between the libraries,
but there's nothing enforcing
those contracts.
Microservice is totally enforced.
You can't have one microservice accessing
the internals of another microservice
unless it's through an interface.
So that kind of forces
the hand of the application
developers
or microservice developers, right?
As far as data and transactions.
Monolith one database easy asset
across all the features,
but there's blurry ownership on who owns
what, what data sets and data tables
or whatever the case may be.
It's a little bit clearer in Modular
Monolith.
But you can have table ownership
per module and you can do some,
permissions around that.
But you've shifted some of some of the,
complexity into the database server
with microservice architectures,
per service data.
No easy distributed, acid.
So that's a problem.
But,
you need sagas and eventual consistency
across multiple databases so that that's,
something you got to deal with.
So as we mentioned before,
microservices
isn't always the right answer.
You got to look and see what's going
to be most effective for you.
Okay.
When each one fits, let's go over this
real quick.
Monolith.
New product, small teams, fast iterations,
requirements changing all the time.
Great fit for that long
term use is limited.
You're just looking for something
quick and dirty.
Monolith modular.
When I got multiple development
teams, one deployment still,
I want a clean architecture
that's with clear ownership
that moves me from monolith to modular,
and then it might involve
some microservices later.
I can take those individual libraries
and fold them into microservices.
As long as I adhere to the,
interface boundaries that I established.
Microservices are great
when I have multiple teams needing
independent deploys, large,
complex systems with distinct
scalability needs, and the organization
has operational maturity as far as CI, CD
pipelines, observability, and freestyle
practices.
Here's the problem though, right?
In microservices
that you need to be careful of,
you still need to architect the system.
You don't just go, oh, I'm
going to ignore the system architecture.
Microservice
will architect their own thing
and it'll be ad hoc at the top.
If you do that, you end up with a big
monolithic mess is what you end up with.
So you still need our architecture,
microservice architecture,
not the individual microservices.
You need to do that,
but also how the system operates.
Holistically.
Okay.
Here are some failures.
Premature when you move to microservices
too early, when you have a tiny team
and a lot of services, there's a lot of
time spent on boilerplate and debugging.
Not on feature development.
Now, this is hard.
Debugging
microservices is difficult, right?
You've got logs coming
from several different, applications.
If it's all running one application,
it's really easy.
All your logs are in one place.
You can set breakpoints really easily.
Right?
That that can be problematic. Right.
So watch out for those sorts of things.
Also a shared database with microservices
typically you don't want to do that.
You want to have a database
per microservice.
If you have multiple services
that are directly hitting a, a database,
you've just created a distributed monolith
to watch out for that.
Also look out for over modularize
monoliths,
where I've got tiny of hundred modules
and with little business
meaning at all.
So understanding
the size of your microservice is going
to be important, right?
If you go too deep into a, well,
too broad, right?
With too many, tiny microservices, you're
going to slow everything down, right?
And it's gonna be harder
to understand the whole architecture.
You gotta create boundaries,
create the boundaries around business
capabilities, not just technical layers.
That's Conway's law,
right?
You need to also make sure that you have
an ability to evolve your architecture.
If you need that, then,
moving from monolith
to modular, you need to identify the major
domains, start establishing
those, those libraries
and establishing interfaces between them.
If I'm moving from modular monoliths
to microservices,
you should already have those interfaces
well-defined.
You're gonna find out real quick
if anyone's circumvented those interfaces
when you move to a microservice.
So make sure that you,
mimic those APIs,
move them out as an individual service,
and you'll find out real quickly
if you had a problem or not.
Okay,
so the most important thing that you guys
can do with microservice architectures
and choosing between these three,
choose the simplest architecture
that involves that solves today's problem,
but with a eye towards
enough modularity
that you can solve for tomorrow's.
Right now,
since we're
talking about microservices
in this course,
we're going to skip from monolithic
directly over to microservices.
But we are going to start
with a simple monolithic
that can take API calls
and things like that
so that you understand the design pattern
around developing your own microservice.