All right.
On this lecture I'm going to talk about
the event loop and inter process
communication in microservices.
So the goal here
that we want to talk about in this lecture
is how that event
loop works in microservices.
So it can get different events
from different requests
coming in from different microservices
or clients that are asking.
And we need to also show how a blocking
IO reduces throughput.
And we're going to introduce the concept
of promise async and async await.
And we're going to care.
There's a lot going on in this one.
Compare two microservices and three
microservice event driven communication
where we got all that
and we're going to contrast single
threaded versus multi-threaded models
handling that event loop.
So there's a lot going on in this lecture.
So first off
event loops maximize IO concurrency
for handling
non-blocking and stay non-blocking.
So that event loop sits there and is able
to handle multiple requests coming in
and then processes those
and then goes back and waits.
And that's the idea behind it.
But if I have back end processing
that I need to do in my microservice,
then I,
could be blocking more requests
from coming in
and being, processed quickly.
So what happens is you get a buffer
or a queue that gets,
created with all those requests coming in,
and then the event loop just tries
its best to process
what it asks to process
and then go processed
the next one coming through and
get lots of different languages out there.
Use this same kind of event loop
and there's some subtle difference.
And so we're going to talk about
some of those differences.
And we're going to talk about
multi-threaded and single threaded.
A lot of them are single
threaded out there
which makes it programing much easier.
But there's some multi-threaded techniques
that are available in
like Java, for example.
So let's look at the event loop.
Simple event flow through the event loop.
A client
sends in an Http request to a,
a microservice.
There's a service event handler
that's in there that handles that request.
And then, it will go schedule
that work to be done in the event loop.
Right.
That event loop says, okay,
you need to do this work.
Go run
that work in the in the service handler.
And then it's going to do
whatever work it needs to do.
It's going to go ahead and run that.
Maybe it's going to start a query
on the database or whatever it is.
And then when it's done with that, it
returns a control back to the event loop,
which can then, send the event back to
the work that needs to be done.
So it's very simple.
That event loop sits
there and just does its little, work.
An event comes in, it says, oh, handle
that event.
I go work on that event or on that
function that that event is tied to.
And then when I'm done,
I return the result back
to whoever
call me through an Http response.
Okay.
But here's where the problem occurs.
The problem occurs is
when I've got a client
or I've got multiple clients
that are attached to the microservice now.
So in this case here
I've got client A that sends in a request.
Right.
I need to handle request A right.
It's going to go through that.
All right I go ahead and I handle that.
I'm doing a synchronous
read on a database.
Maybe slow IO write
database tends to be or
out of a file system,
whatever the case may be.
Right.
So while it's processing in
in getting that information,
waiting for
to get that information, it's blocked.
Meaning A is not getting the response
back.
Right.
And not only A isn't
getting a response back, but
I can't handle any other events
until that one comes back.
In the meantime,
request to be
comes in from client B
into that event loop.
And the event loop says
okay, I'm going to put that in queue.
So it puts that request in a queue
while it's
waiting for request
A to finish, handling its work.
When it is finished.
Then request will handle that work,
respond all the way back to client
A, and then it will process D request,
and it will go ahead and handle
B's requests and send it back.
So what happens in this case is a request
A comes in response to ask
request B
comes in and request
A since it was handled first.
It's going to get its response back first.
When that response is done then request
B comes back and handles its response.
So I'm getting events coming
in, you know, in a certain order.
And they're going to come out
in a certain order.
But the problem is, is request
B is now waiting for request A to finish.
Oh right.
And that could be the start of latency,
especially if request
A takes a really long time and request B
maybe it's short.
So now it has that dependency.
There.
So let's take a look.
If I use this concept called promises.
Now what a promise is is
it is basically this
data structure that stores,
almost like a mini program counter
in there.
Right.
And it stores, the information
about that request that comes in.
So when a request comes in,
in the request comes in.
And then I'm going to process
that request.
So instead of processing the request
I instead
I create a promise that I'll process
that request in the future.
That's what I do.
I just create a promise
that I'll process that in the future.
Then I go back to the event loop and say,
is there anyone else that needs
any work done?
If the answer is yes,
then I go ahead and take that request
and then if it's an async,
I do the same thing.
I create a promise that says
I'm going to do this later for you.
Then when there aren't any requests
coming in any spare cycles
that it has in the event loop,
it will then go process
through all of those promises.
So I'm going
to process through that promise.
And depending on
how you set up your promise queue,
most of them are first in, first out.
That promise is going to get resolved.
It's going to go off
and do all that work,
go ahead and fire and do all that work off
and then when you're firing
to do all that work off,
go back to the event loop
so that I'm not blocked anymore.
So that work goes off and gets fired.
When all that work is resolved, done
right.
Let's say I've got an external API,
another microservice on the back end,
or a database, right?
When I finally get that result back, it
says, hey,
resolve that promise.
And then the resolve says, okay,
I resolve that promise.
Now I'm going to return back to where I
left off, where that promise was created.
And then it goes back into the event
loop and says, hey, I got it.
I got the results of that promise
that you put in there.
So it's going to say, okay, I'm
going to unfollow that promise.
Right?
Because it's been sitting in the queue,
I'm going to untie the promise,
put the results back in there
and then I'm going to say, okay,
what do I do next?
Oh, the next step is to,
hey, go ahead and send that off
to the client that came in.
So what this allows me to do in the back
end in a single thread with this, promise,
event loop concept is
I can handle multiple requests coming in
and I am no longer blocked by client
A and client beer.
Client one and two.
Whatever request comes
back first
is the one that gets sent back first.
So if I have a really slow back end,
for certain types of requests,
they could come back in a different order.
And in the case
that we're looking at on this slide,
client two has a faster
client to request comes in
and the actual promise gets resolved first
because it's actually accessing
something on the back end that's fast.
So it gets its response back first.
And then client one sitting there will get
its response back later when it's done.
So it mimics as if things are happening
somewhat asynchronously.
But we're handling that
just through this concept of a promise.
So that's what promises are, right okay.
So how does this get implemented.
It gets implemented with some key words
that you see in many of the languages
that are out there today.
It's called the async await.
So async says this is going to be
an asynchronous process
which means by default I'm going to create
a promise inside of it.
And that I'm going to wait
until it resolves before I return.
That's what an async function is, right?
I'm going to return
when that promise resolves,
or the promise errors out either
one, right?
So await the word.
The key word
await really stands for async await.
So this says don't return.
Don't don't start this block of code again
until all the promises that were passed
back or the promise that was passed
back is resolved, or an error.
If there are an error, then there's a try
catch block to handle all of that.
So in the case of the code
that I'm looking at right here,
I have an await
that, is waiting on the promise
of two calls, a user client call
and an order client call.
So both of those will return promises.
And I'm going to say I'm going to wait
for all those promises to resolve
before I continue on with the next line
of code, which the next line of code here
is a response in Json of the user
and the orders.
So this makes it really easy.
So this says this is an asynchronous call,
which it is
because I have an await inside
and what happens when those
both of those promises get resolved.
The one coming
how to use your client in order client.
When both of them get resolved,
then I'm sending a response
back to whoever
called dashboard with the ID.
Very simple.
Hey, here's
an anti-pattern
where I'm actually blocking, right?
So someone asks for a report, I'm
going to go read that file,
and I'm going to block, I'm going to say,
don't do anything else
in the event loop.
I'm going to go read this big old honkin,
you know, maybe
it's a gigabyte
or a terabyte large Json file.
Why would I do that?
I don't know,
and I'm going to return that file back
when I'm done reading it from the drive.
And no one else can do anything
during that time.
So I'm blocking.
Okay.
So that's a different thing to if you look
it follows block programing in in this.
And this follows block programing two
with some syntactic sugar in there.
All right
let's take a look at two microservices
and how they they operate here
I'm going to show you two different ways
that this is happening.
So let's let's take a look at them okay.
In the first diagram here
a client is going to ask for orders
of the order service.
And I'm going to persist those orders
I'm creating a new order right.
Doing a post order
I'm going to persist that order request.
And then I'm going to say to an event bus,
hey, order was created.
That's a one way
call back out there, right?
So this is using an event bus to do this.
All right.
That event gets fired on the event bus.
I have an inventory service on the back
end that's just looking for event created.
Then it's going to do its work.
It's going to go ahead and reserve
some stock in the inventory database.
And then it's going to pass back
that reserve.
And then the inventory
service is going to go yep I got it.
Send that message
back out to the message bus
which will then get passed in
because I'm waiting.
The order service is waiting for
that event.
It's been subscribed to that event.
It gets that event and so on and so forth.
So if you can see right here,
I get by using events
and asynchronous communication between to
microservices, I get a
result back to the client very quickly
that, hey, your order has been created,
but I did not get your orders
been fulfilled in that first one.
In the second one,
if I use asynchronous programing
in the microservice itself,
then in this case here
I'm using the async in await.
I can persist that order, I can reserve
the order, reserve this stock
and you can look and see I'm not returning
anything back from inventory service.
Gets its response back.
Then I'm returning back to the order
service microservice.
Hey, I got that back. And then I'm.
And then I'm sending a response
back to the client I got it,
it's there.
And it's been fulfilled.
So you can see there's some simplicity
in one compared to the other,
but there's more flexibility in the first.
Okay.
Here is a service event driven.
So with event driven like I showed you,
this is where I use a publish
and subscribe and a message queue.
So the broker here is publishing out.
Hey in order was created
and the the back end,
consumer or the one that's doing the work,
the inventory is looking for those events
and it's going to go ahead and do that
inventory reserve.
So that's the difference.
On dealing with events
I'm doing with direct calls.
All right.
Let's look at
if I have three microservices.
And here I need some choreography.
But between the different things and who's
going to handle that choreography.
Do I handle it on the message pass.
Do I handle it through message passing?
In this case
here, the client creates in order,
I get an
order created event
that gets sent out on the message pass.
Who picks that up?
The first one that picks that up
might be the inventory service.
And there's a payment service
that picks set up to.
Hey, they created an order.
All right.
The payment information is in there
as well.
So both inventory
service and payment service
get those events
and they can go ahead and do something.
Now in in this event
do I really want to pay for something
if the order has not
if I don't have, inventory for that order
and the answer might be no.
So in that case, I then pass an event
that, hey,
the inventory has been reserved, but
I'm not going to say that everything's
done yet because I need to pay for it.
So now I have, an event on.
Hey, the inventory is reserved
and the order has been created.
Now I can go ahead and authorize
that payment.
The payment happens,
and the order is complete.
So here I've got several messages
that I need to call choreograph.
And most that query
choreography happens in the order service.
In this case.
So in this case here's another example.
I've got some subscriptions
to different events
and how those events are handled
by the different,
workers here,
whether it's the inventory, worker
or the, payment, worker.
Right now
there's other techniques that I can use,
which is a synchronous Rest event.
So this is where service A call service
B over a KTP directly.
Right. Instead of an event bus.
And in this one I'm saying,
hey, I'm going to check out,
I'm going to check out with my, cart.
I reserve the information, I reserve
the inventory, I hit the database,
with that, reservation or in this case,
I'm going to check out of a hotel.
This is what this case is,
and I just passed that information back.
But remember, in this case,
the client is completely blocked
until everything is complete.
So this can be very long
wait times for, the client.
Right.
But these are simple calls, right?
These are I'm going to do a post or a
get or a put to a specific endpoint.
And that can be that's demonstrated here
using Node.js with like Axios Post.
And that's a direct call there.
Right.
We've talked about a lot of the blocking,
risk involved in the blocking, lecture
that was done earlier.
But here's another example
of how how it happens.
Right.
I could get two requests coming in,
to a service handler.
And, because I may be calling
another microservice
on the backend or a database or something.
And if it's slow
or if maybe I'm in a retry block,
heaven forbid,
I'm in a retry block right where it takes
maybe two minutes instead of,
you know, 200 milliseconds.
Request to in
this case is completely blocked.
May even timeout.
And now I get cascading
timeout failures in my,
architecture.
Right.
So those are the kind of the differences
between things.
So here are some differences
between, the different methods.
So I've got the synchronous call.
The strength is I get that immediate
response back from a request.
And the main risk
is that blocking, concept.
But I did have some mitigation here.
I have timeout, circuit breaker,
bulkhead and fallback positions
with events
where I have a broker in the middle.
I have temporal decoupling, which means
that events can happen out of order.
And I no longer
have that latency dependency.
That could be there.
The main risk here is eventual consistency
and duplication of delivery,
because the events are coming in
in all different orders,
and I don't know who's processed the event
and who hasn't and things like that.
So with these, I need to make sure
I have in into potency.
I have correlation IDs,
I have retries and things like that.
When things, timeout.
All right.
Let's look at some of the languages
and what the languages do here.
Right.
Node.js for is an event loop,
a single threaded event loop.
And you can do multi-threaded,
but it's, it's it's more difficult.
It's really good for heavy IO APIs and
but avoid any like CPU heavy, handlers.
And that's because of that async
IO wait stuff.
So that works really
well for that sort of thing.
Okay, it can do multi-threaded,
but that's optional.
Python built in with their async Kio.
They have process workers and I can say
each request that comes in or
type of request can fire up a new thread,
or I can stay single threaded
and I can use that async await.
Just like I have in Node.js,
Java uses, reactive programing
where each each one can come in a thread
per request,
which is really cool,
but my programs can get very large,
based off of that.
But there's lots of really cool technology
out there, like spring,
spring in, model view
controller, is the thread per request.
Web flux is a reactive event,
a loop handler.
So there's Java
has some really cool things in it,
but it comes with complexity.
Go uses go
routines and runtime scheduler and.
Net pulling. It is not single threaded.
It is multi-threaded.
Right. So it uses a different scheduler.
It has currency built in and control
with go routines and channels and context.
So this one's actually pretty cool
the way that they set it up.
Rust has both single
threaded and multi-threaded.
It does have, locking threads and
to to io,
which is a concept
that's the same as the promise
concept async in await.
So I can
offload blocking work
to different threads as well.
So you can see that as a language
is the newer languages have, have gotten,
some new technology in there
that is easier.
Java has the most technology in there.
It's been around a long time, but can be
deemed somewhat complex to work with.
Okay, let's take a look at single
threaded versus
multi-threaded models just real quickly
so you understand the difference.
So with a single threaded model
I have my one event loop.
And I can use these async await to mimic
some asynchronous type of programing.
And I can have asynchronous
IO on the back end.
It can attach to multiple different
microservices on the back end,
but it's one event loop in
a in multi-threaded each request
that comes in.
Or it could be each client that connects
depends on how you have this set up.
Could be its own thread
that's working with that request.
Right.
So those requests come in,
a worker thread gets fired up
and works on it and then shuts down.
Now there's overhead with threads
at both in timing and in resources
that you need to be concerned about.
Java dealt with this by having,
virtual threads,
which are very small
but they are a duplication but very small.
Part of the of the work is duplicating.
They're pretty fast.
So they kind of have done
some really interesting things there.
So that's the main difference
between those two.
All right.
So common patterns
that we see across all the languages
IO paths can be non-blocking or bounded.
I can make them synchronous
or asynchronous.
I can add timeouts and retries
and backoff policies.
I can limit my fan out and queue depth.
So I don't have big problems
with blowing out my queues and using all
my resources.
And I can propagate cancel ization
across all downstream calls.
So if I have a cancel that comes
in, you've waited too long.
I don't want you to do any more.
I can propagate those calls
all the way down.
Make sure that, into potency events
on the consumer side are happening.
So something is called
multiple times that I'm not creating, a,
a payment every time, if that,
if I, that I can use
correlation IDs to make sure
that that happens appropriately.
Okay.
So to recap, event loads
are there in every single one of them.
They can handle things
multi-threaded or single threaded.
I do have blocking
io that can cause problems
but also can can create some stability
as well.
Take a look at promise
async and await as preserving
those non-blocking flow right
so things can continue to flow.
And you may want to
look at how you're going to handle
multiple 234, microservice
coordination and choreography,
using events instead of, direct calls.
Right.
And take a look
at the different languages.
Some languages might be useful for some of
your microservices over others.
That's one of the beauties
of the microservice
architecture, is I can pick the language
based off of the need.