All right.
In this lecture
I'm going to talk about reactive streams
and the concepts behind them.
If we already if you already listen
to the async, lecture and specifically
the back pressure, push pull and hybrid
reactive systems are hybrid.
A push and pull and,
and there are, libraries and frameworks
that have been set up to make this easier
for the programmer to, to work with us.
And so we're going to talk about
these reactive stream concepts.
And we're going to touch on
just very lightly some of the frameworks
that are out there today.
So if I look at reactive streams
it's all about asynchronous programing.
And it's making sequences
based off of those asynchronous things
so that I can say, hey,
I want to process this bit of data.
I maybe a million times, right?
Or this type of data
and a million bits of it, through
maybe these five, 10
or 100 different sequential steps
that happen and maybe,
maybe some might even be in parallel.
But there's some sequence
that happens through these things.
So it's great for like,
oh, data processing,
certain certain
things that I need do a lot of.
Right.
So this is where the consumer can remember
consumers here are the workers, right.
The workers are requesting demand
from the Up channel.
So it's almost backwards.
Most of the time.
We go out there and say, hey,
I need someone to do something for me.
Go do it right.
In this case, the workers are out there.
And in this lecture we call those
the consumers of these requests.
So those workers are out there saying,
I can handle this much.
And there's a contract
that gets established between
the people requesting the work
and the workers on the back end.
Right.
So the producers of the requests
can run at different speeds in this case.
Right.
Which says that a, I may be,
running really fast
as I've got to do all this stuff.
And,
there may be a whole bunch of workers
on the back end saying,
I can handle ten of those.
And I have a million of them. Right.
And then another one says, I can handle,
1000 of those, another 50,000, 100,000,
whatever the case may be.
So this allows things to run
at different speeds, and the back pressure
keeps the throughput stable under load
across all of this, which is really cool.
Okay.
Why this matters push only systems.
As we learned in previous, lectures,
I can overload down service.
Streams are down service, microservices,
which in this case is the consumer.
Right.
So the back pressure says, hey,
don't overwhelm me, dude.
Right. I can only handle so much.
So that's for that back pressure concept.
So with the push only system, I can
overwhelm the back end with a pull system.
I can actually slow things way down.
Maybe even too much where the consumers
are out there saying, I can do ten now,
I can do 50 now, I can do 100 now,
whatever the case may be.
So the combination of both of those
is that hybrid combination.
And that's
what reactive streams are set up to do.
So the back pressure on
hey how much can you give me is actually
formalized through a contract via
something called a request.
So I can say, hey, the front end,
that's asking for some saying
I need to do a million things.
And the backend worker
consumer microservice
saying, hey, I can take 100 of those.
So naturally the producer of the request
is only going to send that number in.
And, I'm going to be able to get those,
those things back.
Now, what's really cool about
this is I can compose these,
blocks of work that need to be done
through microservices,
through composable operator chains.
Now, this is actually really cool
because I can pass that same data
from that client that's calling,
back in microservice a microservice B
microservice C, D, ad infinitum,
that,
that is going to flow through all of them.
I can pass that composable operator
chain directly into the first one
and then lay down all the rest.
It will, handle all the back pressure
of all the other ones going through.
Right?
Which is really slick.
That's what
Reactive Streams really handles. Right?
So the core concept here is the publisher.
Remember, they're the ones that are asking
for all the request and the subscribers,
the one handling that request. Right.
A subscription
is that contract between the request.
Right.
The subscription is hey,
I need to do this many things.
And also I can cancel, right?
If I'm the one asking for work to be done.
And I say I need to do a thousand things
and I get maybe halfway,
halfway through the workers
halfway through and I go, you know what?
I've decided to change.
So I need to cancel.
So that's part of that, that, contract.
That's a expose there, too.
And then here are some of the signals that
can come back, some of the events like,
when I subscribe, right
when a consumer is,
sitting there saying, hey,
I'm, I can I can work on these things.
When someone subscribes to a,
I want to tell you that I can do that.
I have that signal on subscribe.
So that's an event that comes in.
Another one there is called on next.
So that says all right
I finish what you asked me to do.
What's next.
And then there's on air.
And then on complete
these are events that get passed.
Right.
So I need to be able to notify the requester, hey what do I do if there's an error.
What do you want me to do?
Right? I'm going to send you
I got an error.
I got something completed.
I finished
all the requests that you asked me to.
I finished the one request.
That's the on next, type of thing.
Then I have this concept
that this is actually pretty slick
concept of operators.
So an operator can say, I'm
going to take that data that you gave me,
and I'm either going to map it,
I'm going to filter it, I'm
going to do a flatMap on it,
I'm going to reduce on it.
Right.
These are different operators
that can happen in these reactive systems.
And then I've got some terminal signals
here that are
hey I'm done completed or on error
I got an error.
Don't know what to do.
So those are the ones that kind of shut
down that stream that you've established
in these reactive streams.
So we've already talked about back
pressure, but I want to go over it
one more time,
make sure everyone understands consumer is
the one that is saying, I can do the work.
That's the worker.
The publisher is the one that's saying,
I got work for you to do. So
in this case here,
the subscription has already happened.
Right?
And the consumer says, I can take two.
Give me two.
All right.
Perfect.
So what happens is I get two events
and on next event from the publisher
here's one.
And here's two.
Right. I handled the two.
And the publishers pausing.
It's not going to send me
any more information
until I'm done with those
and say I can take another one.
And then I'm going to get an on next event
from the publisher, the one asking
for the request to the worker,
the consumer on the back end.
Okay.
So let's look at stream, you know,
connecting these streams together.
Right.
The subscriber says to the publisher,
remember this subscriber
is the one asking for work
to be done right.
The publisher is
is the one that is actually doing.
Oh no, I got that backwards. The
the publisher cost.
The publisher is saying,
hey, I need you to do this work for me.
The subscriber is the same thing
as a consumer, right?
Publish and subscribe consumer.
We need one term.
There's too many terms on this.
So the the publisher is saying, hey,
the subscriber
saying I can do work for you.
And it says, all right, I gotcha.
And, I can do three things for you.
Comes up next requests.
Then I say, here
are the three things that you want to do.
And now I'm done.
I'm done asking for more things.
And that's how that works.
All right.
Here's a simple example of
let me make this a little bit bigger
for us here of, in a Java Java Flow API,
they have the concept of a publisher where
I'm publishing and a subscriber.
That's why we use this right here.
The publisher is subscribing to the
the worker basically.
Right.
He's saying, hey, one, once you do
things once I'm connected,
I'm going to send out two requests,
that I can get done.
So the publisher here is subscribing
to work that, could be requested.
Remember, the publisher is the consumer.
It's the one that is actually
doing the work right?
So he's asking, hey, give me work to do.
When on next is called.
Go ahead and do that work. Right.
So here the publisher is submitting things
to be done.
Okay. Let's take a look at the Node.js.
Now this is Node.js doing the same thing
with a library called RxJS.
So in this case here I have different,
operators that can happen.
And I can set up a pipeline
where I'm setting up this pipe
and it's doing the same sort of thing.
I can I can limit how much is being
pumped through at a time.
So take a look at our XJS.
We'll go in more depth
on these, in later lectures.
Okay.
So practical uses of these streaming APIs
where I can tie
these together, event processing,
where I've got pipelines
with multiple transformation stages
that have high,
IO and heavy integrations
where blocking is very expensive.
Look at real time analytics and telemetry
processing, fan out and fan in
work, flows that are controlled on demand
where I can control those.
I need x number of these things
because I've got a big low coming in
or decrease them.
Okay.
Let's look at some examples here.
So you want to use streaming endpoints.
When I've got clients
I can consume partial results over time.
They're great for notification, progress
speeds, large incremental payload
type of things.
They're strong fit for really long
running workloads with intermittent status
that I want to hey,
I want to say how far I've gotten so far.
Avoid them for simple Crud endpoints
because,
they are complex,
to manage and debug as well.
So if I have something that's simple and
easy, like a Crud endpoint
with a quick database call on the back end
and then go with a simple arrest,
interface here.
And look at some,
you know, more simple synchronous style
when latency and load are low.
Right.
Because you are adding some complexity
to, to reactive streams.
Right.
When do you use them?
I already talked when workload is
IO bound with unpredictable latency,
when throughput and concurrency matter
more than, simplicity.
This is a big trade off and you need
bounded resources under burstable,
traffic.
Right, so that you're not blowing out
all your resources.
And make sure that you can support
non-blocking stack
and reactive, observability,
so that I can debug these things
and then make sure also
that I've got event and stream semantics,
that follow what the business flow are.
Right.
Because if you do that mismatch, then
what you've developed
is not going to be used
when you don't use them,
when simple crud can be used.
If I have CPU, CPU bound logic,
then I'm not getting a lot of benefit
here, right?
I could use different technique.
I when teams lack reactive tooling
and debugging, experience is hard to do.
But that's why you're taking this course
so you can learn it.
And remember this is just an introduction.
We're going to have several lectures
on specifically,
reactive frameworks
and the concepts behind them.
Okay.
Here's,
here's like a back of the envelope.
You can choose reactive streams.
If at least three of these are true,
traffic is bursty
or concurrency are high,
the downstream latency is variable.
Overload protection needs to be,
demand aware flow.
So control it's very dynamic right.
In the end,
non-blocking infrastructure is available
and output is event driven
and incremental over time.
So you need at least three of those
to happen.
There aren't a lot of use cases
where this would be true,
but it's important
to understand these things.
All right.
Let's let's take a look at trade offs
throughput.
Obviously strong concurrent.
So this is good for strong concurrent
IO heavy workloads.
Resource safety.
It reduces overhead risk
complexity.
Huge, right.
It can be hard to debug,
especially if you don't have your operator
chain set up appropriately.
Make sure that you understand
what shared reactive
programing is like.
It's not, trivial.
So you have to wrap your head around that
and then make sure
that you have observability in there
and that can be hard, hard to do.
Okay.
Also be careful that you're not mixing
blocking calls inside reactive pipelines.
This could be really, detrimental
and cause some, some, issues.
Also, having unlimited buffers between
operators can cause a lot of problems.
So you want some push back?
There because operators
may operate at different speeds.
So make sure that you have some, limits
there.
Also make sure that you're not ignoring
any of the cancellations,
errors, timeouts and things like that.
And then don't overuse reactive styles
where simple crud
would be the best way to go.