All right.
In this lecture I'm going to talk about
scaling strategies for microservices.
So this is just the beginning
of of scaling.
We're going to go more into depth.
There's several several different lectures
on different scaling strategies.
But this is kind of the,
the top high level overview
of some of those scaling strategies
that you should be looking at, right.
Systems are often designed early
for just traffic, minimal traffic.
And then they sometimes will experience,
a growing user base or seasonal spikes
or whatever the case may be.
I released
a, a new product when I was CIO,
and we released a new product,
and we did not scale appropriately,
and we were down within,
like 30 minutes of launching.
He was a total disaster
because we did not plan
for the scalability that, that hit us.
We weren't even close to
to getting, the numbers that that hit us.
The idea here
is that when a load does increase,
that we can act fast enough
so that we don't lose users
and so that we don't lose,
other, applications
that are using our stuff
through, timeouts and through,
retries that aren't, are being serviced.
So we need to be able
to sustain this growth and not just throw,
hey, I'm just going to throw
a whole bunch of machines at it.
But we also need to shrink as well.
Okay.
So there's two fundamental directions
in scaling.
There's horizontal and vertical.
So with vertical I'm
adding resources to a single machine.
More CPUs more memory faster storage.
That's vertical scaling right.
This is expensive to do,
with resources and time.
If I already have it on one machine
and I need to scale vertically,
how do I add more CPUs, more memory
and storage?
That can be very difficult to do.
Let's. I'm using some cloud techniques.
I can scale vertically and dynamically,
but it is it is, more difficult.
A better way to go that gives me,
more machines
and a more distributed load, but adds
maybe some latency to it
is horizontal scaling
and this is scaling out.
I can have more servers
behind a load balancer,
but I am introducing more latency
to the system and more complexity.
Right. And additional costs. Right.
I can partition the data and services
across multiple nodes.
These are all really good strategies.
So if a user has
a distributed
request comes in actually to your, your,
microservice, orchestrator,
I need to distribute requests,
a load balancer gets hit and then
the servers are spun up to handle the,
those new, requests
coming in with vertical scaling.
I just add more CPUs and memory.
Now, there are some really cool techniques
in virtualization
that let me scale VMs up, but not down.
So keep that in mind.
Has a way of doing
virtual, vertical scaling.
All right.
Let's talk about stateless
and stateful implications of scaling.
We've talked about stateless
and state for a microservices before.
Keep this in mind that stateless
microservices are easier to scale
because they have no state,
which means they're not storing anything
locally.
There's nothing persistent.
And I can just
click those things on very quickly
and spin them up quickly.
So wherever you can in your application
where you think
there's going to be a bottleneck
or you need to scale, you should work on
making that a stateless microservice.
If you can keep the stateful services,
in another place, stateful
services can be scaled, but it's harder.
You do have to store session
data in local,
and so you've got to share some data
between some of the microservices
tends to cause some coupling
that could, have problems.
You have sticky sessions,
which is a new technique that you can have
a session span, multiple microservices.
So these are some techniques
that you can use.
But like I said, if you can go stateless
for scaling
that's a far better than stateful.
But there are some techniques to
do stateful service scaling.
Okay.
Some common tactics.
So you want to optimize your code
to reduce
expensive calls and improve queries
and add indices and things like that.
When you're talking about data,
you can cache things pretty aggressively.
So you're not maybe going
and hitting another microservice.
Every time you need something,
you can cache something
that turns something into, more stateful.
But there could be some benefit.
And there are some in process caches
like radius and CDN that you can use for,
keeping these repeated results in memory
and reusing them.
You can scale vertically.
This is you by a bigger machine.
Immediate release happens that way
for, new, new CPUs.
I there's so many,
cores in these brand new servers
that are out there, it's amazing.
And memory.
And so you could go bigger vertically,
but that can
cause cause
you some, expense that you don't want.
Right?
You can look at horizontal scaling
by adding more nodes in and distributing
load.
You have to make sure if you're
architected properly, this is pretty easy
on, on stateless,
microservices,
if you're having a data problem
and you want to scale horizontally,
then you come up with, data partitioning,
strategies like sharding databases
or splitting services.
And making sure we kind of do our best
to keep that
a microservice has its own database,
concept in there.
Okay.
Load balancing.
So load
balancing is pretty straightforward.
I've got a someone is sending a request
in, it hits a load balancer first,
then the load balancer picks
which server to, send the request
to to distribute the, the,
the load the requests,
and then that that server
actually responds back to the user.
Right.
There's lots of different,
load balancers out there.
Some are at the network level
and some are at the application level.
So either a TCP or up at the application
layer at layer seven http
health checks can help check if server
A is, running slow compared to server
B, things like that.
Lots of different strategies on these load
balancers and schedulers, right?
Typically round robin works pretty good
where I just go around in a circle, right?
That tends to work pretty well
for most systems.
More complex
and more busy systems have a much more,
sophisticated,
load balancing, algorithms.
Okay.
Some of the concerns you want, though,
is that, evenly distributing the load
that have fast failover and with minimal
overhead as much as possible.
So you want to make sure
that schedulers really fast.
Some other things to help with,
scaling is
if I see that
I'm let's say that I have a,
a zip code, a zip code lookup service.
Okay. Very cool.
Right. A zip code lookup service.
You give me an address
and I look up the zip code for you.
Very cool.
Let's say that,
I've got a, a shipping server.
Right.
And the shipping server
or service is geared towards a specific.
I decided to create shipping services
based off of state.
Which state are you in?
I might want to do a little crazy thing
in cache.
Some of those, zip codes
that I'm getting from the zip code service
I based off of, address.
And I may want to, cache that.
So if someone's using the same address
multiple times
that, I might be hitting that backend
server every time.
This is a scaling strategy
that works pretty well as client side.
Caching.
There's server side caching as well.
There's lots of different strategies here
for caching.
The downside that you get with caching is
you can get stale data,
you can get invalid, caches.
So you got some complexity there and
you could increase your memory, usage.
So it's an interesting
it's a good strategy,
but she can't just store everything
and keep it forever.
That can cause you some problems.
All right.
Let's talk about data layer scaling.
If everything's
hitting the same database,
I can absolutely run into some issues
here, right?
Especially read and write.
We all know that read is much faster
than.
Right.
So, I can have a bunch of read replicas,
that I have,
spread throughout my architecture.
That could be really interesting.
Sharding is a technique
where I actually split the database
up based off of some key in a table.
And,
so now, when someone asks for something,
I can go to a specific shard
and get that database
that has all the information
in that shard, based off that key,
there are trade offs with this, and
there are some really good back
end systems that handle this stuff
pretty much seamlessly for you now,
which is really cool.
Some great storage, techniques out there
that will do a lot of this stuff for you,
but you still need to know that
the technique exists and that it is valid.
Especially Kafka is a great example.
They have partitioning and sharding
that you could do on your Kafka servers
if you overwhelm them,
that, increase performance dramatically.
Let's
talk about asynchronous workloads, right?
This is where I just fire
and forget, right?
Which is really kind of cool, right?
Because I can just fire something off
and it's like a one way call,
and I'm not waiting for,
something to come back.
Typically you're going to do this
with, like, message queues,
but you can make, process.
You can do, asynchronous calls as well,
with other techniques.
Those aren't the only ones.
Just message cuz
you can go directly to sockets.
And you don't need a response back
with the rest API.
Not so much.
It's always synchronous, right?
Some of the benefits of this is it
smooths out any spikes,
decreases the amount of traffic
that you have going on,
and it keeps the user facing lower
latency.
They get they
they get a response back quickly.
They may not get an answer back
from back in service, but at least
the user is not waiting
for something on the back.
Yeah,
and it also allows the back end services
and workers
to scale separately from the front end.
And we will talk a lot about asynchronous
workloads and queues.
I'll later on in the course
write some of the trade offs.
Scaling is not free.
It's going to cost you money.
Whether you're
increasing the amount of memory,
whether you're adding more servers,
there's a lot more moving parts
that increases,
failure modes and complexity,
grows,
which I've got to manage that as well.
And you've got to balance this
performance calls versus cost constraints.
Yeah. This is what makes you an architect.
You've got to understand
what the cost benefits are of everything.
Okay.
An example scenario here.
Imagine a product that launches
and the traffic doubles.
All right.
What strategies could I use?
Right away
I could have caching your database hits.
I can use, I could scale the web tier
to horizontally behind a load balancer.
I can, if the bottleneck
becomes a database, I can use sharding.
And, read
replicas is a good way to go with that.
There's lots of different steps
you can do on this.
So we are going to talk
a lot about different scaling techniques,
this whole semester.
So key takeaways is understand the pluses
and minuses of the different scaling
techniques that you have.
And look at and make sure
that you can understand vertical scaling
and the benefits
of that over horizontal scaling.
And then stateless
services are a whole lot easier
to scale than stateful services.
How you can use asynchronous
and caching techniques.
That will give you,
scaling pretty quick.
And then also typically your data layer
usually is the hardest part to scale.
So, watch out for that, where you can.