Okay.
In this lecture I'm going to talk about
retries, timeouts and backoff.
These are typically they're always done
at the client side of the rest client
server interface.
But remember as a microservice
you could be both a client
and a server at the same time.
So you gotta pay attention
to how you're doing this
and make sure,
because you might be a server that you're
propagating the appropriate errors
back up to whoever's calling you.
If you get something down on the bottom
that's causing you not to be able to do
your work, you need to let
other services know as well.
All right.
The reason that we have
these techniques is because networks,
are not as reliable
as just a single system system.
There's a lot of
environment things going on
that can increase latency.
You can drop packets,
other services can become overloaded.
You could have temporary outages.
There's a whole bunch of different things
that you're dealing with
that you typically don't deal
with on a single machine,
running on one CPU and things like that.
Right.
So we need to make sure that we have
some reliability in our system.
So this ability to retry,
to have timeouts to back off
all these are key design patterns
that we need to look at.
So core definitions timeout.
What is the maximum time I'm going to wait
before I give up from the client
I send something through.
I don't give a validation back.
I'm going to timeout after a certain time.
Retry says I'm going
to deliberately retry a failed request.
And I use and I use it
when failures are likely temporary.
So if I get like a timeout,
I may try it again.
Right?
If I get an a real a real error
like on the back end server crash,
I may try it again, but if I get an error
that's a client error, like a bad request,
I there no reason to retry there.
Right back off.
Says that I'm going to retry,
but I'm going to retry.
I'm going to wait longer
before I retry again.
Right.
So I'm going to not retry retry retry
retry or retry.
Wait a little bit. Retry again.
If it's still fails
wait a little bit longer.
Retry again there
we'll talk about some both strategies
okay.
Not all failures that you have
in these client
server
relationships in microservices are equal.
It could be a client error.
It could be a server error.
It could be a network error.
And the the error codes
that we talked about in previous,
lectures talk about the different types
of failures that we have.
And it's really important to understand
what those are and use those effectively.
They should be described in the contract
that you have with the client
and the server and the rest API.
Okay.
All right.
Why do we need timeouts.
Let's talk about that
without timeouts a client if I'm
if I'm sending something to a, a server,
a microservice on the back end,
and I'm stuck and I don't have a timeout,
I could be stuck
waiting for a really long time.
I minutes, hours.
If she do it that long,
I need some kind of a timeout. Right.
Which if I do that,
that means other threads and resources,
can be completely blocked at that time.
So I'm sitting there kind of waiting,
right, without without doing anything.
It can also cause cascading failures
because all of a sudden I am blocked.
I'm a microservice
that's waiting other other microservices
up the chain or user up the chain that's
using me is going to try and access me.
And now I can't take that request.
So I timeout up.
I have a long time for them to wait.
And you get this cascading, block
that happens, which is no fun and can
cause a lot of grief for you, especially
when you're trying to debug things.
So if you do set your timeout,
what you should make sure that it's short
enough to fail fast,
but long enough to handle any normal
latency or variance in the system.
So if you're doing a third party app,
your timeout may be a little bit longer
because you are going out
over the full blown internet.
Then just staying within your own network
and out there in the full blown internet.
With microservices,
it can be a wasteland of noisy
neighbors and things that give you
different performance numbers.
Each time that you run.
So it is
important to identify
the correct timeout for the,
the interaction
that two microservices are having.
And they will be different.
Okay.
So let's try out retries.
They're useful but they can be dangerous.
So you got to be careful here right.
What if I have a duplicate request.
And the first attempt actually succeeded?
It went through.
But on my retry, I did a retry.
I didn't wait on the timeout long enough.
How am I going to handle that?
I also have retry storms.
If I set my read time times too
short to short, I can overwhelm servers.
If you're scaling on the back end,
I can exhaust lots of resources.
There's also some hidden latency
in retries.
Every time I call a retry,
it can multiply.
The back end server
that's accepting those,
it can multiply the latency,
on responding.
So remember that if you are doing retries,
you should always pair them
with into potent operations.
Backoff strategies
and a maximum number of attempts.
So keep that in mind okay.
Let's talk about into potent
and safe retries.
Right. An operation is into potent.
If repeating it has the same effect
as running it once.
Now in the rest interface, get put
and patch are all into potent calls.
So if I call them over and over again,
I should get the same result
on the back end.
Service shouldn't really change
much of what's going on.
Even with a patch.
Should be the same patch as before.
A post, on the other hand,
is not into potent by default by I.
When I do a post,
I'm going to create something new.
All right, so if you have to have
good strategies on the server side
and also on the client side for
into potent operations to make them safe
use into potency keys, that's technique
where I specify individual ID
keys, for the post that I'm going in.
And then on the back end
I can store and do dedupe requests.
If it's the same requests coming through,
I can do that and say,
I've already accepted that request
and I can accept that post requests again.
So let you retry
without having duplication, side effects
okay.
Let's talk about backoff strategies.
So a backoff strategy remember it's
how much time I'm going to wait
before I retry.
And then how long am I going to do that
before I completely don't do it anymore?
There's a fixed backoff where I say, I'm
going to wait a certain amount of time
between retries,
and then I'm going to retry again.
There's a linear backoff
where I'm adding a little bit of time
to it, like, 100 milliseconds.
So at first is 200 milliseconds,
and the next time I retry, it's
going to be 300 milliseconds,
then 405 hundred
until I reach my maximum
number of retries.
Another one that seems to be
the most popular is a exponential backoff,
where I have 100, 200, 400, 800.
You get it.
And then sometimes I add a little jitter
in there where I do a random number.
So it's not as predictable.
Sometimes when you add
a little bit of chaos in the system,
it behaves a little bit better.
So it's not as predictable.
Okay.
Another important thing that you need
to do here is have a retry budget.
How many times
am I going to retry before I fail myself
and and tell
whoever called me, that, hey,
I can't do this operation
or in your logic,
you you handle those and say,
I'm just not going to
I'm not going to send that information.
I'm not going to ask for that. I'll do it
another way.
Whatever your strategy is,
you do need to have a maximum, retry.
And what are you going to do
when you retry?
Is exhausted when it fails.
Right.
You can do this on number of retry
or time limit.
Either one works pretty well.
And make sure that you implement
these retry budgets per client.
Per server.
It could you have to look at the behavior
between these servers
okay.
Circuit breaker.
Now circuit breaker is really cool
because let's say that I have
a, a client that failed
and I retried it five times.
Exponential. Back off. No problem.
And it failed.
Okay.
Well, all right, I handle that failure.
I do something else, I log it, whatever.
And then I have another one that fails
another request comes in.
It does the same thing.
Why would I keep doing that thing
over and over again?
So a circuit breaker says,
when I've reached a certain threshold, I'm
not going to even allow those calls
to the back end server anymore.
And now I log that in.
I can ask for some admin help.
Or maybe I send another
to another client client
to an admin server that says, hey,
this server appears to be down.
I'm not getting access to this anymore.
That could be your API gateway.
Even then, it can start doing things.
The idea here is that the
the calls will fail fast
until the dependency shines
shows sign of recovery.
So I'm not always swarming the network
with a whole bunch of retries that can
cause a lot of grief.
Okay, another
thing that you make sure that you do is
if you are doing retries
and how long you're waiting, log
those for observability.
So if I do have something monitoring
what's going on with my, microservice
architecture, I can make sure that I'm
getting everything that I need to in there
to make good decisions,
whether I need to scale automatically.
But maybe I need to like, restarts
some microservices
or whatever the case may be.
Okay,
so let's talk about a quick example here.
I've got a service
that calls a third party shipping API.
And in here I put a 500 millisecond,
which is the average, right.
I've seen some on third party
up to 2 or 3 seconds,
which you know that can happen as well.
Right.
So but every half a second I'm going to,
I'm going to I
if I don't you're back in a half a second,
I'm going to fail.
Right.
And then I'm going to try a retry
at that time.
All right.
And I'm going to do
an exponential back off with the jitter.
So I'm going to do 500 milliseconds.
Probably going to wait probably another
500 millisecond maybe only let's say
100 milliseconds, then 204 hundred and 800
with a little bit of a jitter,
a random number between 50 and -50,
something like that.
If the call succeeds
on the second attempt, we'll say it did.
Then the user,
if the.
So that's good news, right?
It it worked on the second attempt.
Let's say that it exhausted
completely the limit that I had.
Maybe it was ten.
Then the request fails and returns
A503 to the user.
Whoever called me, right, saying,
hey, I've got an internal problem
going on here.
Okay.
Key takeaways here.
Use timeout.
It helps prevent hanging in systems
and protects, system resources.
Retries can improve reliability,
but it must be controlled.
Right.
Have a good backoff strategy and jitter
to prevent any synchronized retry storms.
That that can happen into potency.
Make sure you understand that both
on the server side and the client side.
Make sure that you are in your retries.
Having a strategy
for not into potent calls.
And then also, use retry limits
so that you can fail.
Effectively,
up the chain if you need to.